<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_tdin">[Translation from Dante, 
                     Inferno Canto xxxiii 1-78]</title>
            <author corresp="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name xml:id="AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>
               <name type="institution" xml:id="SUB">Göttingen State and University Library, University of Göttingen</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Historic Building</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Papendiek 14</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>D-37073 Göttingen</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher xml:id="TGA">Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
               <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <email>info@thomasgray.org</email>
               </addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <ref target="http://www.thomasgray.org/">http://www.thomasgray.org/</ref>
               </addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Mitford's <emph>Note-book</emph></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This e-text is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>
								Spelling has been modernized throughout, except in case of conscious archaisms. 
								Contractions, italics and initial capitalization have been largely eliminated, 
								except where of real import. Obvious errors have been silently corrected, 
								punctuation has been supplied. 
							
						The editor would like to express his gratitude to the library staff of the
						<ref target="http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/" rend="newWindow">Göttingen State and 
							University Library (SUB Göttingen)</ref> for their invaluable assistance.
						</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCNAF">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition n="linegroups indented" xml:id="lgindent" scheme="css">text-indent: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="linegroups vertically spaced" xml:id="lgvspace" scheme="css">margin-bottom: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned centrally" xml:id="align-center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned right" xml:id="align-right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned left" xml:id="align-left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition n="inline" xml:id="inline" scheme="css">display: inline</rendition>
            <rendition n="italic" xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem"
              xml:id="txt_GrayTh1716_tdin"
              corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_tdin"
              subtype="eceptext"
              rendition="#lgindent"
              rhyme="none"
              met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+/"
              n="10"
              ana="#iamb #pentameter">
            <link type="author" target="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716"/>
            <head>[Translation from Dante, 
                     <emph>Inferno</emph> Canto xxxiii 1-78]</head>
            <lg>
               <l n="1">From his dire food the grisly felon raised</l>
               <l n="2">His gore-dyed lips, which on the clottered locks</l>
               <l n="3">Of the half-devoured head he wiped, and thus</l>
               <l n="4">Began: 'Would'st thou revive the deep despair,</l>
               <l n="5">The anguish, that, unuttered, natheless wrings</l>
               <l n="6">My inmost heart? Yet if the telling may</l>
               <l n="7">Beget the traitor's infamy, whom thus</l>
               <l n="8">I ceaseless gnaw insatiate, thou shalt see me</l>
               <l n="9">At once give loose to utterance and to tears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="10">'I know not who thou art nor on what errand</l>
               <l n="11">Sent hither; but a Florentine my ear,</l>
               <l n="12">Won by thy tongue, declares thee. Know, thou see'st</l>
               <l n="13">In me Count Ugolino, and Ruggieri,</l>
               <l n="14">Pisa's perfidious prelate, this: now hear</l>
               <l n="15">My wrongs and from them judge of my revenge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="16">'That I did trust him, that I was betrayed</l>
               <l n="17">By trusting, and by treachery slain, it recks not</l>
               <l n="18">That I advise thee; that which yet remains</l>
               <l n="19">To thee and all unknown (a horrid tale),</l>
               <l n="20">The bitterness of death, I shall unfold.</l>
               <l n="21">Attend, and say if he have injured me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="22">'Through a small crevice opening, what scant light</l>
               <l n="23">That grim and antique tower admitted (since</l>
               <l n="24">Of me the Tower of Famine hight, and known</l>
               <l n="25">To many a wretch) already 'gan the dawn</l>
               <l n="26">To send. The whilst I slumbering lay, a sleep</l>
               <l n="27">Prophetic of my woes with direful hand</l>
               <l n="28">Oped the dark veil of fate. I saw methought</l>
               <l n="29">Toward Pisa's mount, that intercepts the view</l>
               <l n="30">Of Lucca, chased by hell-hounds gaunt and bloody</l>
               <l n="31">A wolf full-grown; with fleet and equal speed</l>
               <l n="32">His young ones ran beside him. Lanfranc there</l>
               <l n="33">And Sigismundo and Gualandi rode</l>
               <l n="34">Amain, my deadly foes, headed by this</l>
               <l n="35">The deadliest: he their chief, the foremost he</l>
               <l n="36">Flashed to pursue and cheer the eager cry.</l>
               <l n="37">Nor long endured the chase: the panting sire,</l>
               <l n="38">Of strength bereft, his helpless offspring soon</l>
               <l n="39">O'erta'en beheld, and in their trembling flanks</l>
               <l n="40">The hungry pack their sharp-set fangs embrued.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="41">'The morn had scarce commenced when I awoke:</l>
               <l n="42">My children (they were with me) sleep as yet</l>
               <l n="43">Gave not to know their sum of misery,</l>
               <l n="44">But yet in low and uncompleted sounds</l>
               <l n="45">I heard 'em wail for bread. Oh! thou art cruel,</l>
               <l n="46">Or thou dost mourn to think what my poor heart</l>
               <l n="47">Foresaw, foreknew; oh! if thou weep not now,</l>
               <l n="48">Where are thy tears? Too soon they had aroused them,</l>
               <l n="49">Sad with the fears of sleep, and now the hour</l>
               <l n="50">Of timely food approached; when, at the gate</l>
               <l n="51">Below, I heard the dreadful clank of bars</l>
               <l n="52">And fastening bolts. Then on my children's eyes</l>
               <l n="53">Speechless my sight I fixed, nor wept, for all</l>
               <l n="54">Within was stone. They wept, unhappy boys,</l>
               <l n="55">They wept; and first my little dear Anselmo</l>
               <l n="56">Cried, 'Father, why do you gaze so sternly?</l>
               <l n="57">What would you have?' Yet wept I not or answered</l>
               <l n="58">All that whole day or the succeeding night,</l>
               <l n="59">Till a new sun arose with weakly gleam</l>
               <l n="60">And wan, such as mought entrance find within</l>
               <l n="61">That house of woe. But oh! when I beheld</l>
               <l n="62">My sons, and in four faces saw my own</l>
               <l n="63">Despair reflected, either hand I gnawed</l>
               <l n="64">For anguish, which they construed hunger. Straight</l>
               <l n="65">Arising all they cried, 'Far less shall be</l>
               <l n="66">Our sufferings, sir, if you resume your gift;</l>
               <l n="67">These miserable limbs with flesh you clothed;</l>
               <l n="68">Take back what once was yours.' I swallowed down</l>
               <l n="69">My struggling sorrow, nor to heighten theirs.</l>
               <l n="70">That day and yet another, mute we sat</l>
               <l n="71">And motionless. O earth, could'st thou not gape</l>
               <l n="72">Quick to devour me? Yet a fourth day came,</l>
               <l n="73">When Gaddo, at my feet outstretched, imploring</l>
               <l n="74">In vain my help, expired; ere the sixth morn</l>
               <l n="75">Had dawned, my other three before my eyes</l>
               <l n="76">Died one by one. I saw 'em fall; I heard</l>
               <l n="77">Their doleful cries. For three days more I groped</l>
               <l n="78">About among their cold remains (for then</l>
               <l n="79">Hunger had reft my eyesight), often calling</l>
               <l n="80">On their dear names, that heard me now no more;</l>
               <l n="81">The fourth, what sorrow could not, famine did.'</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="82">He finished; then with unrelenting eye</l>
               <l n="83">Askance he turned him, hasty to renew</l>
               <l n="84">The hellish feast, and rent his trembling prey.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
