<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_aleg">[The Alliance of Education and Government. A Fragment]</title>
            <author corresp="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name xml:id="AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>
               <name type="institution" xml:id="SUB">Göttingen State and University Library, University of Göttingen</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Historic Building</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Papendiek 14</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>D-37073 Göttingen</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher xml:id="TGA">Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
               <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <email>info@thomasgray.org</email>
               </addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <ref target="http://www.thomasgray.org/">http://www.thomasgray.org/</ref>
               </addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Commonplace Book</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This e-text is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>
								Spelling has been modernized throughout, except in case of conscious archaisms. 
								Contractions, italics and initial capitalization have been largely eliminated, 
								except where of real import. Obvious errors have been silently corrected, 
								punctuation has been supplied. 
							
						The editor would like to express his gratitude to the library staff of the
						<ref target="http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/" rend="newWindow">Göttingen State and 
							University Library (SUB Göttingen)</ref> for their invaluable assistance.
						</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCNAF">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition n="linegroups indented" xml:id="lgindent" scheme="css">text-indent: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="linegroups vertically spaced" xml:id="lgvspace" scheme="css">margin-bottom: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned centrally" xml:id="align-center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned right" xml:id="align-right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned left" xml:id="align-left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition n="inline" xml:id="inline" scheme="css">display: inline</rendition>
            <rendition n="italic" xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem"
              xml:id="txt_GrayTh1716_aleg"
              corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_aleg"
              subtype="eceptext"
              rendition="#lgindent"
              rhyme="aa"
              met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+/"
              n="10"
              ana="#iamb #pentameter #couplet #heroiccouplet">
            <link type="author" target="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716"/>
            <head>
               <emph>[The Alliance of Education and Government. A Fragment]</emph>
            </head>
            <head type="heading">Essay I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <p>
                  	                . . . 
                  	πόταγ᾽, ὦ 
                  	᾽γαθέ· τὰν 
                  	γὰρ ἀοιδάν<lb/>
                  		οὔτι πω εἰς 
                  		Ἀΐδαν γε τὸν 
                  		ἐκλελάθοντα 
                  		ϕυλαξεῖς.
                  </p>
               <bibl>
                  	Theoc[ritus, <emph>Idyll</emph> i. 62-63].
                  </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l n="1">As sickly plants betray a niggard earth,</l>
               <l n="2">Whose barren bosom starves her generous birth,</l>
               <l n="3">Nor genial warmth nor genial juice retains</l>
               <l n="4">Their roots to feed and fill their verdant veins;</l>
               <l n="5">And as in climes, where winter holds his reign,</l>
               <l n="6">The soil, though fertile, will not teem in vain,</l>
               <l n="7">Forbids her gems to swell, her shades to rise,</l>
               <l n="8">Nor trusts her blossoms to the churlish skies:</l>
               <l n="9">So draw mankind in vain the vital airs,</l>
               <l n="10">Unformed, unfriended, by those kindly cares</l>
               <l n="11">That health and vigour to the soul impart,</l>
               <l n="12">Spread the young thought and warm the opening heart.</l>
               <l n="13">So fond Instruction on the growing powers</l>
               <l n="14">Of nature idly lavishes her stores,</l>
               <l n="15">If equal Justice with unclouded face</l>
               <l n="16">Smile not indulgent on the rising race,</l>
               <l n="17">And scatter with a free though frugal hand</l>
               <l n="18">Light golden showers of plenty o'er the land:</l>
               <l n="19" rhyme="aaa" ana="#triplet">But Tyranny has fixed her empire there,</l>
               <l n="20" rhyme="aaa" ana="#triplet">To check their tender hopes with chilling fear,</l>
               <l n="21" rhyme="aaa" ana="#triplet">And blast the blooming promise of the year.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="22">This spacious animated scene survey</l>
               <l n="23">From where the rolling orb, that gives the day,</l>
               <l n="24">His sable sons with nearer course surrounds,</l>
               <l n="25">To either pole and life's remotest bounds.</l>
               <l n="26">How rude so e'er the exterior form we find,</l>
               <l n="27">Howe'er opinion tinge the varied mind,</l>
               <l n="28">Alike to all the kind impartial heaven</l>
               <l n="29">The sparks of truth and happiness has given:</l>
               <l n="30">With sense to feel, with memory to retain,</l>
               <l n="31">They follow pleasure and they fly from pain;</l>
               <l n="32">Their judgement mends the plan their fancy draws,</l>
               <l n="33">The event presages and explores the cause.</l>
               <l n="34">The soft returns of gratitude they know,</l>
               <l n="35">By fraud elude, by force repel the foe;</l>
               <l n="36">While mutual wishes, mutual woes, endear</l>
               <l n="37">The social smile and sympathetic tear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="38">Say then, through ages by what fate confined</l>
               <l n="39">To different climes seem different souls assigned?</l>
               <l n="40">Here measured laws and philosophic ease</l>
               <l n="41">Fix and improve the polished arts of peace.</l>
               <l n="42">There Industry and Gain their vigils keep,</l>
               <l n="43">Command the winds and tame the unwilling deep.</l>
               <l n="44">Here force and hardy deeds of blood prevail;</l>
               <l n="45">There languid pleasure sighs in every gale.</l>
               <l n="46">Oft o'er the trembling nations from afar</l>
               <l n="47">Has Scythia breathed the living cloud of war;</l>
               <l n="48">And, where the deluge burst, with sweepy sway</l>
               <l n="49">Their arms, their kings, their gods were rolled away.</l>
               <l n="50">As oft have issued, host impelling host,</l>
               <l n="51">The blue-eyed myriads from the Baltic coast.</l>
               <l n="52">The prostrate south to the destroyer yields</l>
               <l n="53">Her boasted titles and her golden fields:</l>
               <l n="54">With grim delight the brood of winter view</l>
               <l n="55">A brighter day and heavens of azure hue,</l>
               <l n="56">Scent the new fragrance of the breathing rose,</l>
               <l n="57">And quaff the pendent vintage, as it grows.</l>
               <l n="58">Proud of the yoke and pliant to the rod,</l>
               <l n="59">Why yet does Asia dread a monarch's nod,</l>
               <l n="60">While European freedom still withstands</l>
               <l n="61">The encroaching tide, that drowns her lessening lands,</l>
               <l n="62">And sees far off with an indignant groan</l>
               <l n="63">Her native plains and empires once her own?</l>
               <l n="64">Can opener skies and suns of fiercer flame</l>
               <l n="65">O'erpower the fire that animates our frame,</l>
               <l n="66">As lamps, that shed at even a cheerful ray,</l>
               <l n="67">Fade and expire beneath the eye of day?</l>
               <l n="68">Need we the influence of the northern star</l>
               <l n="69">To string our nerves and steel our hearts to war?</l>
               <l n="70">And, where the face of nature laughs around,</l>
               <l n="71">Must sickening Virtue fly the tainted ground?</l>
               <l n="72">Unmanly thought! what seasons can control,</l>
               <l n="73">What fancied zone can circumscribe the Soul,</l>
               <l n="74">Who, conscious of the source from whence she springs,</l>
               <l n="75">By Reason's light on Resolution's wings,</l>
               <l n="76">Spite of her frail companion, dauntless goes</l>
               <l n="77">O'er Libya's deserts and through Zembla's snows?</l>
               <l n="78">She bids each slumbering energy awake,</l>
               <l n="79">Another touch, another temper take,</l>
               <l n="80">Suspends the inferior laws that rule our clay:</l>
               <l n="81">The stubborn elements confess her sway;</l>
               <l n="82">Their little wants, their low desires, refine,</l>
               <l n="83">And raise the mortal to a height divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="84">Not but the human fabric from the birth</l>
               <l n="85">Imbibes a flavour of its parent earth:</l>
               <l n="86">As various tracts enforce a various toil,</l>
               <l n="87">The manners speak the idiom of their soil.</l>
               <l n="88">An iron-race the mountain-cliffs maintain,</l>
               <l n="89">Foes to the gentler genius of the plain:</l>
               <l n="90">For where unwearied sinews must be found</l>
               <l n="91">With sidelong plough to quell the flinty ground,</l>
               <l n="92">To turn the torrent's swift-descending flood,</l>
               <l n="93">To brave the savage rushing from the wood,</l>
               <l n="94">What wonder if, to patient valour trained,</l>
               <l n="95">They guard with spirit what by strength they gained;</l>
               <l n="96">And while their rocky ramparts round they see,</l>
               <l n="97">The rough abode of want and liberty,</l>
               <l n="98">(As lawless force from confidence will grow)</l>
               <l n="99">Insult the plenty of the vales below?</l>
               <l n="100">What wonder in the sultry climes, that spread</l>
               <l n="101">Where Nile redundant o'er his summer-bed</l>
               <l n="102">From his broad bosom life and verdure flings,</l>
               <l n="103">And broods o'er Egypt with his watery wings,</l>
               <l n="104">If with adventurous oar and ready sail,</l>
               <l n="105">The dusky people drive before the gale,</l>
               <l n="106">Or on frail floats to distant cities ride,</l>
               <l n="107">That rise and glitter o'er the ambient tide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
