<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_chcc">The Characters of the Christ-Cross Row, By a Critic, To Mrs —</title>
            <author corresp="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name xml:id="AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>
               <name type="institution" xml:id="SUB">Göttingen State and University Library, University of Göttingen</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Historic Building</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Papendiek 14</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>D-37073 Göttingen</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher xml:id="TGA">Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
               <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <email>info@thomasgray.org</email>
               </addrLine>
               <addrLine>
                  <ref target="http://www.thomasgray.org/">http://www.thomasgray.org/</ref>
               </addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>1843 (Mitford)</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This e-text is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>
								Spelling has been modernized throughout, except in case of conscious archaisms. 
								Contractions, italics and initial capitalization have been largely eliminated, 
								except where of real import. Obvious errors have been silently corrected, 
								punctuation has been supplied. 
							
						The editor would like to express his gratitude to the library staff of the
						<ref target="http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/" rend="newWindow">Göttingen State and 
							University Library (SUB Göttingen)</ref> for their invaluable assistance.
						</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCNAF">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition n="linegroups indented" xml:id="lgindent" scheme="css">text-indent: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="linegroups vertically spaced" xml:id="lgvspace" scheme="css">margin-bottom: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned centrally" xml:id="align-center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned right" xml:id="align-right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition n="aligned left" xml:id="align-left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition n="inline" xml:id="inline" scheme="css">display: inline</rendition>
            <rendition n="italic" xml:id="i" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="poem"
              xml:id="txt_GrayTh1716_chcc"
              corresp="authors.xml#txt_GrayTh1716_chcc"
              subtype="eceptext"
              rendition="#lgvspace"
              rhyme="aa"
              met="-+|-+|-+|-+|-+/"
              n="10"
              ana="#iamb #pentameter #couplet">
            <link type="author" target="authors.xml#aut_GrayTh1716"/>
            <head>The Characters of the Christ-Cross Row, By a Critic, To Mrs —</head>
            <lg>
               <l n="1">Great D draws near---the Duchess sure is come,</l>
               <l n="2">Open the doors of the withdrawing-room:</l>
               <l n="3">Her daughters decked most daintily I see,</l>
               <l n="4">The dowager grows a perfect double D.</l>
               <l n="5">E enters next and with her Eve appears.</l>
               <l n="6">Not like yon dowager depressed with years:</l>
               <l n="7">What ease and elegance her person grace,</l>
               <l n="8">Bright beaming as the evening-star her face.</l>
               <l n="9">Queen Esther next---how fair e'en after death;</l>
               <l n="10">Then one faint glimpse of Queen Elizabeth;</l>
               <l n="11">No more, our Esthers now are nought but Hetties,</l>
               <l n="12">Elizabeths all dwindled into Betties.</l>
               <l n="13">In vain you think to find them under E,</l>
               <l n="14">They're all diverted into H and B.</l>
               <l n="15">F follows fast the fair---and in his rear</l>
               <l n="16">See folly, fashion, foppery straight appear,</l>
               <l n="17">All with fantastic clues, fantastic clothes,</l>
               <l n="18">With fans and flounces, fringe and furbelows.</l>
               <l n="19">Here Grub-street geese presume to joke and jeer,</l>
               <l n="20">All, all but Grannam Osborne's
            <emph>Gazetteer</emph>.</l>
               <l n="21">High heaves his hugeness H: methinks we see</l>
               <l n="22">Henry the Eighth's most monstrous majesty.</l>
               <l n="23">But why on such
            <emph>mock</emph> grandeur should we dwell?</l>
               <l n="24">H mounts to heaven and H descends to hell.</l>
               <l n="25">As H the Hebrew found, so I the Jew:</l>
               <l n="26">See Isaac, Joseph, Jacob pass in view.</l>
               <l n="27">The walls of old Jerusalem appear,</l>
               <l n="28">See Israel and all Judah thronging there. [...]</l>
               <l n="29">P pokes his head out, yet has not a pain:</l>
               <l n="30">Like Punch he peeps, but soon pops in again.</l>
               <l n="31">Pleased with his pranks, the pisgys calls him Puck,</l>
               <l n="32">Mortals he loves to prick and pinch and pluck.</l>
               <l n="33">Now a pert prig, he perks upon your face;</l>
               <l n="34">Now peers, pores, ponders with profound grimace;</l>
               <l n="35">Now a proud prince, in pompous purple dressed,</l>
               <l n="36">And now a player, a peer, a pimp or priest,</l>
               <l n="37">A pea, a pin, in a perpetual round,</l>
               <l n="38">Now seems a penny, and now shows a pound.</l>
               <l n="39">Like perch or pike in pond you see him come;</l>
               <l n="40">He in plantations hangs like pear or plum,</l>
               <l n="41">Pippin or peach, then perches on the spray,</l>
               <l n="42">In form of parrot, pye or popinjay.</l>
               <l n="43">P, Proteus-like, all tricks, all shapes can show,</l>
               <l n="44">The pleasantest person in the Christ-cross Row. [...]</l>
               <l n="45">As K a king, Q represents a queen,</l>
               <l n="46">And seems small difference the sounds between.</l>
               <l n="47">K as a man with hoarser accent speaks;</l>
               <l n="48">In shriller notes Q like a female squeaks.</l>
               <l n="49">Behold, K struts as might a king become;</l>
               <l n="50">Q draws her train along the drawing-room.</l>
               <l n="51">Slow follow all the quality of state:</l>
               <l n="52">Queer Queensberry only does refuse to wait. [...]</l>
               <l n="53">Thus great R reigns in town, while different far,</l>
               <l n="54">Rests in retirement
            <emph>little</emph> rural R;</l>
               <l n="55">Remote from cities lives in lone retreat,</l>
               <l n="56">With rooks and rabbit-burrows round his seat.</l>
               <l n="57">S sails the swan slow down the silver stream. [...]</l>
               <l n="58">So, big with weddings, waddles W,</l>
               <l n="59">And brings all womankind before your view:</l>
               <l n="60">A wench, a wife, a widow and a w[hor]e,</l>
               <l n="61">With woe behind and wantonness before.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
