<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (18 December 1750)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 43-44</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">186 mm x 113 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 156, vol. i, 334-340
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=156</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xiv, section iv, 221
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:221</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 173-174
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:173</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XCVIII, vol. i, 220-222
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:220</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXXIII, vol. ii, 227-229
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:227</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XL, vol. iii, 98-101
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:98</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXV, vol. i, 160-161
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:160</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XIV, vol. i, 331-332
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:331</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0177">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1750-12-18"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Brown, James, 1709-1784</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Speed, Henrietta Jane, 1728-1783</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">A Long Story</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Voltaire</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Montesquieu</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mercure Historique</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Frederick the Great</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Fleury, Joly de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Buffon, Comte de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bargelon, Daniel</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Wanstead, Gray's house at</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Stoke Poges</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0177">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>My dear Wharton</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You are apprised by this time (I don't doubt) that your Mr Spencer is chose at Pembroke. I
					received, while I was at Stoke, a Letter from [Tuthill], wherein were these Words 'Spencer will, I am
					almost persuaded, be chose at this Audit, &amp; perhaps without a Quarrel. I shall vote for him with great Pleasure, because I believe
					he may justly claim it, &amp; because I believe Dr Wharton would, if he knew of our Election, desire it, for <hi rend="italic">he</hi>
					was maintain'd by his Mr Wilkinson.' Dr Long did not make any Resistance, when he saw how it would
					go, so Chapman had little Occasion for his <hi rend="italic">effectual Interest.</hi> oh, by the Way
					I give you joy of that agreeable Creature, who has got one of your Prebends of 400Â£ a Year, &amp;
					will visit you soon, with that dry Piece of Goods, his Wife.
				</p>
         <p>Of my House I can not say much: I wish I could! but for my Heart it is no less yours than it has
					long been; &amp; the last Thing in the World, that will throw it into Tumults, is a fine Lady. the
						Verses you so kindly try to keep in countenance were wrote to divert that particular Family, &amp;
					succeeded accordingly. but, being shew'd about in Town, are not liked there at all. Mrs French, a
					very fashionable Personage, told Mr W: that she had seen a Thing by a Friend of his, wch she did not know what to make of, for it aim'd
					at every Thing, &amp; meant nothing. to wch he replied, that he had always taken her for a Woman of Sense, &amp; was very sorry to be
					undeceived. On the other hand the Stanza's, wch I now enclose to you, have had the Misfortune by Mr
					W:s Fault to be made still more publick, for wch they certainly were never meant, but it is too late
					to complain. they have been so applauded, it is quite a Shame to repeat it. I mean not to be modest; but I mean, it is a Shame for
					those, who have said such superlative Things about them, that I can't repeat them. I should have been glad, that you &amp; two or three
					more People had liked them, wch would have satisfied my ambition on this Head amply. I have been this Month in town, not at
					Newcastle-House, but diverting myself among my gay Acquaintance; &amp; return to my Cell with so much the more Pleasure. I dare not
					speak of my future Excursion to Durham for fear â&#x80;&#x93; but at present it is my full Intention.</p>
         <p>His Prussian Majesty has published the <hi rend="italic">Suite des Memoires</hi>
					 pour servir a l'Histoire de la Maison de Brandebourg, wch includes a very free Account of his
						Grandfather's Life, who was the first King of that House, Reflections on the gradual Advance in
					Science, Commerce, &amp;c: of his Subjects, &amp; on their Changes in Religion. it is much in Voltaire's Manner. the Book itself is at present hard to be got, but you may see a good Extract of it in the Mercure
						historique, a Work publish'd monthly: whether it is that for Oct: or Sept:r I can not justly say.
					there is also an Account of the History of Crusades, wch seem's to be Voltaire's, &amp; promises
					well. I hear talk of a Pamphlet, call'd, Voix du Sage &amp; du Peuple, ascribed to Montesquieu; &amp;
					a Book, styled only <hi rend="italic">Lettres,</hi> by the Procureur General, Fleury, on the Power of
					the Clergy in France, but have not seen either of them, being very scarce as yet. Mr de Buffon has
					discover'd the Speculum of Archimedes, wch burns at 200 Foot distance; and a Chymist in</p>
         <p>[ ]</p>
         <p>You mention Stonhewer. I should be glad to know whether he frequents you? whether you find him improved? &amp; what sort of Life he
					leads among your Country-folks? Brown, who has been in the midst of Tumults &amp; Mutinies
						lately [and Tuthill, desire their] best Compliments to you. mine
					ever wait on Mrs Wharton.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, believe me<lb/> Most truly Yours. </salute>
            <dateline>Dec: 18. Cambridge.</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <q>
               <p>ELEGY, WRITTEN IN A COUNTRY-CHURCHYARD </p>
               <p>The Curfeu tolls the Knell of parting Day, <lb/> The lowing Herd wind slowly o'er the Lea, <lb/> The Ploughman homeward plods his
							weary Way, <lb/> And leaves the World to Darkness &amp; to me. <lb/> Now fades the glimm'ring Landscape on the Sight, <lb/> And
							all the Air a solemn Stillness holds: <lb/> Save where the Beetle wheels his droning Flight, <lb/> Or drowsy Tinkleings lull the
							distant Folds: <lb/> Save that from yonder ivy-mantled Tower <lb/> The mopeing Owl does to the Moon complain <lb/> Of such, as
							wand'ring near her secret Bower <lb/> Molest her ancient solitary Reign. <lb/> Beneath those rugged Elms, that Yewtree's Shade,
							<lb/> Where heaves the Turf in many a mould'ring Heap, <lb/> Each in his narrow Cell for ever laid, <lb/> The rude Forefathers of
							the Hamlet sleep. <lb/> The breezy Call of incense-breathing Morn, <lb/> The Swallow twitt'ring from the straw-built Shed, <lb/>
							The Cock's shrill Clarion, &amp; the ecchoing Horn, <lb/> No more shall rowse them from their lowly Bed. <lb/> For them no more the
							blazing Hearth shall burn, <lb/> Or busy Huswife ply her Evening Care. <lb/> No Children run to lisp their Sire's Return, <lb/>
							Nor climb his Knees the envied Kiss to share. <lb/> Oft did the Harvest to their Sickles yield, <lb/> Their Furrow oft the stubborn
							Glebe has broke, <lb/> How jocund did they drive their Team a-field! <lb/> How bow'd the Woods beneath their sturdy Stroke! <lb/>
							Let not Ambition mock their useful Toil, <lb/> Their homely Joys, &amp; Destiny obscure; <lb/> Nor Grandeur hear with a disdainful
							Smile <lb/> The short &amp; simple Annals of the Poor. <lb/> The Boast of Heraldry, the Pomp of Power, <lb/> And all that Beauty,
							all that Wealth e'er gave, <lb/> Awaits alike th' inevitable Hour. <lb/> The Paths of Glory lead but to the Grave. <lb/> Forgive,
							ye Proud, th' involuntary Fault, <lb/> If Memory to These no Trophies raise, <lb/> Where thro' the long-drawn Ile &amp; fretted
							Vault <lb/> The pealing Anthem swells the Note of Praise. <lb/> Can storied Urn or animated Bust <lb/> Back to its Mansion call
							the fleeting Breath? <lb/> Can Honour's Voice provoke the silent Dust, <lb/> Or Flatt'ry sooth the dull cold Ear of Death? <lb/>
							Perhaps in this neglected Spot is laid <lb/> Some Heart, once pregnant with celestial Fire, <lb/> Hands, that the Reins of Empire
							might have sway'd, <lb/> Or waked to Extasy the living Lyre; <lb/> But Knowledge to their Eyes her ample Page <lb/> Rich with the
							Spoils of Time did ne'er unroll: <lb/> Chill Penury repress'd their noble Rage, <lb/> And froze the genial Current of the Soul.
							<lb/> Full many a Gem of purest Ray serene <lb/> The dark unfathom'd Caves of Ocean bear: <lb/> Full many a Flower is born to
							blush unseen, <lb/> And wast it's Sweetness on the desert Air. <lb/> Some Village-Hambden, that with dauntless Breast <lb/> The
							little Tyrant of his Fields withstood, <lb/> Some mute inglorious Milton here may rest, <lb/> Some Cromwell, guiltless of his
							Country's Blood. <lb/> Th' Applause of list'ning Senates to command, <lb/> The Threats of Pain &amp; Ruin to despise, <lb/> To
							scatter Plenty o'er a smiling Land, <lb/> And read their Hist'ry in a Nation's Eyes, <lb/> Their Lot forbad: nor circumscribed
							alone <lb/> Their growing Virtues, but their Crimes confined; <lb/> Forbad to wade thro' Slaughter to a Throne, <lb/> Or shut the
							Gates of Mercy on Mankind, <lb/> The struggling Pangs of conscious Truth to hide, <lb/> To quench the Blushes of ingenuous Shame,
							<lb/> Or heap the Shrines of Luxury &amp; Pride <lb/> With Incense, kindled at the Muse's Flame. <lb/> Far from the madding
							Crowd's ignoble Strife, <lb/> Their sober Wishes never learn'd to stray: <lb/> Along the cool sequester'd Vale of Life <lb/> They
							kept the noiseless Tenour of their Way. <lb/> Yet ev'n these Bones from Insult to protect <lb/> Some frail Memorial still erected
							nigh, <lb/> With uncouth Rhymes &amp; shapeless Sculpture deck'd, <lb/> Implores the passing Tribute of a Sigh. <lb/> Their Name,
							their years, spell'd by th' unletter'd Muse, <lb/> The Place of Fame &amp; Elegy supply; <lb/> And many a holy Text around She
							strews <lb/> That teach the rustic Moralist to die. <lb/> For who to dumb Forgetfulness a Prey <lb/> This pleasing anxious Being
							e'er resign'd, <lb/> Left the warm Precincts of the chearful Day, <lb/> Nor cast one longing lingering Look behind? <lb/> On some
							fond Breast the parting Soul relies, <lb/> Some pious Drops the closing Eye requires: <lb/> Ev'n from the Tomb the Voice of Nature
							cries, <lb/> And in our Ashes glow their wonted Fires. <lb/> For Thee, who mindful of th' unhonour'd Dead <lb/> Dost in these
							Lines their artless Tale relate, <lb/> If chance by lonely Contemplation led <lb/> Some kindred Spirit shall enquire thy Fate;
							<lb/> Haply some hoary-headed Swain may say, <lb/> 'Oft have we seen him at the Peep of Dawn <lb/> 'Brushing with hasty Steps the
							Dews away <lb/> 'To meet the Sun upon the upland Lawn. <lb/> 'There, at the Foot of yonder nodding Beech, <lb/> 'That wreathes its
							old fantastic Roots so high <lb/> 'His listless Length at Noontide would he stretch <lb/> 'And pore upon the Brook, that babbles
							by. <lb/> 'Hard by yon Wood, now smiling as in Scorn <lb/> 'Mutt'ring his wayward Fancies would he rove <lb/> 'Now drooping
							woeful-wan, like one forlorn, <lb/> 'Or crazed with Care, or cross'd in hopeless Love. <lb/> 'One Morn I miss'd him on the custom'd
							Hill, <lb/> 'Along the Heath, &amp; near his fav'rite Tree: <lb/> 'Another came, nor yet beside the Rill, <lb/> 'Nor up the Lawn,
							nor at the Wood was he. <lb/> 'The next with Dirges due in sad Array <lb/> 'Slow thro' the Churchway-Path we saw him born. <lb/>
							'Approach &amp; Read, for thou canst read, the Lay <lb/> 'Graved on the Stone beneath yon aged Thorn. </p>
               <p>Epitaph. </p>
               <p>Here rests his Head upon the Lap of Earth <lb/> A Youth, to Fortune &amp; to Fame unknown: <lb/> Fair Science frown'd not on his
							humble Birth, <lb/> And Melancholy mark'd him for her own. <lb/> Large was his Bounty &amp; his Soul sincere, <lb/> Heaven did a
							Recompence as largely send: <lb/> He gave to Misery all he had, a Tear; <lb/> He gain'd from Heav'n ('twas all he wish'd) a Friend.
							<lb/> No farther seek his Merits to disclose, <lb/> Or draw his Frailties from their dread Abode, <lb/> (There they alike in
							trembling Hope repose) <lb/> The Bosom of his Father &amp; his God. </p>
            </q>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
