<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (5 March 1766)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 172-173</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">227 mm x 190 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 420, vol. iii, 919-923
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=420</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter lii, section iv, 320-321
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:320</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXI, vol. iii, 100-105
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:100</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXVI, vol. ii, 468-472
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:468</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXXVII, vol. iv, 74-80
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:74</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXVII, vol. ii, 101-102
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:101</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LII, vol. i, 420-421
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:420</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0475">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1766-03-05"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0475">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Wharton M:D: at</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Old-Park near Darlington</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>March 5. 1766. Pemb: C: </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I am amazed at myself, when I think I have never wrote to you: to be sure it is the sin of witchcraft
					or something worse. something indeed might be said for it, had I been married like Mason, who (for the first time since that great
					event) has just thought fit to tell me, that he never pass'd so happy a winter as the last, &amp; this in spite of his anxieties, wch
					perhaps (he says) might even make a part of his happiness: for his Wife is by no means in health, she has a constant cough, yet he is
					assured, her lungs are not affected, &amp; that it is nothing of the consumptive kind. what say you to this case? may I flatter him,
					that breeding will be a cure for this disorder? if so, I hear she is in a fair way to be well. as to me I have been neither happy, nor
					miserable: but in a gentle stupefaction of mind, &amp; very tolerable health of body hitherto. if they last, I shall not much complain.
					the accounts one has lately had from all parts make me suppose you buried under the snow, like the old
					Queen of Denmark: as soon as you are dug out, I should rejoice to hear your voice from the battlements
					of Old-Park. the greatest cold we have felt here was Jan: 2, Thermom: (in the garden) at 4 in the afternoon standing at 30 Deg: ½, and
					next day fell a little snow, wch did not lie. it was the first we had had during the winter. again, Feb: 5 toward night, Therm: was
					down at 30 D: with a clear sky; the snow-drops then beginning to blow in the garden: next day was a little snow. but on the 11th &amp;
					12th fell a deep snow (the weather not very cold) wch however was melted on ye 15th, &amp; made a flood in the river. next day the
					Thrush was singing, &amp; the Rooks building. at &amp; about London instead of snow they had heavy rains. on the 19th the red Hepatica
					blew, &amp; next day the Primrose. the Crocus is now in full bloom. so ends my chronicle. </p>
				     <p>My oracle of state (who now &amp; then utters a little, as far as he may with discretion) is a very
					slave &amp; pack-horse, that never breaths any air better than that of London, except like an Apprentice, on Sundays with his
						Master and Co:. however he is in health, &amp; a very good Boy. it is strange, the turn that things
					have taken. that the late Ministry should negociate a reconciliation with Ld B:, &amp; that Ld Temple
					should join them; that they should after making their (bad) apologies be received with a gracious kind of contempt, &amp; told that his
					Ldp: could enter into no political connections with them: that on the first division on the American business that happen'd in the H: of Lords they should however all join to carry a point against the Ministry by a
					majority indeed of four only, but the D: of Y–k present &amp; making one: that when the
					Ministers expostulated in a proper place, they should be seriously assured the K: would support them. that on a division on an
					insignificant point to try their strength in the H: of Commons they should again lose it by 12 majority: that they should persist
					nevertheless: that Mr Pitt should appear <hi rend="italic">tanquam e machinâ,</hi> speak for 3 hours &amp; ½, &amp; assert the rights
					of the Colonies in their greatest latitude: that the Minister should
					profess himself ready to act with &amp; even serve under him: that he should receive such a compliment with coldness, &amp; a sort of
					derision: that Norton should move to send him to the Tower: that when the great questions came on, the
					Miny: should always carry their point at one, two, three in the morning by majorities of 110 &amp; 170 (Mr Pitt entirely concurring
					with them, &amp; the Tories, People of the Court, &amp; many Placemen, even Ld G: Sackville, constantly
					voting against them) all these events are unaccountable on any principles of common-sense. I attribute much of the singular part to the
					interposition of <hi rend="italic">Women</hi>
					 as rash as they are foolish. on Monday (I do not doubt, tho' as yet I
					do not certainly know it) the Bill to repeal the Stamp-act went thro' that House, &amp; to-day it is before the Lords, who surely will
					not venture to throw it out. oh, that they would!–but after this important business is well
					over, there must be an eclaircissement: some amends must be made &amp; some gracious condescensions insisted on, or else who would go
					on, that really means to serve his country! The D: of Bedford &amp; Ld Temple were gone down to their Villas, &amp; I believe are not
					likely to come back. Ld Chesterfield, who had not been for many years at the house, came the other day to qualify himself in order to
					leave a proxy, that should vote with the Ministry. some body (I thought) made no bad application of
					those lines in Virgil L: 6. v: 489 <q>
						         <p>At Danaum proceres, Agamemnoniæq phalanges &amp;c:</p>
					       </q> to Mr Pitt's first appearance (for no one expected him) in the house. turn to the place.
				</p>
				     <p>Every thing is politicks. there are no literary productions worth your notice, at least of our country. the French have finish'd
					their great Encyclopedie in 17 Volumes: but there are many flimsey
					articles very hastily treated, &amp; great incorrectness of the Press. there are now 13 Vol: of Buffon's Natural History, &amp; he is not come to the Monkies yet, who are a very numerous people. the Life of Petrarch has entertain'd
					me: it is not well written, but very curious &amp; laid together from his own letters &amp; the original writings of the 14th Century:
					so that it takes in much of the history of those obscure times, &amp; the characters of many remarkable persons. there are 2 vols: 4to,
					&amp; another (unpublish'd yet) that will compleat it.
				</p>
				     <p>Mr W: writes me now &amp; then a long and lively letter from Paris, to wch place he went the last
					summer with the gout upon him sometimes in his limbs, often in his stomach &amp; head. he has got somehow well (not by means of the
					climate, one would think) goes to all publick places, sees all the best company &amp; is very much in fashion. he says, he sunk like
					Queen Eleanour at Charing-Cross, &amp; has risen again at Paris. he returns again in April: but his
					health is certainly in a deplorable state. Mad: de la Perriere is come over from the Hague to be
					Ministress at London. her Father-in-law Viry is now first Minister at Turin. I sate a morning with her
					before I left London. she is a prodigious fine Lady, &amp; a Catholick
					 (tho' she did not expressly own it to me) not fatter than she was: she had a cage of foreign birds
					&amp; a piping Bullfinch at her elbow, two little Dogs on a cushion in her lap, a Cockatoo on her shoulder, &amp; a sl[ight] suspicion of Rouge on her cheeks. They were all exceeding glad to [see] me,
					&amp; I them.</p>
				     <p>Pray tell me the history of your winter, &amp; present my respects to Mrs Wharton. I hope Miss Wharton &amp; Miss Peggy with the
					assistance of Sister Betty make a great progress in Natural History: recommend me to all their good
					graces, &amp; believe me ever</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Truly Yours </salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>If you chance to see or send to Mr &amp; Mrs Leighton, I will trouble you to make my compliments: I
						have never received the box of shells, tho' possibly it may wait for me at Mr Jonathan's in Town, where I shall be in April. Mr Brown
						is well &amp; desires to be remember'd to you &amp; Mrs Wharton. I have just heard, there are like to be warm debates in the house of
						Lords, but that the Ministry will undoubtedly carry it in spite of them all. they say, Ld
							Cambden will soon be Chancellour.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
