<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (1 March 1759)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 291, vol. ii, 617-618
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=291</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XLIII, 176-179
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:176</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 225-226
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:225</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXXV, vol. ii, 78-81
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:78</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0336">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1759-03-01"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0336">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Cambridge. March 1. 1759 </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Did I tell you I had been confined in Town with the Gout for a fortnight? well, &amp; since I came hither, it is come again. yesterday I came abroad again for the first time in a great shoe, &amp; very much out of
					humour; and so I must return again in three days to town about <hi rend="italic">business,</hi> wch is not like to add much to the
					sweetness of my temper, especially while Stocks are so low.</p>
				     <p>I did not remember ever to have seen the joint-criticism from Prior-park, that you speak of; so little impression did it make: nor
					should I believe now, that I had ever seen it, did I not recollect, what a prejudice the Parsons
					express'd to human sacrifice, wch is quite agreeable to my way of thinking, since Caractacus convinced me of the propriety of the
					thing. it is certain, that their fancies did in no sort influence me in the use of my Tomahawk. now you must know, I do not much admire
					the Chorus of ye <hi rend="italic">rocking-stone,</hi> nor yet much disapprove it. it is grave &amp; solemn and may pass. I insist
					however, that <hi rend="italic">deigns</hi> (tho' it be a rhyme) should be <hi rend="italic">deign'st,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">fills fill'st,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">bids bid'st.</hi> do not blame me, but the English Tongue. the beginning of the
					Antistrophe is good: I do not like <q>
						         <p>
							           <hi rend="italic">mæandring</hi> way,<lb/> Where <hi rend="italic">Vice</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Folly</hi> stray.</p>
            </q> nor
					the word <hi rend="italic">sprite.</hi> the beginning too of ye Epode is well, but you have used the epithet <hi rend="italic">pale</hi> before in a sense somewhat similar &amp; I do not love repetitions. the line <hi rend="italic">Or magic numbers</hi>
					interrupts the run of ye Stanza, &amp; lets the measure drop too short. there is no beauty in repeating <hi rend="italic">ponderous
						sphere.</hi> the two last lines are the best.</p>
				     <p>The sense of your simile about the distant thunder is not clear, nor well-expressed: besides it implies too strong a confession of
					guilt.</p>
				     <p>The Stanza you sent me for ye 2d Ode is very rude, &amp; neither the Idea, nor verses touch me much.
					it is not the Gout, that makes me thus difficult, finish but your <hi rend="italic">Death-Song</hi> as well as you imagined &amp; begun
					it; &amp; mind, if I won't be more pleased than any body </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, dear Mason, I am ever<lb/> Truly Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Did I tell you, how well I liked Whithead's two Odes? they are far better than any thing he ever
						wrote.</p>
					       <p>Mr Brown &amp; Jemmy Bickham lament your indolence, as to the degree, in Chorus. as to me, I should
						have done just so for all the World.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
