<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (24 March 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 269, vol. ii, 567-569
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=269</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXXIV, 144-147
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:144</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section iv, 257-258
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:257</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 206-208
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:206</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXV, vol. ii, 26-29
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:26</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0311">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1758-03-24"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Hurd, Richard, 1720-1808</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Stukeley, Dr. William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Shenstone, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mallet, Paul Henri</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hurd, Dr. Richard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Fréret, Nicholas</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Fénel, Jean-Baptiste</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Akenside, Dr. Mark</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0311">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have full as much <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi> as yourself, tho' much less dissipation, but I can not make this my excuse for being
					silent, for I write to you <hi rend="italic">pour me desennuyer,</hi> tho' I have little enough to say. I know not, whether I am to
					condole with you on this Canterbury Business, for it is not clear to me, that You or the Church are
					any great Losers by it. if you are; be so good to inform me, &amp; I will be sorry. however there is one good thing in it: it proves
					the Family are mortal.</p>
         <p>You do not seem to discover, that Mons: Mallet is but a very small Scholar, except in the erudition
					of the Goths. there are a-propos two Dissertations on the Religion &amp; Opinions of the Gauls, publish'd in the <hi rend="italic">Memoires de l'Acad. des Belles-Lettres &amp; des Inscriptions,</hi> Vol. 24me. 4to. one by the Abbé
						Fenel, in wch he would shew, that about Tiberius, and Claudius times the Druids, persecuted &amp;
					dispersed by the Romans, probably retired into Germany &amp; propagated their doctrines there. this is to account for some similitude
					to the Gaulish notions wch the religion of Germany seems to bear, as Tacitus has described it, whereas J: Cæsar makes them extremely
					different, who lived before this supposed dispersion of ye Druids. the other by Mons:r Freret is to
					shew the reverse of all this, that there was no such dispersion, no such similitude, and that if Cæsar &amp; Tacitus disagree, it is
					because the first knew nothing but of those Nations that border'd on the Rhine, &amp; the other was acquainted with all Germany. I do
					not know, whether these will furnish you with any new matter, but they are well enough wrote &amp; easily read. I told you before (that
					in a time of dearth) I would venture to borrow from the Edda without entering too minutely on particulars: but if I did so, I would
					make each image so clear, that it might be fully understood by itself, for in this obscure mythology we must not hint at things, as we
					do with the Greek Fables, that every body is supposed to know at school. however on second thoughts I think it would be still better to
					graft any wild picturesque fable absolutely of one's own invention upon the Druid-Stock, I mean upon those half-dozen of old fancies,
					that are known to have made their system. this will give you more freedom &amp; latitude, &amp; will leave no hold for the Criticks to
					fasten on.</p>
         <p>Pray, when did I pretend to finish, or even insert passages into other people's works? as if it were equally easy to pick holes,
					&amp; to mend them. all I can say is, that your elegy must not end with the worst line in it. it is
					flat, it is prose, whereas that above all ought to sparkle, or at least to shine. if the sentiment must stand, twirl it a little into
					an apophegm, stick a flower in it, gild it with a costly expression, let it strike the fancy, the ear,
					or the heart, &amp; I am satisfied.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Hodges</hi>
					 is a sad Fellow, so is Dr Akenside, &amp; Mr Shenstone, our friends &amp; companions. your story of G:ck is a good one; pray, is it true, &amp; what came of it? did the tragic Poet call a
						Guard?
				</p>
         <p>It was I, that hinder'd Mr Brown from sending the Pamphlet. it is nonsense, &amp; that nonsense all stole from Dr Stukely's book about Abury &amp; Stone-henge. yet if you will have it, you may.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, &amp; let me hear soon from you.<lb/> I am ever <lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
            <dateline>Good Friday 1758 </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I wish you may come with Mr H:d, but I don't expect it.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
