<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (August 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 339, vol. ii, 745-746
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=339</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXIX, 266-268
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:266</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xlii, section iv, 291-292
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:291</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXV, vol. ii, 220-223
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:220</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XCIX, vol. ii, 390-391
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:390</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CVII, vol. iii, 286-288
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:286</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXIII, vol. ii, 60-61
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:60</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XLII, vol. i, 394-395
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:394</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0390">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1761-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0390">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Mason</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Be assured he never will die, so the better the thing is in value, the worse for you. the true way
					to immortality is to get you nominated one's Successor: Age &amp; Diseases vanish at your name, Fevers turn to radical heat, &amp;
					Fistulas to issues: it is a judgement that waits on your insatiable Avarice. you could not let the poor old Man die at his ease, when
					he was about it, &amp; all his family (I suppose) are cursing you for it.</p>
         <p>I should think your motions, if you are not perverse, might be so contrived as to bring you hither for a week or two in your way to
					the Coronation, &amp; then we may go together to Town, where I must be early in September. do, &amp; then I will help you to write a
					bawdy Sermon on this happy occasion. our friend Jemmy Bickham is going off to a living (better than
					400£ a-year) somewhere in the neighbourhood of Mr Hurd; &amp; his old Flame, that he has nursed so
					many years, goes with him: I tell you this to make you pine.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Ld John on his recovery, &amp; he answers me very chearfully, as if his illness had been
					but slight, &amp; the Pleuresy were no more than a hole in one's stocking. he got it (he says) not by scampering, &amp; racketing,
					&amp; heating his blood, as I had supposed: but by going with Ladies to Vauxhall. he is the picture (&amp; pray so tell him, if you see
					him) of an old Alderman, that I knew, who after living 40 years on the fat of the land, (not milk
					&amp; honey, but arrack-punch &amp; venison) &amp; losing his great toe with a mortification, said to the last, that he owed it to two
					grapes, wch he eat one day after dinner. he felt them lie cold at his stomach the minute they were down. </p>
         <p>Montagu (as I guess, at your instigation) has earnestly desired me to write some lines to be put on
					a Monument, wch he means to erect at Bellisle. it is a task I do not love, knowing Sr W: W: so
					slightly as I did: but he is so friendly a Person, &amp; his affliction seem'd to me so real, that I could not refuse him. I have sent
					him the following verses, wch I neither like myself, nor will he, I doubt. however I have shew'd him,
					that I wish'd to oblige him. tell me your real opinion.</p>
         <q>
            <p>Here foremost in the dang'rous paths of fame <lb/> Young Williams fought for England's fair renown: <lb/> His mind each Muse, each
						Grace adorn'd his frame, <lb/> Nor Envy dared to view him with a frown. <lb/> At Aix uncall'd his maiden-sword he drew <lb/> (There
						first in blood his infant-glory seal'd) <lb/> From fortune, pleasure, science, love, he flew, <lb/> And scorn'd repose, when Britain
						took the field. <lb/> With eyes of flame &amp; cool intrepid breast <lb/> Victor he stood on Bellisle's rocky steeps: <lb/> Ah
						gallant Youth!–this marble tells the rest, <lb/> Where melancholy Friendship bends, &amp; weeps. </p>
         </q>
         <p>(3 words below to say, who set up the Monument)</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
