<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (23 April 1757)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 237, vol. ii, 498-500
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=237</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XVII, 75-79
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:75</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 185
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:185</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXXIX, vol. i, 329-331
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:329</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXVI, vol. iv, 5-6
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:5</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0269">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1757-04-23"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0269">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I too am set down here with something greater hopes of quiet, than I could entertain, when I saw you last. at least nothing new has
					happen'd to give me any disturbance, &amp; the assurances, you gave me in your letter from hence, are
					pretty-well confirm'd by experience. I shall be very ready to take as much of Mr D:p's dullness, as he
					chuses to part with, at any price he pleases, even with his want of sleep &amp; weak Bowels into the bargain. and I will be your
					Curate, &amp; he shall live here with all my wit, &amp; a power of learning. Dr Brown's book (I hear)
					is much admired in Town, wch I do not understand. I expected it should be admired here; but they affect not to like it, tho' I know
					they ought. what would you have me do? there is one thing in it I applaud, wch is the dissertation against Trade, for I have always
					said, it was the ruin of the Nation. I have read the little wicked book about Evil, that settled Mr
					Dodsley's conscience in that point, &amp; find nothing in it, but absurdity. we call it Soame Jennyns's, but I have a notion you
					mention'd some other name to me, tho' I have forgot it. St: has done me the honour to send me your friend Ld Newnham hither with a fine recommendatory letter (written by his own desire) in Newmarket-week. do not think he was going to New-Market. no! he came in a Solitaire, great
					Sleeves, jessamine-powder, &amp; a large Bouquet of Jonquils within twelve miles of that place on purpose not to go thither. we had
					three days intercourse, talk'd about the Beaux-Arts, &amp; Rome, &amp; Hanover &amp; Mason, whose praises we celebrated <hi rend="italic">a qui mieux mieux,</hi> vowed eternal friendship, embraced, &amp; parted. I promised to write you a thousand compliments
					in his name. I saw also Ld Villiers &amp; Mr Spencer, who carried him
					back with them, <hi rend="italic">en passant.</hi> they did not like me at all. here has been too the best of all Johns (I hardly except the Evangelist, &amp; the Divine) who is not to be sure a
					bit like my Ld N:, but full as well in my mind. the D: of Bedford has brought his Son, ay, &amp; Mr Rigby too. they were at Church on Sunday morning, and Mr Sturgeon preach'd to them &amp; the Heads, for
					no body else was present. Mr Franklyn is not his Tutor. these are the most remarkable events at
					Cambridge.</p>
         <p>Mr B:y has been here. he had not done what you recommended to him, before he came out of Town, &amp;
					he is return'd thither only the beginning of this week, when he assured me he certainly would do it. alas, what may this delay
					occasion? it is best not to think. oh happy Mr D:p!</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, my best Mason, I am pleased to think how much I am obliged to you, &amp; that, while I live, I must be ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <dateline>April 23. 1757. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
