<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (20 March 1770)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 90</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 513, vol. iii, 1113-1114
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=513</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLVII, vol. iii, 267-269
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:267</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXV, vol. v, 103-104
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:103</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0577">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1770-03-20"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0577">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk By Yarmouth</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>March 20. 1770. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I am sorry for your disappointments &amp; my own. do not believe, that I am cold to Mr Cl:s
					translation: on the contrary I long to see it, &amp; wonder you should hesitate for want of Franks (wch here I have no means of
					getting) do I care about postage, do you think?</p>
				     <p>On Wednesday next I go (for a few days) with Mons: de B: to London. his cursed F:r will have him home in the autumn, &amp; he must pass thro France to improve his talents &amp; morals. he
					goes for Dover on Friday. I have seen (I own) with pleasure the efforts you have made to recommend me to him, <hi rend="italic">sed non
						ego credulus illis,</hi>
					 nor I fear, he neither. he gives me too much pleasure, &amp; at least <hi rend="italic">an equal
						share</hi> of inquietude. you do not understand him so well as I do, but I leave my meaning imperfect, till we meet. I have never met
					with so extraordinary a Person. God bless him! I am unable to talk to you about any thing else, I think.</p>
				     <p>I wonder'd, you should think of Paris at the time of the Dauphin's marriage: it will be a frippery
					spectacle, &amp; the expence of every thing triple. as to <hi rend="italic">Wales,</hi>
					 doubtless I should wish it this summer, but  I can answer for
					nothing, my own employment
					 so sticks in my stomach, &amp; troubles my conscience. when I
					return hither, I will write to you better &amp; more fully.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I am very sincerely yours</salute>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
