<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Ashton (29 May 1739)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>San Marino, CA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HULI">The Huntington</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts</repository>
		                <collection>Huntington Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>HM 7417</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photocopy is at the Bodleian Library, MS. Facs. b. 77, fol. 90b, a MS transcript is at the British Library, Add. MSS 32562, ff. 144-147</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 63, vol. i, 109-111
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=63</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 92, vol. i, 221-224
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:221</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section I, letter no. 3, 41-45
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:41</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 124-125
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:124</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XVIII, vol. i, 28-30
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:28</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0071">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008038">Paris, France</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1739-05-29"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227197">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0071">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>My Dear Ashton</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I shall not make you any excuses, because I can't: I shall not try to entertain you with descriptions, for the same reason; &amp;
					moreover, because I believe you don't care for them. so that you can have no occasion to wonder at my brevity, when you consider me, as
					confined to the narrow bounds of the history of We, quatenus We. which I continue. </p>
				     <p>Our tête à tête conversations, that you enquire after, did consist less in words, than in looks &amp; signs, &amp; to give you a
					notion of them, I ought to send you our pictures; tho' we should find it difficult to set for 'em in such attitudes, as we very
					naturally fall into, when alone together. at present Mr Conway, who lives with us, joins to make them a little more verbose, &amp;
					every thing is mighty well. on Monday next we set out for Rheims, (where we expect to be very dull;) there to stay a month or two; then
					we cross Burgundy, &amp; Dauphiny, &amp; so go to Avignon, Aix, Marseilles, &amp;c: the weather begins to be violently hot already even
					here, &amp; this is our ingenious contrivance, as the summer increases, to seek out cool retreats among the scorch'd rocks of Provence;
					I will not promise, but that if next winter bid fair for extreme cold, we shall take a trip to Muscovy. you in the mean time will be
					quietly enjoying the temperate air of England under your own vine, &amp; under your own (at least under Mrs Lewis's) Fig-tree; &amp; I don't doubt but the fruits of your leisure will turn to more account, than those of our
					laborious peregrination, and while our thoughts are rambling about, &amp; changeing situation oftener than our bodies, you will be
					fixing your attention upon some weighty truth, worthy a Sage of your honour's magnitude. the end of your researches, I mean whatever
					your profound contemplation brings to light, I should be proud to be acquainted with; whither it please to be invoked under the
					appellation of Sermon, Vision, Essay, or discourse: in short, on whatever head you chuse to be loquacious (Wall on
						Infant-Baptism excepted) a dissertation will be very acceptable, &amp; received with a reverence due
					to the hand it comes from.</p>
				     <p>We have seen here your Gustavus Vasa, that had raised the general expectation so high long ago. a
					worthy piece of prohibited marchandise in truth! the town must have been extreme mercifully disposed; if, for the sake of ten innocent
					lines, that may peradventure be pick'd out, it had consented to spare the lives of the ten thousand wicked ones, that remain. I don't
					know what condition your Stage is in, but the French is in a very good one at present; among the rest they have a Madlle
						Duminie, whose every look &amp; gesture is violent Nature; she is Passion itself incarnate: I saw her
					the other night do the Phædra of Racine in a manner; which affected me so strongly, that, as you see, I can't help prattling about her
					even to you, that do not care two-pence. </p>
				     <p>You have got My Ld Conway there among ye; what do people think about him, &amp; his improvements? you possibly see him sometimes, for
					he visits at Mrs Conduit's. is he charming, &amp; going to be married, like Mr Barrett? pray, write to me, &amp; persuade West to do
					the same, who unless you rouse him, &amp; preach to him, what a sin it is to have the vapours, &amp; the dismals, will neglect himself;
					I won't say, his friends; that I believe him incapable of. I again recommend him to your care, that you may nourish him, &amp; cherish
					him, &amp; administer to him some of that cordial spirit of chearfulness, that you used to have the Receipt of. my Compliments to my
						Lord. Good night,</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Yours ever </salute>
					       <signed>T: G: </signed>
					       <dateline>Paris – May 29. N: S: Friday-night.</dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
