<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (5 October 1766)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 427, vol. iii, 938-940
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=427</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XCVIII, 359-362
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:359</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXVII, vol. iii, 120-122
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:120</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0483">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1766-10-05"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mallet, Paul Henri</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0483">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>5 Oct: 1766. P: Hall. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I was going to write to you, when I received your letter, and on the same subject. the first news I
					had was from St: on the 23d. of Sept: in these words:</p>
         <p>'This morning Dr B: dispatch'd himself: he had been for several days past very low-spirited, &amp; within the last two or three
					talk'd of the necessity of dying in such a manner as to alarm the people about him: they removed as they thought every thing, that
					might serve his purpose. but he had contrived to get at a razor unknown to them, &amp; took the advantage of a minute's absence of his
					servants to make use of it.' I wrote to him again (I suspect, he knows our secret, tho' not from me)
					to make farther enquiries, &amp; he says, 27 Sept:, 'I have tried to find out, whether there was any appearance or cause of discontent
					in B:, but can hear of none. a bodily complaint of the gouty kind, that fell upon his nerves &amp; affected his spirits in a very great
					degree is all that I can get any information of; &amp; I am told besides, that he was some years ago in the same dejected way, &amp;
					under the care of <hi rend="italic">proper attendants.</hi>' Mr. W: too in answer to a letter I had written to enquire after his health
					after giving an account of himself, while under the care of Pringle, adds, 'He (Pringle) had another
					Patient at the same time, who has ended very unhappily, that poor Dr B:. the unfortunate Man apprehended himself going mad, &amp; two
					nights after cut his throat in bed.' this is all I know at present of the matter. I have told it you literally, &amp; I conceal
					nothing. as I go to town tomorrow, if I learn any thing more, you shall soon hear from me. in the mean time I think we may fairly
					conclude, that if he had had <hi rend="italic">any other</hi> cause added to his constitutional infirmity, it would have been uppermost
					in his mind: he would have talk'd or raved about it, &amp; the first thing we should have heard of, would have been this, wch (I do
					assure you) I have never heard from any body. there is in this neighbourhood a Mr Wale, who once was
					in the Russia-trade &amp; married a Woman of that country: he always maintain'd, that Dr B: would never go thither, whatever he might
					pretend; &amp; that tho' fond of the glory of being invited thither, he would certainly find or make a pretence for staying at home.
					very possibly therefore he might have engaged himself so far, that he knew not how to draw back with honour; or might have received
					rough words from the Russian Minister offended with his prevarication. this supposition is at least as
					likely as yours; added to what I have said before, much more so: if it be necessary to suppose any other cause than the lunatick
					disposition of the Man. and yet I will not disguise to you, that I felt as you do on the first news of this sad accident, &amp; had the
					same uneasy ideas about it.</p>
         <p>I am sorry the cause you mention should be the occasion of your coming to London: tho' perhaps
					change of air may do more than medicine. in this length of time I should think you must be fully apprised, whether her looks or
					strength or embon-point have suffer'd by this cough: if not; surely there is no real danger. yet I do not wonder, she should wish to
					get rid of so troublesome a companion.</p>
         <p>When I can meet with the book, I will transcribe what you mention from <hi rend="italic">Mallet.</hi>
					 I shall write again soon. do you know of any great, or at least rich, family that want a young Man
					worth his weight in gold to take care of their eldest hope. if you do, remember I have such a one, or
					shall have (I fear) shortly to sell: but they must not stand haggling about him, &amp; besides they must be very good sort of people
					too, or they shall not have him.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! my respects to Mrs Mason. I am ever <lb/> Sincerely Yours. </salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Mr Brown desires his best compliments to you both. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
