<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (8 September 1751)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 161, vol. i, 346-350
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=161</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 175, vol. ii, 111-116
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:111</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 390-392
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 170-173
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:170</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XCV, vol. i, 212-215
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:212</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXVIII, vol. ii, 215-217
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:215</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXXV, vol. iii, 84-86
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:84</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXXI, vol. i, 168-170
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:168</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 52-55
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=52</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0182">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1751-09-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0182">
      <body>
         <q>
            <p>HYMN TO ADVERSITY.</p>
            <p>Daughter of Jove, relentless Power, <lb/> Thou Tamer of the human Breast! <lb/> Whose iron Scourge, &amp; torturing Hour, <lb/>
						The bad affright, afflict the best, <lb/> Bound in thy adamantine Chain <lb/> The Proud are taught to tast of Pain <lb/> And purple
						Tyrants vainly groan <lb/> With Pangs unfelt before, unpitied &amp; alone. <lb/> When first thy Sire to send on Earth <lb/> Virtue,
						his darling Child, design'd, <lb/> To Thee he gave the heav'nly Birth <lb/> And bad to form her infant Mind. <lb/> Stern rugged
						Nurse! thy rigid Lore <lb/> With Patience many a Year she bore: <lb/> What Sorrow was thou bad'st her know, <lb/> And from her own
						she learn'd to melt at other's Woe. <lb/> Scared at thy Frown terrific, fly <lb/> Self-pleasing Folly's idle Brood, <lb/> Wild
						Laughter, Noise, &amp; thoughtless Joy, <lb/> And leave us Leisure to be good: <lb/> Light they disperse, &amp; with them go <lb/>
						The Summer-Friend, the flatt'ring Foe; <lb/> By vain Prosperity received, <lb/> To her they vow their Truth, &amp; are again
						believed. <lb/> Wisdom in sable Garb array'd, <lb/> Immers'd in rapturous Thought profound, <lb/> And Melancholy, silent Maid,
						<lb/> With leaden Eye, that loves the Ground <lb/> Still on thy solemn Steps attend: <lb/> Warm Charity, the general Friend, <lb/>
						With Justice, to herself severe, <lb/> And Pity, dropping soft the sadly-pleasing Tear. <lb/> Oh! gently on thy Suppliant's Head
						<lb/> Dread Goddess lay thy chast'ning Hand, <lb/> Not in thy Gorgon-Terrors clad, <lb/> Nor circled with the vengeful Band, <lb/>
						As by the Impious thou art seen, <lb/> With thund'ring Voice, &amp; threat'ning Mien, <lb/> With screaming Horrour's funeral Cry,
						<lb/> Despair, &amp; fell Disease, &amp; ghastly Poverty. <lb/> Thy Form benign, oh Goddess, wear, <lb/> Thy milder Influence
						impart; <lb/> Thy philosophic Train be there <lb/> To soften, not to wound, my Heart. <lb/> The generous Spark extinct revive,
						<lb/> Teach me to love, &amp; to forgive, <lb/> Exact my own Defects to scan, <lb/> What others are, to feel, &amp; know myself a
						Man. </p>
         </q>
         <p>I send you this (as you desire) merely to make up half a dozen; tho' it will hardly answer your End
					in furnishing out either a Head or Tail-piece. but your own Fable
					may much better supply the Place. you have alter'd it to its Advantage; but there is still something a little embarrass'd here &amp;
					there in the Expression. I rejoice to find you apply (pardon the Use of so odious a Word) to the History of your own Times. speak, &amp; spare not. be as impartial as you can; &amp; after all, the World will not believe, you are
					so, tho' you should make as many Protestations as Bishop Burnet. they will feel in their own Breast,
					&amp; find it very possible to hate fourscore Persons, yea, ninety &amp; nine: so you must rest satisfied with the Testimony of your
					own Conscience. somebody has laughed at Mr Dodsley or at me, when they talk'd of the <hi rend="italic">Bat</hi>: I have nothing more,
					either nocturnal or diurnal, to deck his Miscellany with. we have a Man here that writes a good Hand;
					but he has two little Failings, that hinder my recommending him to you. he is lousy, &amp; he is mad:
					he sets out this Week for Bedlam; but if you insist upon it, I don't doubt he will pay his Respects to you. I have seen two of Dr
						M:idns unpublish'd Works. one is about 44 Pages in 4to against Dr Waterland, who wrote a very orthodox Book on the Importance of the Doctrine of ye Trinity, &amp; insisted, that
					Christians ought to have no Communion with such as differ from them in Fundamentals. M:idn enters no farther into the Doctrine itself
					than to shew that a mere speculative Point can never be call'd a Fundamental; &amp; that the earlier Fathers, on whose concurrent
					Tradition Wat:d would build, are so far, when they speak of the three Persons, from agreeing with the present Notion of our Church,
					that they declare for the Inferiority of the Son, &amp; seem to have no clear &amp; distinct Idea of the H: Ghost at all. the rest is
					employed in exposing the Folly &amp; Cruelty of Stiffness &amp; Zealotism in Religion, &amp; in shewing that the primitive Ages of the
					Church, in wch Tradition had its Rise, were (even by Confession of the best Scholars &amp; most orthodox Writers) the <hi rend="italic">Æra of Nonsense &amp; Absurdity.</hi> it is finish'd, &amp; very well wrote; but has been mostly incorporated into his other Works,
					particularly the Enquiry: &amp; for this Reason I suppose he has writ upon it, <hi rend="italic">This wholly laid aside.</hi> the
					second is in Latin, on Miracles; to shew, that of the two Methods of defending Christianity, one from its intrinsic Evidence, the
					Holiness and Purity of its Doctrines; the other from its external, the Miracles said to be wrought to confirm it. the first has been
					little attended to by reason of its Difficulty; the second much insisted upon, because it appear'd an easier Task, but that it can in
					reality prove nothing at all. 'Nobilis illa quidem Defensio (the first) quam si obtinere potuissent, rem simul omnem expediisse,
						causam qb penitús vicisse viderentur. at causæ hujus defendendæ labor cum tantâ argumentandi
						cavillandi qb molestiâ conjunctus ad alteram, quam dixi, defensionis viam, ut commodiorem longé &amp;
					faciliorem, plerosque adegit—ego veró istiusmodi defensione Religionem nostram non modo non confirmari, sed dubiam potiús
						suspectam qb reddi existimo.' he then proceeds to consider Miracles in general, &amp; afterwards those
					of the Pagans, compared with those of Xt. I only tell you the Plan, for I have not read it out (tho' it is short) but you will not
					doubt to what Conclusion it tends. there is another Thing, I know not what, I am to see. as to the Treatise on Prayer; they say, it is
					burnt indeed.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
            <dateline>Sept: 8. Camb: </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
