<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard Stonhewer (29 June 1760)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 315, vol. ii, 684-686
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=315</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxxvii, section iv, 279-281
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:279</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 235-236
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:235</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCIV, vol. ii, 151-155
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:151</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXXVIII, vol. ii, 353-355
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:353</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XCVI, vol. iii, 243-245
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:243</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CVIII, vol. ii, 49-51
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:49</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXXVII, vol. i, 383-385
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:383</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0363">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1760-06-29"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Macpherson, James, 1736-1796</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Tacitus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Macpherson, James, 1736-1796</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Alembert, Jean le Rond d'</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0363">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>London, June 29, 1760.</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>Though you have had but a melancholy employment, it is worthy of envy, and (I hope) will have all the success it deserves. It was the best and most natural method of cure, and such as could not have been administered by any but
					your gentle hand. I thank you for communicating to me what must give you so much satisfaction.</p>
         <p>I too was reading M. D'Alembert, and (like you) am totally disappointed in his Elements. I could only taste a little of the first course: it was dry as a stick, hard as a stone, and cold as a
					cucumber. But then the Letter to Rousseau is like himself; and the Discourses on Elocution, and on the Liberty of Music, are divine. He has added to his translations
					from Tacitus; and (what is remarkable) though that Author's manner more nearly resembles the best
					French Writers of the present age, than any thing, he totally fails in the attempt. Is it his fault, or that of the language?</p>
         <p>I have received another Scotch packet with a third specimen,
					inferior in kind, (because it is merely description) but yet full of nature and noble wild imagination. Five Bards pass the night at
					the Castle of a Chief (himself a principal Bard); each goes out in his turn to observe the face of things, and returns with an
					extempore picture of the changes he has seen (it is an October night, the harvest-month of the Highlands). This is the whole plan; yet
					there is a contrivance, and a preparation of ideas, that you would not expect. The oddest thing is, that every one of them sees Ghosts
					(more or less). The idea, that struck and surprised me most, is the following. One of them (describing a storm of wind and rain) says <q>
               <p>Ghosts ride on the tempest to-night: <lb/> Sweet is their voice between the gusts of wind; <lb/>
                  <hi rend="italic">Their songs are of other worlds!</hi>
               </p>
            </q> Did you never observe (<hi rend="italic">while rocking winds are piping loud</hi>) that pause,
					as the gust is recollecting itself, and rising upon the ear in a shrill and plaintive note, like the swell of an Ã&#x86;olian harp? I do
					assure you there is nothing in the world so like the voice of a spirit. Thomson had an ear sometimes: he was not deaf to this; and has
					described it gloriously, but given it another different turn, and of more horrour. I cannot repeat the lines: it is in his
						Winter. There is another very fine picture in one of them. It describes the breaking of the clouds
					after the storm, before it is settled into a calm, and when the moon is seen by short intervals.</p>
         <q>
            <p>The waves are tumbling on the lake, <lb/> And lash the rocky sides. <lb/> The boat is brim-full in the cove, <lb/> The oars on
						the rocking tide. <lb/> Sad sits a maid beneath a cliff, <lb/> And eyes the rolling stream: <lb/> Her Lover promised to come,
						<lb/> She saw his boat (when it was evening) on the lake; <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Are these his groans in the gale?</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Is this his broken boat on the shore?</hi>
            </p>
         </q>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
