<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Edward Bedingfield (29 December 1756)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>San Marino, CA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HULI">The Huntington</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts</repository>
		                <collection>Huntington Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>HM 21913</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 231, vol. ii, 490-492
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=231</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0262">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1756-12-29"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Bedingfield, Edward, b. 1730</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7028630">Stoke Ferry, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0262">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To Edward Bedingfield Esq at Oxburgh Hall near Stoke-ferry Norfolk</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAM[BRIDGE]</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <salute> S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I know I have reason to make you many excuses but I never found them answer any other end than to fill up vacancies in a Letter,
					therefore I shall only tell you that I have been longer on the wing this year than usual &amp; than I at first intended, &amp; that I am now return'd at last to my cell, &amp; my solitude. <hi>Frere Thomas</hi> is not so devoted
					to his books or his orisons, as to forget the promise you have made him; &amp; whenever any occasion calls you this way, his
						<hi>other</hi> Great-Chair holds open its arms to receive you, if not with all the grace, yet with as
					much good-will, as any Dutchesses quilted Peché-Mortel, or Sofa with a triple gold-fringe. You desire
					to see more of an Ode w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is no favourite of mine, but as you are disposed to be
					kind to it, here is the beginning. the end you have already.</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>Strophe I.</p> Awake, Æolian Lyre, awake,<lb/> And give to rapture all thy trembling strings.<lb/> From Helicon's harmonious
					springs<lb/> A thousand rills their mazy progress take:<lb/> The laughing flowers, that round them blow,<lb/> Drink life &amp;
					fragrance, as they flow.<lb/> Now the rich stream of musick winds along<lb/> Deep, majestic, smooth, &amp; strong,<lb/> Thro'
					verdant vales, &amp; Ceres' golden reign:<lb/> Now rushing down the steep amain,<lb/> Impetuous,
					headlong, see it pour,<lb/> While rocks &amp; nodding groves rebellow to the roar.<lb/>
					       <p>Antist: I.</p> Oh Sovereign of the willing Soul,<lb/> Parent of sweet &amp; solemn-breathing airs,<lb/> Inchanting Shell! the
					sullen Cares,<lb/> And frantic Passions hear thy soft controul.<lb/> On Thracia's hills the Lord of War<lb/> Has curb'd the fury of
					his car,<lb/> And drop'd his thirsty lance at thy command.<lb/> Perching on the scepter'd hand<lb/> Of Jove thy magick lulls the
					feather'd King<lb/> With ruffled plumes, &amp; flagging wing.<lb/> Quench'd in black clouds of slumber lie<lb/> The terror of his beak, &amp; light'nings of his eye. <p>[           ]</p>
				     </q>
				     <p> It is very strange, that while I am writing to you after so long an interval, a Letter of yours should come, &amp; interrupt me so
					seasonably. I am &amp; shall be at Cambridge, these many months, as far as I can foresee, &amp; how glad to see you, judge by yourself.
					if I stay to say more, the Post will not stay for me;</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> I am, S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
               <lb/> Your most obedient Servant </salute>
					       <signed> T:G: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
