<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (8 May 1742)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 107, vol. i, 201-202
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=107</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter viii, section iii, 148-150
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/148</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 136-138
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/NoC_1911/1/136</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 149, vol. ii, 40-41
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/40</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LIV, vol. i, 101-102
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/101</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section II, letter fragment, 166
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1890/1/166</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section III, letter VIII, vol. ii, 136-137
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/136</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section III, letter VIII, vol. ii, 162-164
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/162</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LVI, vol. i, 125-126
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/125</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section III, letter VIII, vol. i, 266-267
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/266</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0123">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1742-05-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="poem">Imitated from Propertius, Lib: 3: Eleg: 5:</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">[Imitated] From Propertius. Lib: 2: Eleg: 1.</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Thucydides</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Theocritus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Scaliger, Joseph Justus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Propertius</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pliny</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Petrarch</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Nonius Marcellus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Martial</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Anacreon</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0123">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>London, May 8, 1742. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I rejoice to see you putting up your prayers to the May: She cannot choose but come at such a call. It is as light and genteel as
					herself. You bid me find fault; I am afraid I cannot; however I will try. The first stanza (if what you say to me in it did not make me
					think it the best) I should call the worst of the five (except the fourth line). The two next are very picturesque, Miltonic, and
					musical; her bed is so soft and so snug that I long to lie with her. But those two lines 'Great Nature' are my favourites. The
					exclamation of the flowers is a little step too far. The last stanza is full as good as the second and
					third; the last line bold, but I think not too bold. Now, as to myself and my translation, pray do not call names. I never saw
					Broukhusius in my life. It is Scaliger who attempted to range Propertius in order; who was, and still
					is, in sad condition. [...] You see, by what I sent you, that I converse, as usual, with none but the
					dead: They are my old friends, and almost make me long to be with them. You will not wonder therefore, that I, who live only in times
					past, am able to tell you no news of the present. I have finished the Peloponnesian war much to my
					honour, and a tight conflict it was, I promise you. I have drank and sung with Anacreon for the last fortnight, and am now feeding
					sheep with Theocritus. Besides, to quit my figure, (because it is foolish) I have run over Pliny's Epistles and Martial <hi rend="italic">ἐκ</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">παρέργου</hi>; not to mention Petrarch, who, by the way, is sometimes very tender and natural. I must needs tell you
					three lines in Anacreon, where the expression seems to me inimitable. He is describing hair as he would have it painted.</p>
         <q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Ἕλικας</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">δ</hi>' <hi rend="italic">ἐλευθέρους</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">μοι</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Πλοκάμων</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">ἄτακτα</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">συνθεὶς</hi>
               <lb/> '<hi rend="italic">Αφὲς</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">ὡς</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">θέλουσι</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">κεῖσθαι</hi>.</p>
         </q>
         <p>Guess, too, where this is about a dimple.</p>
         <q>
            <p>Sigilla in mento impressa Amoris digitulo <lb/> Vestigio demonstrant mollitudinem. </p>
         </q>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
