<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (6 June 1767)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 444, vol. iii, 963
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=444</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CX, 388-389
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:388</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCII, vol. iii, 144-145
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:144</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0500">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1767-06-06"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0500">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>June 6. 1767. Jermyn-street. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>We are a-coming, but not so fast as you think for, because Mr Brown can not think of stirring till Whitsun-week is over. the Monday
						following we propose to set out in our chaise: do not think of sending Benjamin, I charge you. we shall find our way from Bautry very cleverly.</p>
				     <p>I shall bring with me a drawing, wch Stuart has made. he approves
					your sketch highly, &amp; therefore (I suppose) has alter'd it in every particular, not at all for the better in my mind. he says, you
					should send him an account of the place &amp; position, &amp; a scale of the dimensions; this is what I modestly proposed before, but
					you give no ear to me. the relief, in artificial stone, he thinks, would come to about eight
					guineas.</p>
				     <p>Poor Mr Fitzherbert had a second Son, who was at Caen: he complain'd of a swelling &amp; some pain
					in his knee, wch rather increasing upon him, his Father sent for him over. the Surgeons agreed, it was a White-swelling, &amp; he must
					lose his leg. he underwent the operation with great fortitude, but died the second day after it.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I rejoice, Mr Wood is well, &amp; present my humble service to him.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
