<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Mary Antrobus (September  or October 1764)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
                  <institution key="HSPO">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</institution>
                  <repository>Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat each is in MS. Toynbee d.32 and c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 391*, vol. ii, 842
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=391*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0444">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" notBefore="1764-10"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29394522">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0444">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Monday, Jermyn-Street.     </dateline>
            <salute> Dear Mary </salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I am extremely concerned at the account you give me of poor Dolly's sufferings. the severeness of the pain makes me believe, that
					(when you wrote) her distemper was drawing to its crisis, &amp; the abscess might find a vent of itself, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is
					most to be wish'd.</p>
         <p> I am no friend to Surgeons, &amp; in this case particularly, (as the seat of her malady is so near a very tender part, that is not
					to be trifled with,) I should by no means suffer them to proceed to any operation without the Professor's inspection &amp; advice. if he declares it necessary, let her not be frighted at the sight of steel, for I
					can tell her upon some experience, that one half-hour of the pain she undergoes from her illness is
					much more, than all she will suffer from M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thackeray's hand. I talk as
					supposing it still to come, but perhaps it is all over, &amp; I may congratulate her on having got rid of this evil, &amp; with it of
					those illnesses she has suffer'd so much from these two years, for it is possible Nature may have found out this means to free her from
					those complaints. I heartily wish her well, &amp; hope to hear again from you soon.</p>
         <p> I have been detain'd in Town till now, &amp; go not to Southampton till Wednesday. when I get thither, I shall let M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Brown know, where I am lodged, &amp; you will send your letter to him to direct.</p>
         <p> My complements to M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> A:, pray tell me about B: &amp; his Wife, if they have been to see you.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute> I am your Friend &amp; Servant </salute>
            <signed> T G:       </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
