<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (<hi rend="it">after</hi> 9 November 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 284, vol. ii, 595-597
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=284</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XL, 165-167
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1853/1/165</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXIX, vol. ii, 62-64
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/62</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0328">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7029839">Aston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" notBefore="1758-11-09"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Hurd, Richard, 1720-1808</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hurd, Dr. Richard</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0328">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mr Gray </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I recd your last. but as I had before sent you my 2d Ode I was in hopes to have heard again, with your particular remarks on that.
					Observe the 2d Stanza, that is the 1st Antistrophe, I intend to alter on acct of the sameness of imagery with one in
						Melancholly, but I hope the rest will stand some words excepted, I will attempt a new Madors song to
					please you. but in my own mind, I would not have him sing there at all, on account of the toute ensemble for he sings all the 2d Ode &amp; also all the fourth. so Im afraid he'll be hoarse. I like the Idea of my fourth Ode much &amp;
					the preparation to it. tis the speech of an armed Death to the Britons. Who Mador is supposd to see &amp; hear just at the onset of the
					Battle.</p>
         <p>Thus. <q>
               <p>CHORUS. </p>
               <p>— but why is this <lb/> Why doth our Brother Mador snatch his Harp <lb/> From yonder Bough? Why this way bend his steps </p>
               <p>CARACT: </p>
               <p>He looks entranced. The Fillet bursts that bound <lb/> His liberal locks. His snowy vestments fall <lb/> In ampler folds, &amp;
							all his floating form <lb/> Doth seem to glisten with Divinity. <lb/> Yet is he speechless. Say thou chief of bards <lb/> What is
							there in this airy Vacancy <lb/> That thou with fiery &amp; irregular glance <lb/> Should scan thus wildly? Wherefore heaves thy
							Breast? <lb/> Why starts— </p>
               <p>ODE </p>
               <p>Hark! heard ye not yon footstep dread, <lb/> That shook the Earth with Thundring tread? <lb/> Twas Death. in Haste <lb/> The
							Warrior past, <lb/> High towerd his Helmed head. <lb/> I markt his mail, I markd his Shield, <lb/> I spyd the spar[k]ling of his
							spear, <lb/> I saw his giant Arm the Falcion wield <lb/> Courage was in his van &amp; conquest in his rear. </p>
            </q> and so it goes on but without a word of Odin &amp; Valhalla. yet the general Celtic principle of the happiness of dying in Battle
					is touchd upon wch I hope is not in itself too Scaldic. </p>
         <p>I send you with this another pacquet &amp; I have another ready to follow it then I get to my third Ode &amp; when that is done I
					shall have little more than transcription. When you have all the MS. I would have you keep it, till I write about sending it to Mr
					Hurd. probably we may contrive it without posting. Do excuse all this <hi rend="italic">Caractication</hi> I am seriously desirous of
					getting quit of him &amp; therefore must trouble you till I do.</p>
         <p>Mr Brown has writ me a long Letter about keeping my Divinity act, wch he says I must do next March.
					Do you say so too? if you do I will incontinently drown myself. till when</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I remain, sincerely yours </salute>
            <signed>W MASON. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>My Eyes by Blistering are well again. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
