<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (22 October 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution key="PRIV">Private collection</institution>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a MS copy is at Pembroke College, Cambridge, GBR/1058/GRA/5/6; Christie's, 14 June 1979 (A. A. Houghton Sale), Lot 237, sold to Fleming</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 347, vol. ii, 759-761
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=347</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Athenæum</title>, 21 Feb. 1891, printed by Edmund Gosse
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXXII, vol. ii, 240-241
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:240</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0398">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-10-22"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0398">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Brown President of Pembroke Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>London. Oct: 22. 1761. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have sent down by Gillam's waggon to-day 28 parcels of
					different bulks, wch I suppose will be deliver'd on Monday morning, &amp; must beg the favour, that you will see put into my rooms.
					they are as follows <q>
               <p>1, x2 Chests of Books. <lb/> x3 A Fire grate &amp; instruments <lb/> 4 Steel-Fender <lb/> x5 Basket of Earthen-ware, glasses,
							&amp;c. <lb/> x6 Black Travelling Chest. <lb/> x7 Wainscot-Box<lb/> x8 Sofa. <lb/> 9 Back to
							the same. <lb/> x10 Deal Book-Case taken to pieces. <lb/> x11 Wainscot Chest of Drawers. <lb/> x12 Night-Table. <lb/> x13 Round
							Table, &amp;c. <lb/> x14 Breakfast-Table, &amp;c. <lb/> x15 Small Chest of Drawers. <lb/> x16, x17 Two Feather Beds, &amp;c <lb/>
							x18, x19 Bedstead in two parts. <lb/> 20 Settee &amp; Stools. <lb/> x21, x22, x23 Six Chairs. <lb/> x24, x25, x26 Six slighter
							chairs. <lb/> x27 Fly-Table and Wash-Stand.<lb/> x28 Basket with pillows, cushions, &amp;c: </p>
            </q> Those marked with a cross are easier to break, &amp; therefore pray observe if they appear to have received any damage in coming.
					you will take notice of No 6, &amp; 7 for another reason, because in them are Papers &amp; other things of value to me. they may all
					stand pack'd up as they are, till I come, wch will be in about three weeks, I guess: in the mean time
					I beg no fire may be made, nor any body go flaunting in with a candle, for so many mats &amp; so much packing will make it very
						dangerous.
				</p>
         <p>Mr Gillam (I reckon) will stay for his money till I arrive. </p>
         <p>We are all much out of countenance about this pension. I dare not see Delaval any more, &amp;
					expect to hear Mason has taken Laudanum.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>How goes T. L:s affair?
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
