<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (27 July 1767)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 450, vol. iii, 970-973
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=450</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXV, 400-404
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:400</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCVIII, vol. iii, 152-154
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:152</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0506">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011995">York, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1767-07-27"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Brown, James, 1709-1784</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0506">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Thomas Gray Esqb at Old Park near Darlington</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>YORK</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>York July 27th 1767 </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr Gray </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>In hopes this may catch you before you set off for Hartlepool I answer yours the moment I receive it (Minster Vespers only
					intervening) The Dean has disapointed me &amp; is not yet arrivd, the Robinsons I expect every hour. in the meanwhile I will resume the subject of the Epitaph.</p>
         <p>Had you given me any hint any <hi rend="italic">Lueur</hi> how the three first lines might have been alterd, it would have been
					charitable indeed. But you say nothing, only that I must alter them, Now in my Conscience to wch you appeal I cannot find fault with
					the Sentiment wch they contain, &amp; yet in dispite of my Conscience if I thought that they implyd the least shadow of flattery to the
					ABp I would wipe them out with a spunge dipt in the mud of the kennel. But I cannot think they do. I think on the contrary they give
					the Composition that Unity of Thought wch ought always to run thro compositions of this kind, for in my mind <hi rend="italic">a
						Perfect Epitaph is a Perfect Epigram without a sting.</hi> NB this sentence in our Epistolæ Familiares cum notis variorum will be
					explaind, in a Note of Dr Balguys, to the contentation of every reader; in the meantime if you dont understand it yourself, console
					yourself with the pleasing Idea that Posterity will, &amp; that is enough in reason.</p>
         <p>However to shew you my Complacency, &amp; in dread that you should ever do as you threaten, &amp; call whatever I send you the most
					perfect things in Nature, I will sacrifice the first Stanza on Your Critical Altar. &amp; let it consume either in flame or <hi rend="italic">Smudge</hi> as it chuses. Then we begin, <hi rend="italic">Here sleeps</hi> a very poetical sort of <hi rend="italic">Ci
						git,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">here lies,</hi> &amp; wch I hope will not lead the reader to imagine a sentence lost.</p>
         <q>
            <p>1 Here sleeps what once was Beauty once was Grace<lb/> 2 Grace that with native Sentiment combind<lb/> 3 To form that Harmony of
						Soul &amp; face<lb/> 4 Where Beauty shines the mirror of the mind<lb/> 5 Such was the Maid that in the noon of youth,<lb/> 6 In
						Virgin innocence in natures pride<lb/> 7 Blest with each Art that taste supplies or Truth<lb/> 8 Sunk in her Fathers fond embrace
						&amp; died<lb/> 9 He weeps O venerate the holy tear<lb/> 10 Faith lends her aid to ease afflictions Load<lb/> 11 The Parent mourns
						his child upon her bier<lb/> 12 The Christian yeilds an Angel to his God.
					</p>
         </q>
         <p>Various Lections, pick, &amp; chuse, <lb/> 2 <hi rend="italic">inborn</hi> sentiment.<lb/> 3 <hi rend="italic">displayd</hi> or <hi rend="italic">diffusd</hi> that Harmony &amp;c.<lb/> 7 that <hi rend="italic">springs</hi> from taste or Truth <hi rend="italic">derivd</hi> from taste or Truth, that <hi rend="italic">charms</hi> with taste &amp; Truth. But, after all I dont know that she was a
					Metaphysician Blest with each art <hi rend="italic">that owes its charms</hi> to Truth wch Painting does as well as Logic &amp;
					Metaphysics.<lb/> 10 Faith lends her lenient aid to Sorrows Load. Faith lends her Aid &amp; <hi rend="italic">eases</hi> or <hi rend="italic">lightens</hi> Sorrows Load<lb/> 11 Pensive he <hi rend="italic">mourns</hi> or he <hi rend="italic">views</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gives</hi>
            <lb/> 12 <hi rend="italic">Yet humbly yeilds</hi> or <hi rend="italic">But</hi> humbly</p>
         <p>Now if from all this you can pick out 12 Ostensible Lines, do, &amp; Ill father them, or if you will out of that Lukewarm corner of
					your heart where you hoard up your poetical Charity, throw out a poor mite to my distresses, I shall take it kind indeed. But if not,
					Stat prior Sententia, for I will give myself no further trouble about it. I cannot in this uncomfortable place where my Opus Magnum
					sive didacticum has not advancd ten lines since I saw you.</p>
         <p>God bless Dr Wharton &amp; send him (for his Sympathy) never to feel what I feel. I will come to him the moment I can; write be sure
					you [do] when you return from your longer tour. But I hope to have an answer to this before you set out, because I shall not give the
					ABp any detirminate answer about the matter till I hear again from you. The Robinsons are just arrivd. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu</salute>
            <signed>W. M.</signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I must needs tell you, as an instance of my enjoyments here that Yesterday Mr Comber preachd again
						&amp; dind with me &amp; in the afternoon who but Billy Harvey should preach &amp; drink tea with me!
						The said Billy enquird most Cordially after you &amp; has got your directions how to come at you, by Kirksomething &amp; Spinny moor house, for he is going into Scotland with a Scotch Captain, ten times duller than
						himself. youll have them at Old park almost as soon as this if you dont run away. </p>
            <p rendition="#center">ANECDOTE. </p>
            <p>The Country Folks are firmly persuaded that the Storm (wch made us get up here) was raisd by the Devil out of revenge to Comber for
						preaching <hi rend="italic">at him</hi> the day before in the minster.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
