<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Edward Bedingfield (29 April 1756)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>San Marino, CA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HULI">The Huntington</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts</repository>
		                <collection>Huntington Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>HM 21911</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 215, vol. ii, 461-463
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=215</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0246">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1756-04-29"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Bedingfield, Edward, b. 1730</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0246">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <dateline>Pembroke-Hall. April 29.</dateline>
					       <salute>S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
            </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I do not doubt but before this time You have made many reflections on my caprice, or extreme unpoliteness, in giving no sign of
					gratitude, or even of bare sensibility, to your very obliging Letter. but I shall throw part of the fault on you, for only consider how
					embarassing it is, to receive the highest applause, (&amp; that given with an air of sincerity) without either exposing one's own pride
					quite naked, or affecting to cover it with an aukward humility, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> every body has eyes to see through. in short
					I hope You very accurately informed yourself of my age, before you ventured to treat me so, for had I been some years younger, it might
					have turn'd my head. as it is, I find myself still young enough to tast the sweets of praise (and to like the taste too) yet old enough
					not to be intoxicated with them. to own the truth, they give me spiritis, but I begin to wonder, they should hurt any body's health,
					when we can so easily dash them with the bitter salutary drop of misery &amp; mortality, that we always carry about us. I well remember
					the honour You did me in expressing so kind a prejudice &amp; partiality for one as yet unknown to you, as to offer him your
					Friendship. I own it is difficult to excuse my silence here, &amp; therefore I will trust this part of my cause to your humanity. begin
					to exercise your Good-Will to me by bearing with that natural gloom &amp; heaviness of temper, that hangs about me. when we are better
					acquainted, I fear you will meet with many more essential faults to exercise your indulgence upon.</p>
				     <p> You must indulge me too in another instance of less importance. that Ode, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> has been mention'd to you under the name of the <hi>Powers of Poetry</hi> I should very readily shew
					you, whenever we meet, &amp; be glad to ask your opinion of it: but I can convey it to you no other way than by the Post, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is not to be depended upon, &amp; I have been already threaten'd with publication, tho' there are no more than
					three copies of it in the world. to abate your curiosity I assure you it is very incorrect, &amp; being
					wrote by fits &amp; starts at very distant intervals is so unequal that it will hardly admit of particular corrections. You may believe
					me, for I pretend to judge of myself with tolerable impartiality. you call it <hi>celebrated</hi>, but its celebrity is only owing to
					its being yet unpublish'd. I have written part of another, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> intends to be much
					better, but my Inspiration is very apt to fail me before I come to a conclusion. I desire to know your opinion of M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Mason's four new Odes. you will see, that He is a particular Friend of mine, from reading
						them: yet I expect your judgement upon them &amp; that of your best Northern Criticks, if there be any
					Criticks there. provided You shew yourself noble &amp; forgive my long inactivity, I will repay your Criticism in Poetry, but it must
					be Latin, for I too wrote Latin once upon a time.</p>
				     <p> My Compliments have now a sort of right to wait upon Lady Swinburne, whose former politeness I well
					remember'd, &amp; whose invitation I should gladly embrace if I had the good fortune of seeing York again. there is another Lady I dare not present my respects to, unless You will introduce &amp; recommend them for me.</p>
				     <p> D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Long (in whose College I now reside, for I have left Peter-House) desires
					me to make his Comp<hi rend="super">ts</hi> to You.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> I am, S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
               <lb/> Your most obed<hi rend="super">t</hi> Servant </salute>
					       <signed> T Gray. </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
