<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (1 December 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 307, vol. ii, 653-655
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=307</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter L, 198-200
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1853/1/198</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXCVI, vol. ii, 114-117
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/114</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0354">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1759-12-01"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">Rochefort</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Quiberon</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0354">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am extremely obliged to you [for the] kind attention you bestow on me &amp; my affairs. I have
					not been a sufferer by this calamity: it was on the other side of the street, &amp; did not reach so
					far as the houses opposite to mine: but there was an Attorney, who had writings belonging to me in
					his hands, that had his house burnt down among the first: yet he has had the good fortune to save all his papers. the fire is said to
					have begun in the chamber of that poor Glass-Organist who lodged at a Coffee-house in
						Swithin's-Alley, &amp; perish'd in the flames. two other Persons were destroy'd (in the charitable
					office of assisting their friends) by the fall of some buildings. last night there was another fire in Lincolns Inn Fields, that burnt
					the Sardinian Ambassador's Chappel &amp; Stables with some adjacent houses. 'tis strange, that we all
					of us (here in Town) lay ourselves down every night on our Funeral Pile ready made, &amp; compose ourselves to rest; while every
					drunken Footman, &amp; drowsy Old-Woman, has a candle ready to light it before the morning.
				</p>
         <p>You will have heard of Hawke's Victory before this can reach you (perhaps by an Express). [the Soleil Royal], Monsr de Conflans
					own Ship of [80 guns, &amp; the Hero of] 74, were driven on Shore &amp; [subsequently burnt], two sunk (capital Ships) with [all their crews, fo]r it blew a storm during the whole [day, so that none] could be saved out of
					them. eight [after throwin]g over their cannon were able to run [into th]e mouth of a shallow river
					(where, if the [wi]nd will permit, it is probable, they may be set on fire) &amp; eight ran away, &amp; are supposed to have got into
					Rochefort. two of Hawke's Fleet (of 70 &amp; 60 guns) out of eagerness ran aground, &amp; are lost,
					but most of the Men preserved, &amp; brought off. there is an end of the invasion, unless you are
					afraid of Thurot, who is hovering off Scotland. it is an odd contemplation, that <hi rend="italic">somebody</hi>
					 should have lived long enough to grow a great &amp; glorious Monarch. as to the Nation, I fear, it
					will not know how to behave itself, being just in the circumstances of a Chambermaid, that has got the 20,000£ Prize in the
					Lottery.</p>
         <p>You mistake me; I was always a Friend to <hi rend="italic">Employment,</hi> &amp; no Foe to Money: but they are no friends to each
					other. promise me to be always busy, &amp; I will allow you to be rich.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am Dear Mason, in all situations truly<lb/> Yours. </salute>
            <dateline>At Mr. Jauncey's, in Southampton Row ... Dec: 1. 1759.</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p> I received your letter, Nov: 29, the day on wch it is dated. a wonderful instance of expedition in the Post.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
