<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Beattie to Thomas Gray (1 May 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
                  <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
                  <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
                  <idno>AU MS 30/24/7/3</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 522, vol. iii, 1130-1132
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=522</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0600">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7009782">Aberdeen, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-05-01"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Hume, David</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Scotland</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0600">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Thomas Gray Esquire Regius Professor of Modern History Cambridge with a Book---To be forwarded by Mr Dilly</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute> Dear Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I troubled You with a letter some months ago, enclosing a specimen of a Poem, which I have some thoughts of finishing when I find myself at leisure.—The design of this, is to
					solicit Your acceptance of a Book called An Essay on Truth which M<hi rend="super">r</hi>
						Dilly Bookseller in London sends You by my desire. It is not such a present as I wish to make, but
					it is the best that is now in my power. You will think perhaps that I am very anxious to become a voluminous Author; but that is not
					the case. The present publication is the consequence of necessity rather than choice. I expect neither praise nor profit from it; nay,
					though it were to be succesful, which I am confident cannot happen, my vanity would not be flattered in the least; for I set no value
					on such performances. The occasion of my writing it was this. The business of my profession obliged me, when I first entered upon it,
					to be more conversant than I could have wished with our modern moral &amp; metaphysical writers. I had little relish for them from the
					first, and as I began to understand them better, I hated and despised them the more. Their principles and method of investigation
					seemed to me to be equally unfavourable to Science virtue and good taste. I saw with concern, that the Publick in general, and the
					people of this country in particular, were every day growing more and more attached to them; and I also saw, or thought I saw, that
					those who admired them most, understood them the least. I used to express myself on this subject with so little reserve in my Publick
					Lectures, that some degree of curiosity was excited in the small circle where I am known; and I found it was become necessary for me,
					if I would clear myself of the imputation of being a mere Declaimer and retailer of paradoxes, to publish my sentiments at large, with
					the grounds of them. This is what I have endeavoured to do in the book which now craves the honour of Your acceptance; I have not the
					face to add—and of Your perusal, for I should really be sorry to see You so ill employed, as in the study of a metaphysical
					controversy. Besides I know, that in England Metaphysick has not got such a footing as with us. Whether it be owing to the attachment
					which many among us have to a Countryman, or to something of a minute and sophistical spirit in the
					genius of our people, I know not; but certain it is, that we Scots are at present much inclined to be scepticks and metaphysicians.
					Every body here who can read, reads metaphysick, our writers write it, and our parsons preach it.—If You should at any time do
					my book the honour to look into it, may I hope that You will favour me with Your opinion of the Style: As to the doctrine, I dare say
					we are of the same mind. The style falls far short of my idea of good English: it is often stiff and pedantick in spite of all my
					endeavours to the contrary. I have indeed studied perspicuity more than elegance; because I know that my doctrine will be most
					favourably received by those who understand it best. I have frequently given a little into declamation, and something of a flippant
					drollery, both which I know are unsuitable to a philosophical enquiry. I did this, partly to amuse myself, and partly to [render
						m]y subject not altogether unentertaining.</p>
         <p> [In my l]ast I complained of bad health; I am no[w] much [better], and should be glad to hear that You a[re] well and happy.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute> For I am, with the most perfect regard and esteem Dear Sir<lb/> Your affectionate &amp; most humble servant </salute>
            <signed> J Beattie </signed>
            <dateline>Aberdeen 1<hi rend="super">st</hi> May 1770</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p> I know not what M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Foulis has done with his Milton. I thought it would have been finished long before now. I
						hope he has not neglected to send Your Homer.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
