<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (28 December 1767)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 178-179</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>4 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 185 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 459, vol. iii, 986-990
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=459</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXV, vol. iii, 163-168
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:163</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXII, vol. ii, 483-487
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:483</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLIII, vol. iv, 93-97
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:93</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0515">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1767-12-28"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0515">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Many &amp; various maladies have I labour'd under, since I left the north, but none of them (thanks to my summer expedition) <hi rend="italic">jusqu' a mourir.</hi> the gout came regularly, while I was in town, first in one, then in the other foot, but so
						tame you might have stroked it. since I got hither, <hi rend="italic">another</hi> of my troublesome
					companions for life has confined me to my room, but abstinence has (I believe) got the better of that too, &amp; to-morrow I go abroad
					again. I sent to your brother, before I left London, the <hi rend="italic">maps</hi> you wanted, the
						<hi rend="italic">Decouvertes des Russes,</hi>
					
					       <hi rend="italic">Voyage de Gmelin en Siberie,</hi>
					 Mr. Clerke of Chichester <hi rend="italic">on the Saxon coins,</hi>
					 Lee's <hi rend="italic">Linnæan Dictionary,</hi>
					
					       <hi rend="italic">Verrall's Cookery,</hi>
					 &amp; something else that I have forgot. as to Hudson's
					<hi rend="italic">Flora Anglica</hi> it is not to be had, being out of print: a new &amp; more correct edition is soon expected.
						Willughby's book of <hi rend="italic">fishes</hi> was never publish'd in English, so would not answer
					your end. that of <hi rend="italic">Birds</hi> is indeed in English, but not to be had in the shops &amp; sells at auctions from 30 to
					40 shillings, so I did not buy it without farther orders. I hope this cargo is safe arrived; &amp; another little one, that I sent to
					Miss Wharton &amp; Miss Peggy, directed to the former, to be left at Mr Tho: Wilkinson's in Durham:
					this went by the Newcastle Waggon about 6th of Dec:, &amp; contain'd twelve Flower-roots, viz: 3 Soleil d'or Narcissus, 2 White Italian
					d°: (N:B: of the Double white &amp; yellow Italian there are none to be had this year) 2 Pileus Cardinalis, red; 1 Kroon-vogel, 1
					Degeraad, double White; 1 Belle Grisdelin. 1 Hermaphrodite, &amp; 1 Incomparable, double blew; Hyacinths. for these you must get
					glasses from Newcastle. in the same box was a pocket Lens, wch Miss Wh: (if she pleased) was to give
					to Aunt Middleton, who wanted such a thing.</p>
				     <p>I desire to know, what you thought of Mason's plan for your ground (wch makes so pretty a figure on
					paper); &amp; whether <hi rend="italic">Summers</hi>
					 came to Old-Park to advise about planting. he is a very intelligent modest young Man, &amp; might be
					of great use there. has Miss Wh: served her time yet as a Bride-maid? I hope it may prove a good omen to her! does Miss Peggy rival Claude Lorraine yet, &amp; when does she go to York? do Debo &amp;
						Betty tend their Chrysalises, &amp; their samplers? is Kee's mouth
					as pretty as ever? does Robin read like a Doctor, dance like a Fairy, &amp; bow like a Courtier? does
						Dicky kick up his heels, &amp; study Geography? please to answer me as to all these particulars. my
					Thermometer presents her compliments to her country-sister, &amp; proposes now to open a correspondence with her. she lives against a
					pale in the garden with her back to the East at 9 o'clock in the morning precisely: at any other hour she is not visible, unless upon
					some great occasion. I was in London from 3 Nov: to 14 Dec:, during wch time the weather was commonly
					open, damp, &amp; mild, with the wind in the West, veering either to N: or S:. on the last mention'd day I found some Brambles &amp;
					Feverfew yet flowering in the hedges, &amp; in gardens the double Chrysanthemum, double Chamomile, Borage, Stocks, &amp; single
					Wall-flowers. these were all cut off on the 24th by an E: wind &amp; hard frost, Therm: at 31. next day &amp; today it was at 30. on
					the 26th a little snow fell, wch still lies &amp; freezes.</p>
				     <p>Our Ministry has taken in some odd Coadjutors not much to its credit or strength. it appear'd from
					the first day the Parliament met, that the Opposition were all to pieces among themselves, &amp; soon after the Duke of Bedf:d civilly
					declared to Mr Grenville, that he had the highest opinion of his abilities: but as it was contrary to his principles to keep up a
					constant opposition to the K:s measures, he must not wonder, if his Friends should drop the plan they had for sometime been pursuing.
					accordingly he made his terms, four or five of them were directly to be provided for: the rest were to wait till there was room. Ld Shelburne (the Sec:y), &amp; Mr Cook
					(Joint-Paymaster) were to have gone out, but Ld Chatham insisted on their staying in (it is said) &amp; prevail'd. Mr Conway
						retires, &amp; is to have the army, when Ld Ligonier dies: this is voluntary, I imagine. Ld
						Northington goes off with his pension. Ld Weymouth, &amp; Earl
						Gower supply their places, Mr Thynne is Master of ye Houshold. Ld
					Sandwich, Joint-Postmaster (Ld Hillsborough being created Secretary
					of State for America) Rigby is the other, that must come in (to what place I know not) &amp; conduct,
					I suppose, the House of Commons. how much better &amp; nobler would it have been to have left all these Beggars in the lurch? indeed
					what could be said against it, as all that could oppose the Ministry were already broke into three parts, &amp; one of them had declared publickly against the other two? I conclude the Rockingham-party
					will at last prevail, as they have some character &amp; credit with the People still left.</p>
				     <p>Adieu, my dear Sr. you have had, I hope, no returns of your asthma, since you lay in your own bed. my best respects to Mrs Wharton,
					&amp; love to all the family.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am ever <lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
					       <dateline>Dec: 28. 1767. Pemb: Coll: </dateline>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Shall I write out, &amp; send you, what Leland says of your neighbourhood? it is nothing but short
						notes taken in his journey: but that journey was towards the end of Henry 8th's reign just after the dissolution of Monasteries, wch
						makes it valuable.</p>
					       <p rendition="#center">SPECIMEN. </p>
					       <p>From St Andre's Akeland to Raby Castel 5 miles, part by arable,
						but more by pastures, &amp; morisch hilly ground, baren of wood. Raby is the largest Castel of Logginges in al the Northcuntery, &amp;
						is of a strong building: but not set ether on hil, or very strong ground. as I enterid by a causey into it there was a litle stagne on
						the right hond, and in the first area were but two toures, one at eche end, as Entres, &amp; no other buildid. yn the 2d area, as an
						Entring, was a great Gate of iren with a Tour, &amp; 2 or 3 mo on the right hond. then were al the chief Toures of the 3d Court, as in
						the hart of the castel. The Haul, &amp; al the Houses of Offices be large &amp; stately; &amp; in the haul I saw an incredible great
						beame of an Hart. the great Chaumber was exceding large, but now it is false-rofid, and devidid into 2 or 3 Partes. I saw ther a litle
						chaumber, wherein was in windows of colorid glass al the petigre of ye Nevilles, &amp;c: </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
