<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (9 August 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 112-113</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>1 page
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">210 mm x 161 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 274, vol. ii, 578
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=274</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXIX, vol. ii, 35-36
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:35</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXIV, vol. ii, 311-312
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:311</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXXII, vol. iii, 193-194
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:193</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0317">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1758-08-09"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0317">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton M:D: in</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Southampton Row, Bloomsbury</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>10 AV</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Stoke. Aug: 9 ... 1758. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Doctr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have been, since I saw you in Town, pretty much on the wing, at Hampton, Twickenham, &amp; elsewhere. I staid at the first of these
					places with the Cobhams two days &amp; should (I own) gladly have done so longer, but for the
						reason we talk'd about. the place spite of the weather is delightful: every little gleam of sunshine,
					every accident of light, opens some new beauty in the view, &amp; I never saw in so small a spot so much variety, &amp; so many natural
					advantages, nor ever hardly wish'd more for your company to partake of them. we were also at Hampton-Court, Sion, &amp; several places in the neighbourhood again, particularly at Ld Lincoln's, who (I think) is hurting his view by two plantations in front of his terrace, that regularly answer one another, &amp; are of an
					oval form with rustic buildings in the middle of them, a farm, dairies, &amp;c:. they stand on the opposite side of the water, &amp;
					(as they prosper) will join their shade to that of the hills in the horizon, exclude all the intermediate scene of enclosures, meadows,
					&amp; cattle feeding, &amp; reduce that great distance to nothing. this seems to be the advice of some new Gardiner, or Director of my
					Lord's Taste; his Successor perhaps may cut all down again.</p>
         <p>I shall beg the favor of you (as you were so kind to offer it) to buy us a Lottery-Ticket, if you
					find the Market will not be much lower than at present; &amp; (if you think it has no great hazard in it) enclose it to me here: I will
					take care to repay you as soon as I come to Town, or (if you chuse it) directly. my best respects to Mrs Wharton. pray let me hear
					soon, how you both are.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>believe me ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
