<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>James Beattie to Thomas Gray (6 December 1769)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
		                <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
		                <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
		                <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
		                <idno>AU MS 30/24/7/1</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 507*, vol. iii, 1082-1084
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=507*</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0567">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7009782">Aberdeen, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1769-12-06"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0567">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute> Dear Sir </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> For these three or four months past I have been in a state of dissipation and idleness, endeavouring if possible to rid myself of a
					vertigo which has troubled me much of late years, and which while it lasts disqualifies me entirely for reading and writing. If it had
					not been for this, I should long ere now have answered the very obliging letter I had the honour to receive from You in August last. Soon after I received it I wrote to M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Foulis, telling him that You had made
					choice of the Glasgow Homer, and desired to subscribe for two copies of the large paper of his Milton. That work is now begun; and is said by those who have seen a specimen to be one of the most magnificent books ever published in this
					country.</p>
				     <p> I wonder You can bring Yourself to think so meanly of the Installation-Ode; for You say it can only live a few days. I am quite
					certain this is a mistake; it will make the name of the Duke of Grafton known as long as the English language is understood; which is
					an honour, no other great man of this age has any chance of obtaining at the hands of the muses. I will not say that this Ode is equal
					to some of Your other poems; but I will venture to affirm that it is the finest panegyrical poem in the world. The whole is contrived
					and executed in the highest Dithyrambick taste. The beginning and end peculiarly excellent. The figure of Newton is exceeded by nothing in descriptive poetry. When You adopt the <hi>liquid language of the skies</hi>, Your
					sentiments words and numbers are perfectly Elysian. That happiness of expression for which You are so very remarkable, appears
					throughout.—'And bid it round heaven's altars shed The fragrance of its blushing head' is only
					one instance, but it is a signal one. I known not whether I most admire the propriety of the metaphor, the beauty of the image, or the
					delicacy of the expression: all the three are in perfection. Your imitation of Milton is delightful.
					The poetry is exquisite, and the imitation exact: but it has another claim to my approbation. I have always thought the hymn on the
					nativity, notwithstanding its faults, to be one of the finest poems in the world; I think I am intoxicated, or rather bewitched with
					it: and Your making choice of it for an object of Your imitation seems to justify my opinion of it.—But I cannot within the
					compass of a letter say one half of what I have to say in praise of Your poem. I have heard some people object to its obscurity; but
					sure their attention must be very superficial, or their apprehension very weak, who do so. I understood every word of it at the first
					reading, except one passage (which however I made out at the second) where the printer had made nonsense, by placing a full point at
					the end of a line where there ought to have been no point at all. Do, Sir, permit us to hope, now when
					Your hand is in again, that You will not abandon the muses. This age is indeed nowise remarkable for good qualities of any kind: taste
					and learning were never I believe less attended to in any period since the revival of letters; but still there are a few honest and
					sensible folks among us, whom it is certainly worth while to do something to please. My attention was never more awakened than when I
					found by the newspapers that You was to compose this Installation-ode; if You knew half the pleasure I received from it, You would not
					wonder that I am so very anxious to see more of Your works. I hope You have no vertigo's or headachs to excuse You: God forbid. May You
					long, very long, live healthy and happy.</p>
				     <p> It is a strange transition, and yet I must now speak a little of my own works. I told You in my last, that I had begun a kind of poem, and I promised to send a specimen, which accordingly I have enclosed. The piece will consist of three books of which near two are finished; but bad health and necessary business
					have prevented my making any additions these six months. However I am in no hurry. As this will probably be the last of my poetical
					compositions I propose to finish it at great leisure. It is indeed the only one of them for which I have any esteem; which perhaps is
					owing to its being the latest. Whether it will have any merit or not I cannot say; I am sure my other things have very little. The
					title of this piece is <hi>The Minstrel</hi>. The first hint of it was suggested by M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Percy's Essay on the
					English Minstrels. There was something in the character of the Minstrel there described, which struck
					me and pleased me. I suppose my Hero born in a solitary and mountainous country; by trade a shepherd. His imagination is wild and
					romantick; but in the first part of his life he has hardly any opportunity of acquiring knowledge, except from that part of the book of
					nature which is open before him. The first Canto is a kind of poetical or sentimental history of this period. In the second he meets
					with a Hermit, who in his youth had been a man of the world, and who instructs Edwin (the young Minstrel) in history, philosophy,
					musick, &amp;c. The young man, agreably to that character which he bears from the beginning, shows a strong attachment to poetry, which
					the old hermit endeavours by all possible means to discourage. Edwin seems disposed to follow his advice, and abandon the muses; when
					an irruption of Danes or robbers (I have not as yet determined which) strips him of his little all, and obliges him through necessity
					to take his harp on his shoulder, and go abroad into the world in the character of a Minstrel. And here the poem is to end.—The
					measure is the same with that of Spenser in the fairy queen; but I have avoided all antiquated expressions. I chose this measure,
					partly because it seemed to suit my Gothick subject; but chiefly because it is extremely agreable to my ear, and seems to admit greater
					varieties in the composition than any other English stanza. The passage I have sent you for a specimen is in my judgment neither one of
					the best nor one of the worst. It is taken from the first book, which describes the hero's pursuits and amusements in the first years
					of his life. I beg Your pardon for sending it in so bad order. I cut it out of a book to save the labour of transcribing, which the
					present state of my health would render a very uneasy work. The numbers of the stanza's will direct to the order in which they are to
					be read. You need not return them as I have another copy.</p>
				     <p>[           ]</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
