<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (25 November 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 103</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 536, vol. iii, 1150-1151
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=536</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXXIV, vol. iii, 296-298
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:296</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXXII, vol. v, 114-115
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:114</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0615">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-11-25"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0615">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk by Norwich</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>25 Nov: 1770. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I do not see, why you should suppose that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> only are to have the privilege of being ill. for me, from the
					time you left me (till within these three days) I have been only one day out of the walls of this college. that day was employ'd in
					going to the Hills by way of airing after the gout, &amp; in catching such a cold &amp; cough as has
					given me no rest night or day, &amp; has only now taken its leave of me. I sent away your letter to B: directly: I saw no reason
					against it. he was then at Aubonne near Geneva with his Brother, &amp; is now at Berne. the picture
					is not arrived, nor (I suppose) ever will; tho' he says, he has sent it, but by what conveyance, or by what hand he does not say.</p>
         <p>You do me wrong: I have thought very frequently of you, &amp; especially since Sr A: Allen's death.
					I am rather glad his family were about him, tho' I know not well why, for he perhaps was insensible to it. these sort of deaths are
					alarming to the Spectator; but perhaps the best for the Sufferer. I have now every day before my eyes a Woman of ninety, my
						Aunt, who has for many years been gradually turning into chalk-stones: they are making their way out
					of the joints of both feet, &amp; the Surgeon twice a day comes to increase the torture. she is just as sensible &amp; as impatient of
					pain, &amp; as intractable as she was 60 years ago. she thinks not at all of death, &amp; if a mortification does not come to release
					her, may lie in this agony for months (at least) helpless &amp; bed-rid. this is what you call a <hi rend="italic">natural</hi>
					death!</p>
         <p>It is well, you live in a dry country, but do not your lakes overflow? can any thing get from
						Norwich to Blundeston? 200,000 acres are drown'd in the Fens here &amp; cattle innumerable. our
					Friends at Worcester, Gloucester, &amp;c: are sailing thro' the streets from house to house. Adieu!
					the Post is impatient. my respects to Mrs N:,</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am<lb/> Faithfully Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
