<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (23 October 1760)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
                  <institution key="HSPO">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</institution>
                  <repository>Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 322, vol. ii, 706-707
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=322</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LVII, 223-226
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1853/1/223</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCX, vol. ii, 170-172
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/170</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0371">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1760-10-23"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Macpherson, James, 1736-1796</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Stuart, James</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Macpherson, James, 1736-1796</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Ware Park</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Rochefort</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Chatsworth</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Calais</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Belleisle</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0371">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Oct: 23. 1760. South:n. Row. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am obliged to you for your Letter, &amp; the Bills enclosed, wch I shall take the first
					opportunity I have to satisfy.</p>
         <p>I imagine by this time Ld J: is, or has been, with you to settle matters. Mr Onley (from whom I have twice heard) consents, tho' with great diffidence of himself, to undertake this task: but
					can not well be there himself, till about the 13th of Nov:r. I would gladly hear, what your first
					impressions are of the young Man, for (I must tell you plainly) our M:n, who had seen him at Chatsworth, was not greatly edified, but he hopes the best. tomorrow Dr Gisborne &amp; I go to dine with that
					reverend Gentleman at Kensington during his waiting. he makes many kind enquiries after you, but I see very little of him, he is so
					taken up with the Beaux-Arts. he has lately etch'd my head with his own hand; &amp; his friend Mr
					Sandby, the Landscape-Painter, is doing a great picture with a view of M: Snowdon, the Bard, Edward the first, &amp;c: now all this I take for a Bribe, a sort of Hush-money to me, who caught him last year sitting for his own
						picture; &amp; know, that at this time, there is another Painter doing one of the scenes in
					Elfrida.</p>
         <p>In my way to Town I met with the first news of the expedition from Sr Wm Williams, who makes a part of it, &amp; perhaps may lay his fine Vandyke-Head in the dust. they talk some of
					Rochefort, some of Brest, &amp; others of Calais. it is sure the preparations are great, but the wind blows violently. </p>
         <p>You hear a great deal of a murther said to be committed at a Bagnio in Long Acre, tho' the party was carried to die at a house in
					Mary-bone. two of the Persons named as <hi rend="italic">of the company</hi> that night are Sir William Fowler, a young Officer, &amp;
					one Mr Sutton, a Merchant's Son in the City. God knows, what truth there is in it or what was the meaning of it. [ ] is said to be he,
					[ ] was hanged up by [ ] in a silken-rope, &amp; so left hanging, but the W(a)iter cut him down; &amp; that all this happened the same
						night.
				</p>
         <p>Here is a 2d Edition of the Fragments with a new &amp; fine one added to them. you will perhaps
					soon see a very serious elegy (but this is a secret) on the death of my Lady Coventry. watch for
					it.</p>
         <p>If I had been aware, Mr Mapletoft was in Town, I should have return'd him the two Guineas I have of
					his. neither Osborne, nor Bathurst know, when the Book will come
					out; I will therefore pay it to any one he pleases.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, Dear Sr, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I did not mean to carry away your paper of the two pictures at Ware-Park: but I find I have got it
						here. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
