<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (16 July 1769)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
		                <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
		                <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
		                <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
		                <idno>AU MS 30/24/6/7</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 501, vol. iii, 1070-1072
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=501</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iii, section v, 348-350
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:348</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, fragment, letter no. CCCXLVIII, vol. iii, 228-230
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:228</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, letter IV, vol. ii, 516-517
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:516</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section V, letter V, vol. iv, 137-138
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:137</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLIII, vol. ii, 134-135
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:134</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter III, vol. i, 445-446
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:445</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0560">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1769-07-16"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0560">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have been so unfortunate as to lose the pleasure of seeing your two Friends Dr Gerard &amp; Mr
					Duncan. when they pass'd thro' this place, I was at London; &amp; tho' Ld Strathmore told me, there was a Gentleman, who had letters
					for me, he coud not tell me where he was lodged. after my return hither, when they (I suppose) were
					leaving London, I received your letter by the post.</p>
				     <p>The late ceremony of the D: of Grafton's Installation has hinder'd me from acknowledging sooner the
					satisfaction your friendly compliment gave me. I thought myself bound in gratitude to his Grace unasked to take upon me the task of
					writing those verses, that are usually set to musick on this occasion. I do not think them worth sending you, because they are by
					nature doom'd to live but a single day, or if their existence is prolong'd beyond that date, it is only by means of news-paper
						parodies, &amp; witless criticism. this sort of abuse I had reason
					to expect, but did not think it worth while to avoid it.</p>
				     <p>Mr Foulis is magnificent in his gratitude: I can not figure to myself, how it can be worth his while
					to offer me such a present. you can judge better of this than I, &amp; if he does not hurt himself by it, I would accept the <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi>
					 with many thanks. I have not got, nor even seen it.</p>
				     <p>I could wish to subscribe to his new edition of Milton, &amp; desire to be set down for two copies
					of ye large paper: but you must inform me where &amp; when I may pay the money.</p>
				     <p>You have taught me to long for a second letter, &amp; particularly for what you say will make the contents of it: I have nothing to requite it with, but plain &amp; friendly truth, &amp; that you shall have, join'd to a
					zeal for your fame, &amp; a pleasure in your success.</p>
				     <p>I am now setting forward on a journey towards the North of England, but it will not reach so far as I should wish, as I must return
					hither before Michaelmas, &amp; shall barely have time to visit a few places &amp; a few Friends. </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am, Sr, faithfully &amp; sincerely <lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>If you favor me with a letter soon, be pleased to direct <hi rend="italic">at Tho: Wharton's Esq</hi> of Old-Park near Darlington,
						Durham. To be left at Sunderland-Bridge.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
