<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (9 May 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 142-143</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">204 mm x 161 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 333, vol. ii, 735-737
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=333</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXX, vol. ii, 212-213
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:212</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XCVI, vol. ii, 384-386
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:384</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CIV, vol. iii, 280-282
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:280</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0383">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-05-09"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">York</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Worcester</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0383">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton at</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Old-Park near</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>9 MA GR</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have been very naughty, I confess; but I informed your Brother a good while ago, that both your
					letters came safe to my hands. the first indeed wch went to Cambridge, had had its seal broken, wch naturally I should have attributed
					to the curiosity of somebody at Durham: but as Mr. Brown (who, you know, is care itself) sent it me without taking notice of any such
					thing, I rather believe it was mere accident, &amp; happen'd, after it had pass'd thro' his hands. </p>
         <p>I long to see you, but my visit must be defer'd to another year, for Mr. Jauncey having lost his
						Bishop, &amp; having settled his Son in a Curacy, means to let his house entire, &amp; in September
					I shall be forced to look out for another place, &amp; must have the plague of removing. the glass-manufacture in Worcester:re (I am told) has fail'd. Mr. Price here has left off business, &amp;
					retired into Wales: the Person, who succeeds him, does not pretend to be acquainted with all the secrets of his art. the Man at
						York is now in Town, exhibiting some specimens of his skill to the Society of Arts: him (you say)
					you have already consulted. coats of arms will doubtless be expensive (Price used to have five Guineas for a very plain one) figures
					much more so. unless therefore you can pick up some remnants of old painted glass, wch are sometimes met with in farm-houses, little
					out-of-the-way churches &amp; vestries, and even at country-glasiers shops, &amp;c: I should advice to buy plain colour'd glass (for
					wch they ask here in St Martin's Lane 5S: a pound, but it is sold at York for 2 or 3S:) &amp; make up the tops of your windows in a
					mosaïck of your own fancy. the glass will come to you in square plates, (some part of wch is always wrinkled &amp; full of little
					bubbles, so you must allow for waste), any glasier can cut it into <hi rend="italic">quarrels,</hi> &amp; you can dispose the pattern
					&amp; colours, red, blew, purple, &amp; yellow (there is also green, if you like it) as well or better than the Artisan himself, &amp;
					certainly much cheaper. I would not border it with the same, least the room should be too dark. nor should the <hi rend="italic">quarrels</hi> of clear glass be too small (in the lower part of the window); if they are but turn'd corner-ways, it is enough to give
					it a gothic aspect. if there is anything to see (tho' it be but a tree) I should put a very large diamond-pane in the midst of each
					division.</p>
         <p>I had rather Major G: throw'd away his money, than somebody else. it is not worth while even to
					succeed, unless <hi rend="italic">gratis;</hi>
					 nor in any case to be attempted without the B:s absolute
					concurrence. I wish you joy of Dr Squire's Bishoprick: he keeps both his livings, &amp; is the
					happiest of Devils. Stonhewer, who is coming, will (if you see him) tell you more news vivâ voce, than I could write: I therefore do
					not tap that chapter.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>my best services to Mrs. Wharton, I am ever truly<lb/> Yours</salute>
            <dateline>May 9. 1761. </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I am at last going to Cambridge: it is strange else.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
