<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (27 December 1746)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 17-18</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 185 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 129, vol. i, 259-261
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=129</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section iv, 205
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:205</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 144
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:144</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXXII, vol. i, 151-154
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:151</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter IX, vol. ii, 167-169
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:167</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XIV, vol. iii, 26-29
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:26</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0147">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1746-12-27"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Whalley, John, 1698 or 9-1748</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Warton, Joseph</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Marsham, Sir John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hénault, President</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Diogenes Laertius</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Collins, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bentley, Richard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0147">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>My Dear Wharton.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have received your Bill, &amp; am in Confusion to hear, you have got in Debt yourself in Order to bring me out of it: I did not
					think to be obliged to you so much, nor on such Terms: but imagined you would be here, &amp; might easily spare it. the Money shall be repaid as soon as ever it is wanted, &amp; sooner if the Stocks rise a little higher. my
					Note you will find at the End of my Letter, wch you ought to have, <hi rend="italic">ἐάν</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">τι</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">κατὰ</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">τὸ</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ἀνθρώπινον</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">συμβαίνῃ</hi>: the rest of my Acknowledgements are upon Record, where they ought to
					be, with the rest of your Kindnesses. the Bill was paid me here; I suppose there is no Likelihood of its being stop'd in Town.</p>
         <p>It surprises me to hear you talk of so much Business, &amp; the Uncertainty of your Return; &amp; what not? sure you will find Time
					to give me an Account of your Transactions, &amp; your Intentions. for your Ears, don't let 'em think of marrying you! for I know if
					you marry at all, you will <hi rend="italic">be married.</hi> I mean, passively. &amp; then (besides repenting of what you were not
					guilty of) you will never go abroad, never read any thing more, but Farriery-Books, and Justice-Books, &amp; so either die of a
					Consumption; or live on, &amp; grow fat, wch is worse. for me &amp; my Retirement (for you are in the Right to despise my Dissipation
					de quinze Jours) we are in the midst of Diog: Laertius &amp; his Philosophers, as a Proœmium to the
					Series of their Works, &amp; those of all the Poets &amp; Orators, that lived before Philip of Macedon's Death: &amp; we have made a
					great Chronological Table with our own Hands, the Wonder &amp; Amazement of Mr Brown; not so much for
					Publick Events, tho' these too have a Column assign'd them, but rather in a literary Way, to compare the Times of all great Men, their
					Writeings &amp; Transactions. it begins at the 30th Olympiad, &amp; is already brought down to the 113th; that is, 332 Years. our only
					Modern Assistants, are Marsham, Dodwell, &amp; Bentley. [Tuthill] continues quiet in his Læta Paupertas, &amp; by this Time (were
					not his Friends of it) would have forgot there was any such Place as Pembroke in the World. All Things there are just in Statu quo;
					only the Fellows, as I told you, are grown pretty rudish to their Sovereign in general, for Francis
					is now departed. poor dear Mr Delaval indeed has had a little Misfortune. Intelligence was brought,
					that he had with him a certain Gentlewoman properly call'd Nell Burnet, (but whose Nom de Guerre was Capt:n Hargraves) in an Officer's
					Habit, whom he had carried all about to see Chappels &amp; Libraries, &amp; make Visits in the Face of Day. the Master raised his
					Posse-Comitatus in Order to search his Chambers, &amp; after long Feeling &amp; Snuffleing about the Bed, he declared they had
					certainly been there. wch was very true, &amp; the Captain was then locked up in a Cupboard there, while his Lover stood below in Order
					to convey him out at Window, when all was over. however they took Care not to discover her, tho' the Master affirm'd; had he but caught
					her, he would soon have known, whether it was a Man, or a Woman. upon this Mr Del: was desired to cut out his Name, &amp; did so: next
					Day Dr L: repented, &amp; wrote a Paper to testify he never knew any Hurt of him, wch he brought to Dr Whaley, who would have directly admitted him here, if Stuart had not absolutely
					refused. he was offer'd about at several Colleges, but in vain. then Dr L: call[ed] two Meetings to
					get him re-admitted there, but every one was inexorable &amp; so he has lost his Pupil, who is gone,
					I suppose, to lie with his Aunt Price. Trollope continues in Dev'reux-Court: all our Hopes are now in the Commencement.
				</p>
         <p>Have you seen the Works of two young Authors, a Mr Warton &amp; a Mr Collins, both Writers of Odes? it is odd enough, but each is the half of a considerable Man, &amp; one the
					Counter-Part of the other. the first has but little Invention, very poetical choice of Expression, &amp; a good Ear. the second, a fine
					Fancy, model'd upon the Antique, a bad Ear, great Variety of Words, &amp; Images with no Choice at all. they both deserve to last some
					Years, but will not.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! dear Sr I am very sincerely Yours</salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
            <dateline>Dec: 27 I was 30 Year old yesterday. what is it o'clock by you?</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
