<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (9 November 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 118-119</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>1 page
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">200 mm x 157 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 282, vol. ii, 591-592
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=282</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXVII, vol. ii, 58-60
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:58</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXIX, vol. ii, 324-325
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:324</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXXVII, vol. iii, 208-209
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:208</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0325">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1758-11-09"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Descamps, Jean-Baptiste</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0325">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Wharton, M:D:, in</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Southampton-Row, Bloomsbury</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>10 NO</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Nov:  1758. Stoke.</dateline>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>My judgement is, that if your picture possess but any one of the beauties you see &amp; describe in it, it must be certainly worth
					eight or ten times as much as you gave for it. I only wonder, you should forget to say by what lucky chance you came by it. Old <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi>
					 was a Dutch Master of some note: the history of that School I am very little acquainted with, but if
					I am not mistaken, there was lately publish'd a French account of their lives in two or more Volumes,
					4to, wch I have seen at Nourse's, in wch you may meet with better information.</p>
         <p>I am agreeably employ'd here in dividing <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> with an old <hi rend="italic">Harridan,</hi>
					 who is the spawn of Cerberus &amp; the Dragon of Wantley. When I shall get to Town I can not divine,
					but doubtless it will be between this &amp; Christmas. you were so good to offer me house-room for some of my lumber: I am therefore
					packing up certain boxes &amp; baskets, wch I believe you will be troubled with. but I beg Mrs Wharton to consider well first, whether
					it will be inconvenient to her. if she assures me, it will not, I shall inform you shortly of their shapes &amp; numbers. at present it
					seems to me, that there will be 3 or 4 large boxes; &amp; five baskets of China: the rest Madam Foster
					shall accommodate.</p>
         <p>Ah poor King of Prussia! what will become of him? I am told here, that matters are much worse, than is yet avowed. I also hear that seven Generals have refused the command, wch Hopson is now
					gone with, who has been before censured for ill conduct, &amp; is besides so infirm, that he will not live the voyage.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, Dear Sr, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
