<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (22 January 1759)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 287, vol. ii, 610-611
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=287</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXXIII, 141-143
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:141</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXXIII, vol. ii, 72-74
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:72</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0332">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7029839">Aston, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1759-01-22"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0332">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Aston Jan: 22d –58</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mr Gray </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I cannot help sending you a line to desire that if you can spare a moment from buying &amp; selling of South sea annuities, taking
					inventorys of Old China jars &amp; three legd stools with black feet &amp; grass-green velvit bottoms, you would write me word how you
					do. I ask not criticisms, nor hints, nor emendations these at your leisure, for my tythes are come in, I live within tolerable compass
					&amp; therefore I care not a fig whether Caractacus goes forth or no, evn tho he should bring me as much as Cleone did to my Printer they both begin with a C wch is a good omen.</p>
				     <p>Since your last I writ as you bid me (or to speak more gramatically) bad me to Mr. H &amp; recd his answer he says, "I coud not but smile at Dr Whartons petition. As what I had to say of that
						wretch was no extraordinary pass of pate I may the easier be inducd to make a sacrifice of it to <hi rend="italic">Humanity.</hi> Yet I promise nothing. there will be time enough to think of this for the publication is necessarily
					delayd by the late accident for sometime."</p>
				     <p>This accident was no less than the [loss of the] MS. of his last dialogue on the
						Constitution, by the carelessness of a Leicester bookseller, &amp; he is afraid wont be recoverd if
					so hell have it all to compose afresh from some loose notes. This youll say is a warning for Caractacus, &amp; indeed it does not suit
					his dignity to ride Post, like a lad newly elected at Whites He shall therefore stay with you; for Hurd is returning to
						Thurcaston &amp; I fancy will come to see me, if not Ill go to see him with my own Copy, before I
					think of publishing. I send you at the Bottom a peice of a new stanza for the 2d Ode. I know not if you will not think the rhymes too
					antiquated, or whether it is not a sort of Beauty in the place –
				</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>most sincerely yours. </salute>
					       <signed>W MASON. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I. 2<lb/>
					       </p>
					       <p>Evry Heath &amp; Mountain rude <lb/> Was mute till then, save from the den <lb/> Where watchd some Giant proud, <lb/> The Heifer,
						cag'd in craggy pen, <lb/> Lifted her lowings loud; <lb/> While her fair firstlings streaming gore <lb/> Distaind the
						bone-besprinkled floor. <lb/> Dismal notes! &amp; answered soon. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
