<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (13 December 1765)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 418, vol. ii, 906-908
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=418</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 359-361
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 234, vol. ii, 244-248
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/244</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXX, vol. iii, 97-100
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/97</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXIV, vol. ii, 461-464
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/461</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXXV, vol. iv, 67-70
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iv/1/67</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXVI, vol. ii, 98-101
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/2/98</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 146-148
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=146</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter XVI, vol. i, 561-563
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/561</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0472">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1765-12-13"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Sévigné, Mme de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Newcastle, Margaret Duchess of</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Rheims</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0472">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Cambridge, December 13, 1765. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I am very much obliged to you for the detail you enter into on the subject of your own health: in this you cannot be too
					circumstantial for me, who had received no account of you, but at second hand – such as, that you were dangerously ill, and
					therefore went to France; that you meant to try a better climate, and therefore staid at Paris; that you had relapsed, and were
					confined to your bed, and extremely in vogue, and supped in the best company, and were at all public diversions. I rejoice to find
					(improbable as it seemed) that all the wonderful part of this is strictly true, and that the serious part has been a little
					exaggerated. This latter I conclude not so much from your own account of yourself, as from the spirits in which I see you write; and
					long may they continue to support you! I mean in a reasonable degree of elevation: but if (take notice) they are so volatile, so
					flippant, as to suggest any of those doctrines of health, which you preach with all the zeal of a French atheist; at least, if they
					really do influence your practice; I utterly renounce them and all their works. They are <hi rend="italic">evil spirits,</hi> and will
					lead you to destruction. – You have long built your hopes on temperance, you say, and hardiness. On the first point we are
					agreed. The second has totally disappointed you, and <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> you will persist in it; by all means. But then be
					sure to persist too in being young, in stopping the course of time, and making the shadow return back upon your sun-dial. If you find
					this not so easy, acquiesce with a good grace in my <hi rend="italic">anilities,</hi> put on your understockings of yarn or woollen,
					even in the night-time. Don't provoke me! or I shall order you two night-caps (which by the way would do your eyes good), and put a
					little of any French liqueur into your water: they are nothing but brandy and sugar, and among their various flavours some of them may
					surely be palatable enough. The pain in your feet I <hi rend="italic">can</hi> bear; but I shudder at the sickness in your stomach, and
					the weakness, that still continues. I conjure you, as you love yourself; I conjure you by Strawberry, not to trifle with these
					edge-tools. There is no cure for the gout, when in the stomach, but to throw it into the limbs. There is no relief for the gout in the
					limbs, but in gentle warmth and gradual perspiration.</p>
         <p>I was much entertained with your account of our neighbours. As an Englishman and an Antigallican, I rejoice at their dulness and
					their nastiness: though I fear we shall come to imitate them in both. Their atheism is a little too much, too shocking to rejoice at. I
					have been long sick at it in their authors, and hated them for it: but I pity their poor innocent people of fashion. They were bad
					enough, when they believed every thing! </p>
         <p>I have searched where you directed me; which I could not do sooner, as I was at London when I received your letter, and could not
					easily find her grace's works. Here they abound in every library. The print you ask after is the
					frontispiece to <hi rend="italic">Nature's pictures drawn by Fancy's pencil.</hi>
					 But lest there should be any mistake, I must tell you, the family are not at dinner, but sitting
					round a rousing fire and telling stories. The room is just such a one as we lived in at Rheims: I
					mean as to the glazing and ceiling. The chimney is supported by cariatides: over the mantle-piece the arms of the family. The duke and
					duchess are crowned with laurel. A servant stands behind him, holding a hat and feather. Another is shutting a window. Diepenbecke
					delin. &amp; (I think) S. Clouwe sculps. It is a very pretty and curious print, and I thank you for
					the sight of it. If it ever was a picture, what a picture to have!</p>
         <p>I must tell you, that upon cleaning an old picture here at St. John's Lodge, which I always took for a Holbein; on a ring, which the figure wears, they have found H. H. It has been always called [Bp] Fisher; but is plainly a layman, and probably sir Anthony Denny, who was a
					benefactor to the college.</p>
         <p>What is come of your Sevigné-curiosity? I should be glad of a line now and then, when you have
					leisure.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I wish you well, and am ever<lb/> Yours, </salute>
            <signed>T. GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
