<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (3 August 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 73</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 482, vol. iii, 1039-1040
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=482</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter lix, section iv, 332
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:332</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXXIII, vol. iii, 205-206
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:205</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXL, vol. ii, 505
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:505</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CLV, vol. iv, 125-126
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:125</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XI, vol. v, 75-77
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:75</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXIX, vol. ii, 127
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:127</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LIX, vol. i, 431
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:431</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0539">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-08-03"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Brockett, Lawrence, 1724-1768</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Grafton, Augustus Henry Fitzroy, Duke of, 1735-1811</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Lort, Michael, 1725-1790</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0539">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>3 AV DW</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>3 Aug: 1768. Jermyn-Street <lb/> (Mr Roberts's).</dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>That Mr. Brockett has broke his neck, you will have seen in the News-papers; &amp; also that I (your
					humble Servant) have kiss'd the K:s hand for his succession. they both are true, but the manner how you know not; only I can assure
					you, that I had no hand at all in his fall, &amp; <hi rend="italic">almost</hi> as little in the second happy event. he died on the
					Sunday, on Wednesday following, his Gr: of Grafton wrote me a very polite letter to say, that his Maj: had commanded him to <hi rend="italic">offer</hi> me the vacant Professorship, not only as a reward of &amp;c: but as a credit to &amp;c: with much more too
					high for me to transcribe. <hi rend="italic">You are to say,</hi> that I owe my nomination to the <hi rend="italic">whole
						Cabinet-Council,</hi> &amp; my success to the K:s <hi rend="italic">particular knowledge of me.</hi> this last he told me himself,
					tho' the day was so hot &amp; the ceremony so embarrassing to me, that I hardly know what he said.</p>
         <p>I am commission'd to make you an offer, wch, I have told him (not the King) you would not accept, long ago. Mr. Barrett (whom you know) offers to you 100£ a-year with meat, drink, washing, chaise, &amp; lodging, if you will
					please to accompany him thro' France into Italy. he has taken such a fancy to you, that I can not but do what he desires me, being
					pleased with him for it. I know, it will never do, tho' before you grew a rich fat Rector, I have often wish'd (ay, &amp; fish'd too)
					for such an opportunity. no matter! I desire you to write your answer to him yourself as civil, as you think fit, &amp; then let me
					know the result. that's all. He lives at <hi rend="italic">Lee near Canterbury.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Adieu! I am to perish here with heat this fortnight yet, &amp; then to Cambridge. Dr M: (Mr Vicecan:) came post hither to ask this vacant office on Wednesday last, &amp; went post to carry the
					news back on Saturday. the rest were Delaval, Lort, Peck, &amp; Jebb. as to Lort, he deserved it,
					&amp; Delaval is an honest Gentleman: the rest do me no great honor, no more than my Predecessor did: to be sure, my <hi rend="italic">Dignity</hi> is a little the worse for wear, but mended &amp; wash'd it will do for me.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am very sincerely<lb/> Yours, </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
