<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (8 January 1768)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 461, vol. iii, 992-995
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=461</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXIX, 411-414
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:411</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXVII, vol. iii, 170-172
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:170</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0517">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1768-01-08"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0517">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I did not write to you–that's to be sure: but then consider, I had the gout great part of the time, that I pass'd in Town;
					&amp; eversince I came hither I have been confined to my room; &amp; besides, you know, you were at Aston, &amp; did not much care. as
					to Mons:r de la Harpe he is not to be had at any of the shops, &amp; (they say) never was in England.
					what I saw &amp; liked of his, must have been in some <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheque</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> that I had
					borrow'd.</p>
				     <p>Here are, or have been, or will be all your old &amp; new Friends in constant expectation of you at Cambridge, yet Christmas is past,
					&amp; no Scroddles appears! </p>
				     <q>
					       <p>Prim <hi rend="italic">Hurd</hi>
						 attends your call, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Palgrave</hi> proud,
						<lb/>
						         <hi rend="italic">Stonhewer</hi> the lewd, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Delaval</hi>
						 the loud.<lb/> For thee does <hi rend="italic">Powel</hi>
						 squeeze, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Marriot</hi>
						 sputter,<lb/> And <hi rend="italic">Glyn</hi>
						 cut phizzes, &amp; Tom <hi rend="italic">Nevile</hi>
						 stutter.<lb/>
						         <hi rend="italic">Brown</hi> sees thee sitting on his nose's tip,<lb/> The <hi rend="italic">Widow</hi> feels thee in her aching
						hip,<lb/> For thee fat <hi rend="italic">Nanny</hi> sighs, &amp; handy <hi rend="italic">Nelly,</hi>
						
						         <lb/> And <hi rend="italic">Balguy</hi> with a Bishop in his belly!
					</p>
				     </q>
				     <p>it is true, of the two Archdeacons, the latter is now here, but goes on Monday: the former comes to
					take his degree in February. the Rector writes to ask, whether you are come, that he may do the same.
					as to Johnny, here he is, divided between the thoughts of fornication &amp; marriage. Delaval only
					waits for a little intreaty. the Masters, the Doctor, the
						Poet, &amp; the President, are very pressing &amp; warm; but none so
					warm as the Coffee-house and I. come then away: this is no season for planting, &amp; Ld R:d will <hi rend="italic">grow</hi> as well without your cultivation as with it. at least let us know, what we are to hope for, &amp; when: if it
					be only for the satisfaction of the Methodist Singing-Man, your Landlord.</p>
				     <p>You will finish your <hi rend="italic">Opus magnum</hi>
					 here so clever, &amp; your Series of historical Tragedies with your
					books (that no body reads) all round you; &amp; your Critick at hand, who never cares a farthing (that I must say for him) whether you
					follow his opinion or not; &amp; your Hypercriticks, that nobody (not even themselves) understands, tho' you think, you do. I am sorry
					to tell you, St John's garden is quite at a stand: perhaps you in person may set it going: if not, here is Mr Brown's little
						garden cries aloud to be laid out (it is in a wretched state to be sure, &amp; without any
						taste) you shall have unlimited authority over it, &amp; I will take upon me the whole expence. won't
					you come? I know, you will.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I am ever <lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
					       <dateline>8 Jan: 1768. Pemb: Coll: </dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
