<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Norton Nicholls to Thomas Gray (27 November 1769)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 508, vol. iii, 1085-1087
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=508</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLV, vol. iii, 264-266
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:264</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXIII, vol. v, 97-100
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:97</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0568">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011197">Bath, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1769-11-27"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0568">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Bath, Nov. 27, 1769. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have two reasons for writing, one because it seems an age to me since I heard of you, the other to mention that I have taken the
					liberty of recommending to your notice Mr. de Bonstetten. I have given him a letter to you, but yet I
					thought it best to apprise you of it, that he might not come an entire stranger. I picked him out from among the mob in the rooms
						here, and like him very much; I shall be a little disappointed if you do not think him better than
					common for his age, and very little spoiled considering that he is the only son of the treasurer of Berne, and of one of the six noble
					families which bear the chief sway in the aristocracy. He was first at the university of Lausanne; afterwards his father sent for him
					home; then he went to Leyden, but thought Holland a most triste pays, and begged to be released, so he had leave to cross over to
					England; he seems to have read, and to be unwilling now to waste his time if he knew how to employ it; I think he is vastly better than
					any thing English (of the same age) I ever saw; and then, I have a partiality to him because he was born among mountains; and talks of
					them with enthusiasm–of the forests of pines which grow darker and darker as you ascend, till the <hi rend="italic">nemorum
						nox</hi>
					 is completed, and you are forced to grope your way; of the cries of eagles and other birds of prey
					adding to the horror; in short, of all the wonders of his country, which disturb my slumbers in Lovingland. I made Wheeler acquainted with him, who likes him as well as I, and has
					given him letters to Mr. Pitt and to Mrs. Hay, which have succeeded
					very well. When I go into Switzerland I am to be so directed! so recommended! and to travel with such advantages! but it is absolutely
					necessary to pass a month at Zurich to learn German; and the mountains must be traversed on foot; avec des Grimpons aux mains, and
					shoes of a peculiar construction. I'd give my ears to try.</p>
				     <p>So, because it would have given me infinite pleasure to have heard from the banks of Derwent Water, and because I gave you my
					direction, I was not to have a single line! for my part I would have told you long ago how I was pleased with the country about
					Southampton, delighted with Nettley Abbey, enchanted with the Isle of Wight, (where I passed three days alone searching every corner)
					how from thence I went to my cousin's in Dorsetshire, stayed six weeks, and came hither on my cousin
						Fanny's account; how pleased we were with Stour Head! how much
					more than pleased with Mr. Morris's (which we saw just when Autumn had begun to tinge the woods with
					a thousand beautiful varieties of colour) and with other scenes on the Severn. All this and more I would have told you; and if I had
					been as tedious as an Emperor, I could have found in my heart to have bestowed it all upon you, only you took care to secure yourself
					by leaving me without a direction. </p>
				     <p>We leave this place on Wednesday se'nnight and shall be in town the Saturday after. God knows where you are, but if in town I shall
					have a chance of seeing you. We shall depart for Blundeston the Wednesday after. </p>
				     <p>This place (Bath) surprised and pleased me extremely at first. It was so new a sight to see a town built of hewn stone, instead of
					ragged and dirty brick, and streets and parades on a regular plan, and above all the circus, instead of the confused heap of buildings
					of all shapes and sizes which compose every other town in England. The neighbouring country is very pretty– hills of some height
					with cultivated valleys running among them, the principal one (which leads to Bristol) watered by the Avon. There are many fine trees
					in the hedge-rows; and some woods clothing the sides of the hills. I have seen Mr. Mason's monument for his wife, and like it; but the medallion is I think too small; and the sculpture so small and delicate that it is
					seen to disadvantage at the height where it is placed.</p>
				     <p>Perhaps you will believe me if I say I long to see or hear from you! indeed I do most devoutly. I have a heart that would be much
					more at home at Pembroke Hall than it is at Bath.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! my dear Sir, I am ever most faithfully yours, </salute>
					       <signed>N. N. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>My mother and cousin send their compliments to you. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
