<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (26 July 1760)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <institution key="PRIV">Private collection</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>Christie's, 14 June 1979 (A. A. Houghton Sale), Lot 237, sold to Fleming</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 316, vol. ii, 687-688
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=316</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LIV, 212-214
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:212</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCV, vol. ii, 156-158
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:156</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0364">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1760-07-26"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0364">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>July, 1760.</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Sir </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I guess what the packet is, and desire you would keep it, for I am come back hither, and hope to be with you on Tuesday night. I shall trouble you to have my
					bed aired, and to speak about a lodging for my servant; though (if it be not contrary to the etiquette of the college) I should rather
					hope there might be some garret vacant this summer time, and that he might lie within your walls; but this I leave to your
					consideration.</p>
				     <p>This very night Billy Robinson consummates his good fortune; she has £10,000 in her pocket, and a
					brother unmarried with at least as much more. He is infirm, and the first convoy that sails they all three set out together for Naples
					to pass a year or two. I insist upon it he owes all this to Mr. Talbot in the first place, and in the
					second to me, and have insisted on a couple of thousand pounds between us–the least penny–or he is a shabby fellow.</p>
				     <p>I ask pardon about Madame de Fuentes and her twelve ladies. I heard it in good company, when first
					she arrived, piping hot; and I suppose it was rather what people apprehended than what they experienced. She surely brought them over,
					but I do not find she has carried them about; on the contrary, she calls on my Lady Hervey in a
					morning in an undress, and desires to be without ceremony; and the whole tribe, except Madame de Mora
					(the young countess), were at Miss Chudleigh's ball and many other places: but of late D'Abreu (whom nobody ever liked) has advised them to be disagreeable, and they accept of no invitations.</p>
				     <p>Adieu, dear sir; I hope so soon to be with you, that I may spare you the trouble of reading any more.– </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am ever yours, </salute>
					       <signed>T. G. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I hear there was a quarrel at the [Commenc:t] between Dr. Barnard and Dr. Ogden –mackerel or turbot.
					</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
