<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (July 1763)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 372, vol. ii, 803-804
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=372</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXXXIII, 311-315
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:311</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 266-268
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:266</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLII, vol. iii, 13-15
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:13</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0425">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1763-07"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Algarotti, Francesco, Conte, 1712-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Bedingfield, Edward, b. 1730</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Brown, James, 1709-1784</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">How, William Taylor, d. 1777</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Smart, Christopher</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Algarotti, Francesco, Conte, 1712-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Aston</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0425">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>As I have no more received my little <hi rend="italic">thingumterries,</hi>
					 than you have yours, tho they were sent by the Beverly, Captain
					Allen, I have return'd no answer yet; but I must soon, &amp; that in plain English, and so should you too. in the mean time I borrow'd
					&amp; read them. that on the Opera is a good clever dissertation, dedicated to <hi rend="italic">Guglielmo Pitt.</hi>
					 the other (<hi rend="italic">Il Congresso di Citera</hi>) in
					poetical prose describes the negotiation of three Embassadresses sent by England, France, &amp; Italy to the Court of Cupid to lay
					before him the state of his empire in the three nations, &amp; is not contemptible neither in its kind: so pray be civil to the Count,
					&amp; Signor Howe.</p>
         <p>I think it may be time enough to send poor Smart the money you have been so kind to collect for him, when he has drop'd his law-suit,
					wch I don't doubt must go against him, if he pursues it. Gordon (who lives here) knows, &amp;
					interests himself about him: from him I shall probably know, if he can be persuaded to drop his design. there is a Mr Anguish in Town (with whom, I fancy, you were once acquainted) he probably can best inform you of his condition
					&amp; motions, for I hear, he continues to be very friendly to him. </p>
         <p>When you speak of Mr Bed:ld you have always a dash of gall, that shews your unforgiving temper, only because it was to <hi rend="italic">my</hi> great chair, that he made the first visit. for this cause you refused the
					snuff-box (wch to punish you I shall accept myself) &amp; for this cause you obstinately adhere to the Church of England.
				</p>
         <p>I like your Sonnet better than most dedications. it is simple &amp; natural: the best line in it is <q> So to deceive my solitary
						days &amp;c: </q> there are an expression or two, that <hi rend="italic">break the repose</hi> of it by looking common &amp;
					over-worn. <hi rend="italic">sequester'd shade, woodbine sprays, selected lays</hi>: I dare not
					mention <hi rend="italic">letter'd ease. Life's vain vision</hi> does not pronounce well. bating these, it looks in earnest, &amp; as
					if you could live at Aston, which is not true; but that is not my affair.</p>
         <p>I have got a Mass of Pergolesi, wch is all divinity: but it was lent me, or you should have it. by
					all means send for six Lessons (for the Piano-Forte Harpsichord) of Carlo Bach, not the
						Opera-Bach, but his Brother. to my fancy they are charming, &amp; in the best Italian style: Mr
						Nevile &amp; the old Musicianers here do not like them, but to me they speak not only musick, but
					passion. I can not play them, tho' they are not hard: yet I make a smattering, that serves â&#x80;&#x93; <hi rend="italic">to deceive my
						solitary days.</hi> &amp; I figure to myself, that I hear you touch them triumphantly. Adieu! I should like to hear from you.</p>
         <p>The Petit Bon sends his love to you. all the rest (but Dr May
					&amp; the Master) are dead, or married.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
