<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs. (Dorothy) Gray (19 December 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 77, vol. i, 134-136
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=77</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xiv, section ii, 72-74
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/72</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XXX, vol. i, 49-51
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/49</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XIV, vol. ii, 66-68
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/66</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XIV, vol. ii, 77-80
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/77</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXXII, vol. i, 67-69
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/67</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XIV, vol. i, 197-199
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/197</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0087">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000457">Florence, Italy</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-12-19"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Gray, Mrs. (Dorothy), 1685-1753</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mann, Horace, Sir, 1706-1786</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Florence</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Fiorenzuola</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Bologna</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Apennines</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0087">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Florence, Dec. 19, N. S. 1739. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>We spent twelve days at Bologna, chiefly (as most travellers do) in seeing sights; for as we knew no
					mortal there, and as it is no easy matter to get admission into any Italian house, without very particular recommendations, we could
					see no company but in public places; and there are none in that city but the churches. We saw, therefore, churches, palaces, and
					pictures from morning to night; and the 15th of this month set out for Florence, and began to cross
					the Apennine mountains; we travelled among and upon them all that day, and, as it was but indifferent weather, were commonly in the
					middle of thick clouds, that utterly deprived us of a sight of their beauties: For this vast chain of hills has its beauties, and all
					the vallies are cultivated; even the mountains themselves are many of them so within a little of their very tops. They are not so
					horrid as the Alps, though pretty near as high; and the whole road is admirably well kept, and paved throughout, which is a length of
					fourscore miles, and more: We left the Pope's dominions, and lay that night in those of the Grand Duke
					at Fiorenzuola, a paltry little town, at the foot of Mount Giogo, which is the highest of them all.
					Next morning we went up it; the post-house is upon its very top, and usually involved in clouds, or half-buried in the snow. Indeed
					there was none of the last at the time we were there, but it was still a dismal habitation. The descent is most excessively steep, and
					the turnings very short and frequent; however, we performed it without any danger, and in coming down could dimly discover Florence,
					and the beautiful plain about it, through the mists; but enough to convince us, it must be one of the noblest prospects upon earth in
					summer. That afternoon we got thither; and Mr. Mann, the resident, had sent his servant to meet us at
					the gates, and conduct us to his house. He is the best and most obliging person in the world. The next night we were introduced at the
					Prince of Craon's assembly (he has the chief power here in the Grand Duke's absence). The
						Princess, and he, were extremely civil to the name of Walpole, so we were asked to stay supper, which
					is as much as to say, you may come and sup here whenever you please; for after the first invitation this is always understood. We have
					also been at the Countess Suarez's, a favourite of the late Duke, and
					one that gives the first movement to every thing gay that is going forward here. The news is every day expected from Vienna of the
					Great Duchess's delivery; if it be a boy, here will be all sorts of balls, masquerades, operas, and
					illuminations; if not, we must wait for the Carnival, when all those things come of course. In the mean time it is impossible to want
					entertainment; the famous gallery, alone, is an amusement for months; we commonly pass two or three hours every morning in it, and one
					has perfect leisure to consider all its beauties. You know it contains many hundred antique statues, such as the whole world cannot
					match, besides the vast collection of paintings, medals, and precious stones, such as no other prince was ever master of; in short, all
					that the rich and powerful house of Medicis has in so many years got together. And besides this city
					abounds with so many palaces and churches, that you can hardly place yourself any where without having some fine one in view, or at
					least some statue or fountain, magnificently adorned; these undoubtedly are far more numerous than Genoa can pretend to; yet, in its
					general appearance, I cannot think that Florence equals it in beauty. Mr. Walpole is just come from being presented to the Electress
					Palatine Dowager; she is a sister of the late Great Duke's; a stately old lady, that never goes out
					but to church, and then she has guards, and eight horses to her coach. She received him with much ceremony, standing under a huge black
					canopy, and, after a few minutes talking, she assured him of her good will, and dismissed him: She never sees any body but thus in
					form; and so she passes her life, poor woman! [...]</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
