<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (29 December 1737)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
		                <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 44, vol. i, 71-72
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=44</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 71, vol. i, 167-169
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:167</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xvi, section i, 34-35
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:34</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XII, vol. i, 13-14
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:13</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section I, letter XVI, vol. ii, 27-28
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:27</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section I, letter XVI, vol. ii, 30-32
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:30</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XVI, vol. i, 30-31
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:30</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 145-146
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=145</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section I, letter XVI, vol. i, 163-164
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:163</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0048">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1737-12-29"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0048">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Honble Horace Walpole Esq</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>at the Treasury</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 30 DE</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>My Dear </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I should say Mr Inspector general of the Exports &amp; Imports, but that appellation would make but
					an odd figure in conjunction with the two familiar monosyllables above written, for, Non bene conveniunt, nec in unâ sede morantur
					Majestas &amp; amor, which is being interpreted, Love does not live at the Custom-house: however by
					what style, title, or denomination soever you please to be dignified or distinguish'd hereafter, you'll never get rid of these two
					words, nor of your christian-name: it will stick like a Burr, &amp; you can no more get quitt of it, than St Anthony could of his Pigg:
					we had no Queen to bury here, so I have no procession to tell you of; but we are collecting our
					flowers, as fast as may be, to strew upon her tomb: Mr Pemberton of
					Cath: Hall &amp; one Ambrose of Trin: Hall, a blind Man, they say will bear away the bell; both
					English; Mr Whitehead does not shine vastly this time: the bellman has paid his duty in the following
					epigram. </p>
				     <q>
					       <p>Oh cruel death! how could'st be so unkind <lb/> To snatch the Queen, &amp; leave the King behind? </p>
				     </q>
				     <p>almost as Laconick, as Mr Conways letter; who has wrought to his
						sister in the same style, as one would write to the devil whose ancient title has been, Old Boy:,</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am <lb/> yours ever </salute>
					       <signed>T: GRAY </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
