<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (3 February 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 71</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 467, vol. iii, 1005-1006
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=467</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXII, vol. iii, 179-180
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:179</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter IX, vol. v, 73-74
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:73</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0523">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-02-03"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Anstey, Christopher, 1724-1805</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0523">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Augustus Floyer's Esq in Thrift-Street, Soho London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 4 FE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Wednesday. 3 Feb: 1768 <lb/> Pemb: Coll: </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I intend to return you the letters by tomorrow's Fly, if nothing hinders. I am never the wiser, nor
					the more able to account for T:s letter to Lady L: (wch gave occasion to all the rest) it still looks
					like the suggestion of his Wife working upon his own natural irritability, &amp; the sort of request made in it for the Berwick-living
					(at so improper a time) is not any other way to be accounted for. the <hi rend="italic">sensible &amp; manly</hi> answer to it (I must own) I can not easily digest, especially the end of it: it is plain, as he wrote on, he work'd
					his temper into a ferment, till at last it absolutely turn'd sower. I can not help his temper, but his heart may (for all that) be
					right. in the second letter he is conscious, he had gone too far in his expressions, &amp; tries to give them a sense they will not
					bear: but I allow he is throughout too angry &amp; too contemptuous. your last letter to him (tho' I never saw it) I conclude has done
					no hurt, perhaps has softened him a little. every thing depends upon the manner of their meeting in Devonshire, wch by this time you
					probably know. I do not yet see, why all this passion, why all this trouble of justifying himself to a Man, for whom he never had any
					kindness or regard, &amp; who can be of little use to him in point of interest. Temp: is too precipitate, too rough too in his
					expressions, too much the aggressor, if he thinks Ld L: really his Friend; and if he does not, how in the midst of his resentment can
					he bring himself to shew a desire of accepting farther favours from him? I yet have some little hope, that all may come right again, at
					least right enough for our purpose; for I am more convinced of T:s contempt &amp; want of esteem for L:, than I am of L:s aversion, or
					neglect of T:.</p>
         <p>Mason is here with us, &amp; will stay (I should hope) some time: he is even going to hire a small house opposite to Peter-house, wch
					he can not inhabit till next winter. Mr. Hutton being dead, he has now a landed estate, the income of
					which in a few years will be considerable.</p>
         <p>old Smith of Trinity is dead, &amp; Dr Hinchliffe will probably
					succeed him, tho' Dr Ross &amp; Brocket are also Competitors for it.
					are your India-paper, your Axminster-carpets, your Sofas &amp;
						Pechés-mortels, in great forwardness? have you read Mr. Anstey,
					&amp; the Historical doubts?</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I am sincerely<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
