<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (8 March 1771)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 544, vol. iii, 1168-1171
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=544</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>An Account of the Life and Writings of James Beattie, including many of his original letters</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Sir William Forbes. Edinburgh: A. Constable, 1806, vol. i, 196 ff.
			</bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 303-307
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:303</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXXIX, vol. iii, 305-311
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:305</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, vol. iv, 309-312
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:309</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0624">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1771-03-08"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0624">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Cambridge, 8th March, 1771. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>The <hi rend="italic">Minstrel</hi>
					 came safe to my hands, and I return you my sincere thanks for so acceptable a present. In return, I
					shall give you my undisguised opinion of him, as he proceeds, without considering to whom he owes his birth, and sometimes without
					specifying my reasons; either because they would lead me too far, or because I may not always know what they are myself.</p>
				     <p>I think we should wholly adopt the language of Spenser's time, or wholly renounce it. You say, you
					have done the latter; but, in effect, you retain <hi rend="italic">fared, forth, meed, wight, ween, gaude, shene, in sooth, aye,
						eschew,</hi> &amp;c.; obsolete words, at least in these parts of the island, and only known to those that read our ancient authors, or
					such as imitate them.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 2. v. 5. The <hi rend="italic">obstreperous</hi> trump of fame hurts my ear, though meant to express a jarring sound.</p>
				     <p>St. 3. v. 6. <hi rend="italic">And from his bending,</hi> &amp;c., the grammar seems deficient: yet as the mind easily fills up the
					ellipsis, perhaps it is an atticism, and not inelegant.</p>
				     <p>St. 4. and ult. <hi rend="italic">Pensions, posts, and praise.</hi> I cannot reconcile myself to this, nor to the whole following
					stanza; especially <hi rend="italic">the plaister of thy hair.</hi>
					
				     </p>
				     <p>
					       <hi rend="italic">Surely the female heart,</hi> &amp;c., St. 6. The thought is not just. We cannot justify the sex from the conduct of
					the Muses, who are only females by the help of Greek mythology; and then, again, how should they bow the knee in the fane of a Hebrew
					or Philistine devil? Besides, I am the more severe, because it serves to introduce what I most admire.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 7. <hi rend="italic">Rise, sons of harmony,</hi> &amp;c. This is charming; the thought and the expression. I will not be so
					hypercritical as to add, but it is <hi rend="italic">lyrical,</hi> and therefore belongs to a different species of poetry. Rules are
					but chains, good for little, except when one can break through them; and what is fine gives me so much pleasure, that I never regard
					what place it is in.</p>
				     <p>St. 8, 9, 10. All this thought is well and freely handled, particularly, <hi rend="italic">Here peaceful are the vales,</hi> &amp;c.
						<hi rend="italic">Know thine own worth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Canst thou forego,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
				     <p>St. 11. <hi rend="italic">O, how canst thou renounce,</hi> &amp;c. But this, of all others, is my favourite stanza. It is true
					poetry; it is inspiration; only (to show it is mortal) there is one blemish; the word <hi rend="italic">garniture</hi> suggesting an
					idea of dress, and, what is worse, of French dress.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 12. Very well. <hi rend="italic">Prompting th' ungenerous wish,</hi> &amp;c. But do not say <hi rend="italic">rambling muse;
						wandering,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">devious,</hi> if you please.</p>
				     <p> St. 13. <hi rend="italic">A nation fam'd,</hi> &amp;c. I like this compliment to your country; the simplicity, too, of the following
					narrative; only in st. 17 the words <hi rend="italic">artless</hi> and <hi rend="italic">simple</hi> are too synonymous to come so near
					each other.</p>
				     <p>St. 18. <hi rend="italic">And yet poor Edwin,</hi> &amp;c. This is all excellent, and comes very near the level of st. 11 in my
					esteem; only, perhaps, <hi rend="italic">And some believed him mad,</hi> falls a little too flat, and rather below simplicity.</p>
				     <p>St. 21. <hi rend="italic">Ah, no!</hi> By the way, this sort of interjection is rather too frequent with you, and will grow
					characteristic, if you do not avoid it.</p>
				     <p>In that part of the poem which you sent me before, you have altered several little particulars much for the better.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 34. I believe I took notice before of this excess of alliteration. <hi rend="italic">Long, loaded, loud,</hi> lament, <hi rend="italic">lonely,</hi> lighted, <hi rend="italic">lingering, listening;</hi> though the verses are otherwise very good, it looks
					like affectation.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 36, 37, 38. Sure you go too far in lengthening a stroke of Edwin's character and disposition into a direct narrative, as of a
					fact. In the mean time, the poem stands still, and the reader grows impatient. Do you not, in general, indulge a little too much in <hi rend="italic">description</hi> and <hi rend="italic">reflection</hi>? This is not my remark only, I have heard it observed by others;
					and I take notice of it here, because <hi rend="italic">these</hi> are among the stanzas that might be spared; they are good,
					nevertheless, and might be laid by, and employed elsewhere to advantage.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 42. Spite of what I have just now said, this digression pleases me so well, that I cannot spare it. </p>
				     <p>St. 46, v. ult. The <hi rend="italic">infuriate</hi> flood. I would not make new words without great necessity; it is very hazardous
					at best.</p>
				     <p> St. 49, 50, 51, 52. All this is very good; but <hi rend="italic">medium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">incongruous,</hi> being words of
					art, lose their dignity in my eyes, and savour too much of prose. I would have read the last line– 'Presumptuous child of dust,
					be humble and be wise.' But, on second thoughts, perhaps–<hi rend="italic">'For thou art but of dust'</hi>–is better and
					more solemn, from its simplicity.</p>
				     <p>St. 53. <hi rend="italic">Where dark,</hi> &amp;c. You return again to the charge. Had you not said enough before?
				</p>
				     <p>St. 54. <hi rend="italic">Nor was this ancient dame,</hi> &amp;c. Consider, she has not been mentioned for these six stanzas
					backward.</p>
				     <p>St. 56, v. 5. <hi rend="italic">The vernal day.</hi> With us it rarely thunders in the spring, but in the summer frequently.
				</p>
				     <p>St. 57, 58. Very pleasing, and has much the rhythm and expression of Milton in his youth. The last four lines strike me less by far. </p>
				     <p>St. 59. The first five lines charming. Might not the mind of your conqueror be checked and softened in the mid-career of his
					successes by some domestic misfortune (introduced by way of episode, interesting and new, but not too long), that Edwin's music and its
					triumphs may be a little prepared, and more consistent with probability?
				</p>
				     <p>I am happy to hear of your successes in another way, because I think you are serving the cause of human nature, and the true interest
					of mankind. Your book is read here too, and with just applause.</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
