<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Norton Nicholls to Thomas Gray (14 June 1769)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 498, vol. iii, 1062-1064
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=498</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XIX, vol. v, 88-91
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:88</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0557">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1769-06-14"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0557">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>June 14, 1769. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I know you think that I have entirely neglected botany, or you would have had twenty troublesome letters before now; but this is not
					entirely the case, as my journal will witness for me when you see it. I have indeed met with severe rebuffs and discouragements, and
					difficulties that almost reduced me to despair; but I believe it is because I ventured beyond my strength, and expected to make out
					readily every wild flower I found, instead of condescending to take my garden for a master, and learn gradually the botanical
					characters from flowers I know; which seems more reasonable than endeavouring to discover the others by characters I have not yet
					learnt. I have not writ to ask questions, because there would be no end of it, and I am sure I should never make you understand me
					except I enclosed the plant. But I have had innumerable to ask if you had been at my elbow. Having nothing to say myself, I waited for
					some time rather in expectation of hearing some news of the Ode, which I long most impatiently to see;
					Oh! whilst I remember it, (to set my conscience at ease) I must tell you that some time ago I received a letter from Woodyer the bookseller, (to acknowledge the receipt of some money I sent him) in which there was a postscript longer
					than the letter itself, to say how much obliged &amp;c. he should be if, by my interposition, he (Woodyer) might be admitted to a share
					in the sale of the Ode said to be yours, if it should be printed, for that it would sell prodigiously. Unto which, his most humble
					request, I have so far graciously condescended as (not answering his letter, because that would divulge the secret which is already
					public) to make it known to you. Thus much I have done, because as he did me the honour of preferring me, I was not certain whether in
					justice I could suppress it entirely; how just or reasonable the request itself may be I know not, and so I wash my hands of him and
					ask pardon.</p>
         <p>Why will you mention Skiddaw or any such insolent mountain to me who live within two miles of the
					sea and cannot see it till I come within two yards of it? think of me when you listen to the sound of Lawdoor waterfall, or wander among the rocks of Borrowdale, and send an eagle to fetch me from Dorsetshire and
					deliver me from the naked downs. Alas! alas! when shall we live among the Grisons? visit the Bishop of Coire? or pass a summer at
					Chiavenna?</p>
         <p>I have been very idle (that you will not be surprised to hear) except in my garden, and there very diligent, very much amused, very
					much interested, and perfectly dirty with planting, transplanting &amp;c. and with tolerable success.
					Besides I have now free access, and an open firm descent to my lake, and a very shady little walk that winds a little way close on its
					bank; and have planted weeping willows, and poplars, and alders, and sallows; and shall expect you next summer to come and find fault,
					and sit in the shade. </p>
         <p>I am just reading Mémoires de Sully, which please me extremely, more than almost any thing; and
					particularly what I read a few minutes ago, the surprise of the fortress of Fescamp by Bois Rosé. You
					remember the fifty men hanging by a rope midway of a perpendicular rock six hundred feet high, and the sea at bottom rising till it set
					the boats that brought them adrift, and prevented the possibility of their returning. Fear seizing the foremost man, and Bois Rosé (who
					was last of the train) climbing over the backs of the fifty to lead them on. It is told with all its circumstances more like the
					surprise of Platæa or other such descriptions in Thucydides, than a French writer.</p>
         <p>Dr. Marriott has not writ, and is, I hear, to have his house full of foreign ambassadors; so our Cambridge journey is at an end. We
					shall set out from hence about the middle of July for the west; but I beseech you let me hear first from you; and ....
					 from Keswick it would really be cruel to refuse me a line, though you will not write from
						..... or Cambridge.</p>
         <p>I should be extremely obliged to you if you would once more lend me your book of Wilton, if you
					could send it by the fly, to be left at Payne's at the Meuse Gate for
					me till I call; and add necessary instructions for the country about Southampton, for that must be my Keswick this year.</p>
         <p>Adieu! I really want to hear a little oftener from you; if I thought writing about nothing, on my part, would have any effect, that
					should not stand in the way.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am most faithfully and affectionately yours, </salute>
            <signed>N. N. </signed>
            <dateline>Blundeston, 14th June, 1769.</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>My mother's compliments.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
