<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (1 August 1768)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 185-186</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">236 mm x 182 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 480, vol. iii, 1037-1038
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=480</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXXI, vol. iii, 202-203
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:202</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXIX, vol. ii, 503-504
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:503</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CLIV, vol. iv, 123-124
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:123</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0537">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1768-08-01"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0537">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Thomas Wharton, M:D:</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>of Old-Park near Darling-</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>ton</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>1 AU</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Jermyn-Street. 1. Aug: <lb/> (at Mr Roberts's) 1768. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have been remiss in answering your last letter, wch was sent me to Ramsgate from Cambridge: for I have pass'd a good part of the
					summer in different parts of Kent much to my satisfaction. could I have advised any thing essential in
					poor Mrs Ett:s case, I had certainly replied immediately: but we seem of one mind in it. there was
					nothing left but to appeal to Delegates (let the trouble &amp; expence be what they will almost) &amp;
					to punish, if it be practicable, that old Villain, who upon the bench of justice dared to set at nought all common sense &amp; all
					humanity.</p>
				     <p>I write to you now chiefly to tell you (and I think you will be pleased, (nay, I expect the whole family will be pleased with it,)
					that on Sunday se'nnight, Brockett died by a fall from his horse, being (as I hear) drunk, &amp; some
					say, returning from Hinchinbroke: that on the Wednesday following, I received a letter from the D: of
						Grafton, saying, He had the K:s commands to <hi rend="italic">offer</hi> me the vacant Professorship,
					that &amp;c: (but I shall not write all he says) &amp; he adds at the end, <hi rend="italic">that from private as well as publick
						considerations He must take the warmest part in approving so well judged a measure as he hopes I do not doubt of the real regard &amp;
						esteem with wch he has the honor to be,</hi> &amp;c: there's for you. so on Thursday the K: sign'd the warrant, &amp; next day at his
					Levee I kiss'd his hand. he made me several gracious speeches, wch I shall not report, because every
					body, who goes to court, does so. by the way I desire, you would say, that all the Cabinet-Council in words of great favour approved
					the nomination of your humble Serv:t &amp; this I am bid to say, &amp; was told to leave my name at
					their several doors. I have told you the outside of the matter &amp; all the manner: for the inside you know enough easily to guess t,
					&amp; you will guess right. as to his Grace I have not seen him before or since.</p>
				     <p>I shall continue here perhaps a fortnight longer, perishing with heat: I have no Thermometer with me, but I feel it as I did at
					Naples. next summer (if it be as much in my power, as it is in my wishes) I meet you at the foot of Skiddaw. my respects to Mrs
					Wharton, &amp; the young Ladies great &amp; small: love to Robin &amp; Richard.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I am truly <lb/> Yours. </salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>At your instance I have kiss'd Mrs Forster, &amp; forgot old quarrels. I went to visit the
						Daughter, who has been brought to bed of a Boy, &amp; there I met with the Mother.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
