<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (26 April 1744)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 9-10</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">233 mm x 186 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 115, vol. i, 222-225
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=115</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter ii, section iv, 177-179
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:177</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 141-142
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:141</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LX, vol. i, 117-121
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:117</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter V, vol. ii, 148-150
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:148</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter VIII, vol. ii, 189-192
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:189</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LX, vol. i, 132-134
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:132</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter II, vol. i, 292-294
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:292</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0133">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1744-04-26"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Brown, James, 1709-1784</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">De Principiis Cogitandi. Liber Primus. Ad Favonium.</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Warton, Joseph</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Armstrong, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Akenside, Dr. Mark</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Stoke Poges</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Caxton</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0133">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Thomas Wharton Esq, at M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Alderman</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Wharton's of</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
               <addrLine>By Caxton Bay</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>You write so feelingly to little Mr Brown, &amp; represent your abandon'd Condition in Terms so
					touching, that, what Gratitude could not effect in several Months, Compassion has brought about in a few Days, &amp; broke that strong
					Attachment, or rather Allegiance, wch I &amp; all here owe to our sovereign Lady &amp; Mistress, the President of Presidents, &amp;
					Head of Heads (if I may be permitted to pronounce her Name, that ineffable Octogrammaton) the Power of LAZINESS. you must know she had been pleased to appoint me (in Preference to so many old Servants of hers, who had
					spent their whole Lives in qualifying themselves for the Office) Grand Picker of Straws, &amp; Push-Pin-Player in ordinary to her
					Supinity (for that is her Title) the first is much in the Nature of Ld President of the Council, &amp; the other, like the
					Groom-Porter, only without the Profit. but, as they are both Things of very great Honour in this Country, I consider'd with myself the
					Load of Envy attending such great Charges, &amp; besides (between you &amp; I) I found myself unable to support the Fatigue of keeping
					up the Appearance, that Persons of such Dignity must do, so I thought proper to decline it, &amp; excused myself as well as I could:
					however as you see such an Affair must take up a good deal of Time, &amp; it has always been the Policy of this Court to proceed
					slowly, like the Imperial, &amp; that of Spain, in the Dispatch of Business; so that you will the easier forgive me, if I have not
					answer'd your Letter before.</p>
         <p>You desire to know, it seems, what Character the Poem of your young Friend bears here. I wonder to
					hear you ask the Opinion of a Nation, where those who pretend to judge, don't judge at all; &amp; the rest (the wiser Part) wait to
					catch the Judgement of the World immediately above them, that is, Dick's Coffee-House, &amp; the
						Rainbow: so that the readier Way would be to ask Mrs This &amp; Mrs T'other, that keeps the Bar
					there. however to shew you I'm a Judge, as well as my Countrymen, tho' I have rather turn'd it over, than read it, (but no matter: no
					more have they) it seems to me above the middleing, &amp; now &amp; then (but for a little while) rises even to the best, particularly
					in Description. it is often obscure, &amp; even unintelligible, &amp; too much infected with the Hutchinson-Jargon. in short it's great fault is that it was publish'd at least 9 Years too early. and so methinks in a few Words, a la Mode du Temple, I have very pertly
					dispatch'd what perhaps may for several Years have employd a very ingenious Man worth 50 of myself. here is a small poem, call'd the
						Enthusiast, wch is all pure Description, &amp; as they tell me by the same Hand. is it so, or not?
					Item, a more bulky one upon Health, wrote by a Physician: do you know him? Master Tommy
						Lucretius (since you are so good to enquire after the Child) is but a puleing Chitt yet, not a bit
					grown to speak off, I believe, poor Thing! it has got the Worms, that will carry it off at last. oh Lord! I forgot to tell you, that Mr
						Trollope &amp; I are in a course of Tar-Water, he for his Present,
					and I for my future Distempers: if you think it will kill me, send away a Man &amp; Horse directly, for I drink like a Fish. I should
					be glad to know how your [ ] goes on, &amp; give you Joy of it.</p>
         <p>You are much in the Right to have a Taste for Socrates, he was a divine Man. I must tell you by Way of the News of the Place, that
					the other Day Mr Fraigneau (entering upon his Professorship) made an Apology for him an Hour long in
					the Schools, &amp; all the World, except Trinity-College, brought in Socrates Guilty. Adieu, Dr Sir, &amp; believe me</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Your Friend &amp; Servant, </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
            <dateline>Cambridge .. Thursday Ap: 26.
					</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
