<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (1 February 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
                  <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
                  <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
                  <idno>AU MS 30/24/6/5</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>
                        <hi rend="it">covering letter only</hi> (a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford), the instructions for printing are at Princeton University Library, <ref target="http://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/RTC01/c00001">Robert H. Taylor Collection</ref>, section I. Modern (Bound) Manuscripts, vol. 52</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 466, vol. iii, 1001-1004
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=466</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter lvii, section iv, 329-330
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:329</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXX, vol. iii, 175-177
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:175</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXIV, vol. ii, 490-491
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:490</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLVI, vol. iv, 101-103
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:101</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXIV, vol. ii, 114-116
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:114</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LVII, vol. i, 428-429
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:428</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0522">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-02-01"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Dodsley, James, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="edition">Poems by Mr. Gray (1768)</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="edition">Poems by Mr. Gray (1768)</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="edition">Odes by Mr. Gray (1757)</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0522">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Mr Beattie</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Feb: 1. 1768.<lb/> Pembroke-Hall. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am almost sorry to have raised any degree of impatience in you, because I can by no means satisfy
					it. the sole reason I have to publish these few additions now is to make up (in bulk) for the omission
					of that <hi rend="italic">long story</hi>; &amp; as to the notes, I do it out of spite, because the Publick did not understand the two
					odes (wch I have call'd Pindaric) tho' the first was not very dark, &amp; the second alluded to a few common facts to be found in any
					six-penny History of England by way of question &amp; answer for the use of children. the parallel passages I insert out of justice to
					those writers, from whom I happen'd to take the hint of any line, as far as I can recollect.</p>
         <p>I rejoice to be in the hands of Mr Foulis, who has the laudable ambition of surpassing his Predecessors, the <hi rend="italic">Etiennes,</hi>
					 &amp; the <hi rend="italic">Elzeviers</hi>
					 as well in literature, as in the proper art of his profession. he surprises me in mentioning Miss
						Hepburne, after whom I have been enquiring these fourteen years in vain. when the two odes were first
					publish'd, I sent them to her: but as I was forced to direct them very much at random, probably they never came to her hands. when the
					present edition comes out, I beg of Mr Foulis to offer her a copy in my name (with my respects, &amp; grateful remembrances). he will
					send another to you, Sr, &amp; a third to Ld Gray, if he will do me the honour of accepting it. these
					are all the presents I pretend to make (for I would have it consider'd only as a new edition of an old book) after this if he pleases
					to send me one or two, I shall think myself obliged to him. I can not advise him to print a great number, especially as Dodsley has it
					in his power to print as many as he pleases, tho' I desire him not to do so.</p>
         <p>You are very good to me in taking this trouble upon you. all I can say is, that I shall be happy to return it in kind, whenever you
					will give me the opportunity. believe me, </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Sr faithfully Yours </salute>
            <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>You will be so obliging to tell me this packet is come to your hands.
					</p>
            <p>The Title (I would wish) should be only <hi rend="italic">Poems by Mr Gray</hi> without any mention of notes or additions. the size,
						&amp; disposition of the lines I must leave to Mr Foulis: if he thinks it should be in 4to, the two
						Odes printed at Str:y Hill are very well (as you say) as to the form &amp; type, but the paper is
						rather too thin &amp; transparent. I prescribed nothing to Dodsley, but it appear'd to me, that he meant to publish a smaller edition
						(&amp; consequently a cheaper) than in 4to, but of this I am not certain. Mr F: will also determine,
						whether the few notes there are shall stand at the bottom of the page (wch is better for the Reader) or be thrown to the end with
						references (wch improves the beauty of the book). the poems should stand (I think) in this order
						&amp; with these titles. <list>
                  <item>1. Ode. Lo! where the rosy &amp;c: </item>
                  <item>2. Ode, on the death of a favourite Cat. </item>
                  <item>3. Ode, on a distant prospect of Eton-College. </item>
                  <item>4. Ode, to Adversity.
							</item>
                  <item>5. The progress of Poesy, a Pindaric Ode. </item>
                  <item>6. The Bard, a Pindaric Ode. </item>
                  <item>7. The Fatal Sisters (from the Norse-tongue) </item>
                  <item>8. The Descent of Odin (from the Norse-tongue) </item>
                  <item>9. The Triumphs of Owen, a fragment (from the Welch) </item>
                  <item>10. Elegy, written in a country church-yard. </item>
               </list> please to observe, that I am entirely unversed in the doctrine of <hi rend="italic">stops</hi>, whoever therefore shall deign
						to correct them, will do me a friendly office: I wish I stood in need of no other correction. if Mr
						F: has the large edition with Mr Bentley's designs, he will do well to print from it (the <hi rend="italic">long story</hi> being
						omitted) as it seems the most accurate for in Dodsley's miscellanies there are several blunders of the press. the Strawberry-hill edition of the two Pindaricks is also the best. /now for the notes.
					</p>
            <p>[           ] </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
