<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (5 June 1748)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 27-28</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">185 mm x 151 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 145, vol. i, 303-308
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=145</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter vii, section iv, 189-190
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/189</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 151-152
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/NoC_1911/1/151</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXXXI, vol. i, 175-179
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/175</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XVI, vol. ii, 186-189
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/186</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXIII, vol. iii, 51-55
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/51</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXVII, vol. i, 148-150
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/148</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter VII, vol. i, 302-304
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/302</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0164">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1748-06-05"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="fre">French</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Thomson, James</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Gresset, Jean Baptiste Louis de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Diodorus</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0164">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>My Dear Wharton</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> Tho' I have been silent so long; do not imagine, I am at all less sensible to your Kindness, wch (to say the Truth) is of a
						Sort, that however obvious &amp; natural it may seem, has never once occur'd to any of my good
					Friends in Town, where I have been these seven Weeks. their Methods of Consolation were indeed very extraordinary: they were all so
					sorry for my Loss, that I could not chuse but laugh. one offer'd me Opera-Tickets, insisted upon
					carrying me to the Grand-Masquerade, desired me to sit for my Picture. others asked me to their
					Concerts, or Dinners &amp; Suppers at their Houses; or hoped, I would drink Chocolate with them, while I stayed in Town. all my
					Gratitude (or if you please, my Revenge) was to accept of every Thing they offer'd me: if it had been but a Shilling, I would have
					taken it. thank Heaven, I was in good Spirits; else I could not have done it. I profited all I was able of their Civilities, &amp; am
					returned into the Country loaded with their Bontés &amp; Politesses, but richer still in my own Reflexions, wch I owe in great Measure
					to them too. suffer a great Master to tell them you for me in a better Manner</p>
         <q>
            <p>Aux sentimens de la Nature, <lb/> Aux plaisirs de la Verité, <lb/> Preferant le goût frelaté <lb/> Des plaisirs, qu'a fait
							l'imposture<lb/> Ou qu'inventa la vanité;<lb/> Voudrois-je partager ma vie <lb/> Entre les jeux
						de la folie, <lb/> Et l'ennui de l'oisiveté, <lb/> Et trouver la melancolie <lb/> Dans le sein de la volupté? &amp;c: </p>
         </q>
         <p>Your Friendship has interested itself in my Affairs so naturally, that I can not help troubleing you with a little Detail of them.
					the House I lost was insured for 500£, &amp; with the Deduction of 3 per Ct they paid me 485£, with wch I bought, when Stocks were
					lower, 525£. the Rebuilding will cost 590, &amp; other Expences, that necessarily attend it, will mount that Summ to 650. I have an Aunt that gives me 100£; &amp; another, that I hope will lend me what I shall want: but if (contrary to my Expectation) I should be forced to have
					recourse to your Assistance: it can not be for above 50£; &amp; that, about Xmas next when the Thing is to be finish'd. and now, my
					dear Wharton, why must I tell you a Thing so contrary to my own Wishes, &amp; to yours, I believe? it is impossible for me to see you
					in the North, or to enjoy any of those agreeable Hours I had flatter'd myself with. I must be in Town several Times dureing the Summer;
					in August particularly, when half the Money is to be paid: the Relation, that used to do Things for
					me, is from Illness now quite incapable; &amp; the good People here would think me the most careless &amp; ruinous of Mortals, if I
					should think of such a Journey at this Time. the only Satisfaction I can pretend to, is that of hearing from you; &amp; particularly
					about this Time, I was bid to expect good News.
				</p>
         <p>Your Opinion of Diodorus is doubtless right; but there are Things in him very curious, got out of better Authors now lost. do you
					remember the Egyptian History, &amp; particularly the Account of the Gold-Mines? my own Readings have
					been cruelly interrupted. what I have been highly pleased with is the new Comedy from Paris, by Gresset; Le Mechant, one of the very best Drama's I ever met with. if you have it not, buy his Works altogether in two little
						Volumes. they are collected by the Dutch Booksellers, &amp; consequently there is some Trash; but
					then there are the Ver-vert, the Epistle to P: Bougeant, the
						Chartreuse that to his Sister, an Ode on his Country, &amp; another on Mediocrity; &amp; the Sidnei, another Comedy, wch have great Beauties. there is a Poem by Thomson, the
					Castle of Indolence, with some good Stanzas. Mr. Mason is my Acquaintance: I liked that Ode very much, but have found no one else, that did. he has much Fancy, little Judgement, &amp; a good deal of
					Modesty. I take him for a good &amp; well-meaning Creature; but then he is really <hi rend="italic">in Simplicity a Child,</hi>
					 &amp; loves every body he meets with: he reads little or nothing, writes abundance, &amp; that with
					a Design to make his Fortune by it. there is now, I think, no Hopes of the Pembroke Business coming
					to any-thing. [My poor Tuthill] will be in a Manner destitute (even of a Curacy) at Midsummer. I need not bid you think of him, if any probable Means offer of doing him Good: I fear, he was not made to
					think much for himself. pray, let me hear from you soon. I am at Mrs Rogers's of Stoke near Windsor, Bucks. my thanks, &amp; best
					Compliments to Mrs Wharton, &amp; your Family. does that Name include any body, that I am not yet acquainted with?</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am ever <lb/> Truly Yours </salute>
            <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
            <dateline>June. 5 ... 1748.</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
