<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (9 November 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 283, vol. ii, 593-594
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=283</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXXIX, 163-164
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:163</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxxiv, section iv, 273-274
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:273</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 212-214
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:212</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXVIII, vol. ii, 61-62
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:61</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXX, vol. ii, 325-326
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:325</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXXVIII, vol. iii, 210-211
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:210</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CV, vol. ii, 43-44
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:43</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXXIV, vol. i, 378-379
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:378</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0326">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1758-11-09"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0326">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Mason, Rector of Aston, at Sheffield in Yorkshire</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Nov: 9. 1758. Stoke. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I should have told you, that Caradoc came safe to hand, but my critical faculties have been so taken
					up in dividing <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> with the Dragon of Wantley's Dam, that they are not yet
					composed enough for a better &amp; more tranquil employment: shortly however I will make them obey me; but am I to send this copy to Mr
					Hurd, or return it to you? methinks I do not love this travelling to &amp; again of manuscripts by the Post. while I am writing, your
					second packet is just arrived. I can only tell you in gross, that there seem to me certain passages alter'd wch might as well have been
					let alone; &amp; that I shall not be easily reconciled to Mador's <hi rend="italic">own</hi> song. I
					must not have my fancy raised to that agreeable pitch of heathenism, &amp; wild magical enthusiasm, &amp; then have you let me drop
					into moral philosophy, &amp; cold good sense. I remember you insulted me, when I saw you last, &amp; affected to call, that wch
					delighted my imagination, <hi rend="italic">Nonsense</hi>: now I insist, that Sense is nothing in poetry, but according to the dress
					she wears, &amp; the scene she appears in. if you should lead me into a superb Gothic building with a thousand cluster'd pillars, each
					of them half a mile high, the walls all cover'd with fretwork, &amp; the windows full of red &amp; blue Saints, that had neither head,
					nor tail; and I should find the Venus of Medici in person perk'd up in a long nich over the high altar, as naked as ever she was born,
					do you think it would raise, or damp my devotions? I say, that Mador must be entirely a Briton, &amp; that his preeminence among his
					companions must be shewn by superior wildness, more barbaric fancy, &amp; a more striking &amp; deeper harmony both of words &amp;
					numbers. if British antiquity be too narrow, this is the place for Invention, &amp; if it be pure invention, so much the clearer must
					the expression be, &amp; so much the stronger &amp; richer the imagery. there's for you now. </p>
         <p>I am sorry to hear you complain of your eyes. have a care of candle-light, &amp; rather play at hot-cockles with the children, than either read or write. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am truly &amp; ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
