<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Warton to Thomas Gray (20 April 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution key="BDLN">Bodleian Library, Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Special Collections</repository>
                  <collection>Warton papers</collection>
                  <idno>Dep. c. 638, f. 42</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">320 mm x 194 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>the <ref target="https://archives.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/repositories/2/resources/3251">Warton papers</ref> are the property of Trinity College, Oxford, they were deposited in the Bodleian in 1978 and 1979</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Digital facsimile [JPEG] from original letter</title>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 521, vol. iii, 1128-1130
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=521</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0599">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44371601">Warton, Thomas, 1728-1790</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011375">Winchester, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-04-20"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Warton, Thomas, 1728-1790</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pope, Alexander</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0599">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am infinitely obliged to you for the Favour of your Letter. Your Plan for the <hi rend="italic">History of English Poetry</hi> is admirably constructed; and much improved from an Idea of Pope,
					which Mr Mason obligingly sent me by Application from our Friend Dr Hurd. I regrett that a writer of your consummate Taste should not
					have executed it.</p>
         <p>Although I have not followed this Plan, yet it is of great service to me, and throws much light on many of my Periods, by giving
					connected views and Details. I begin with such an introduction, or general Dissertation, as you had intended: viz. on the Northern
					Poetry with its introduction into England by the Danes and Saxons, &amp; its duration. I then begin my <hi rend="italic">History</hi>
					at the conquest which I write chronologically in Sections; and continue, as matter successively offers itself, in a series of regular
					Annals, down to &amp; beyond the Restoration. I think with you, that Dramatic poetry is detached from the idea of my work, that it requires a separate consideration, &amp; will swell the size of my book beyond all bounds. One of
					my Sections, a very large one, is entirely on Chaucer, and exactly fills your Title of <hi rend="italic">Part Second.</hi> In the
					course of my Annals I consider collaterally the Poetry of different Nations as influencing our own. What I have at present finished
					ends with the section on Chaucer, &amp; will almost make my first Volume; for I design two Volumes in quarto. This first Volume will
					soon be in the press. I should have said before, that although I proceed chronologically, yet I often
					stand still to give some general view, as perhaps of a <hi rend="italic">particular species</hi> of poetry, &amp;c. and even <hi rend="italic">anticipate</hi> sometimes for this purpose. These <hi rend="italic">views</hi> often form <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
					Section; yet are interwoven into the Tenor of the work without interrupting my historical series. In this respect, some of my Sections
					have the effect of your <hi rend="italic">Parts</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Divisions.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>You do me a favour in requesting me to pay an attention to Mr Stiguer. I return to Oxford in a few
					Days, when I will make it my business to find him out, and to introduce him according to your wishes. I do not know his College, nor
					have I heard of his name. But he will easily be found out. </p>
         <p>I cannot take my Leave without declaring, that my strongest incitement to prosecute the <hi rend="italic">History of English
						Poetry</hi> is the pleasing hope of being approved by you; whose <hi rend="italic">true genius</hi> I so justly venerate, and whose
						<hi rend="italic">genuine Poetry</hi> has ever given me such sincere pleasure.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am, Sir, with the greatest Esteem, your most obedient humble Servant</salute>
            <signed>T. Warton </signed>
            <dateline>Winchester-College, April 20. 1770.</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
