<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Norton Nicholls to Thomas Gray (16 March 1771)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 545, vol. iii, 1172-1174
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=545</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXXVII, vol. v, 130-134
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843v/1/130</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0625">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1771-03-16"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Sandoval, Prudencio de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Robertson, Dr. William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Rapin de Thoyras, Paul</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Petrarch</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Herbert of Cherbury, 1st Baron</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hall, Edward</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Guicciardini, Francesco</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Froissart, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Eremita, Daniel</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Switzerland</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0625">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Blundeston, March 16, 1771. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>Yesterday I received a letter from De Bonstetten, crammed fuller than it could hold, and containing besides two little
					after-thoughts, one three inches by two, the other two by one, which flew out when I opened the letter like the oracles of the Sybil.
					But I like this much better than any I have received; he intreats us a deux genoux to come, and I you in the same posture and with
					equal earnestness; if he does not esteem me he is an idiot to take so much pains to persuade me to believe it, because, if he were
					false, I see no end that it could answer to make a dupe of me at the expense of so much labour and unnecessary dissimulation. He
					promises, if we come, that he will visit us in England the summer following. Let us go then, my dear Mr. Gray, and leave low thoughted
						care at the foot of the mountains, for the air above is too pure for it. During the winter, my
					wandering inclinations are quiet in their hybernacula; but these two or three last glorious days succeeding the rigour of such an
					unusual season, have awakened them; the animal and vegetable world rejoice, and every thing that has life in it begins to shew it. I
					have lived in the air (being fortunately compelled to attend my garden myself) except during dinner, &amp;c. The effect of this and De
					Bonstetten's letter is, that I find something 'che mi sprona' invincibly to go to Switzerland this
					summer. A deux genoux, I again intreat you to go with me. To-day, as I sat at breakfast in a room without sun, I felt myself in prison,
					and the world abroad appeared to me not a reality, but some golden vision raised by enchantment. The moment the windows were flung up,
					an earthly smell came in, exhaled by the sun from the loose and fermenting mould of the garden and fields. 'In those vernal seasons of
					the year, when the air is calm and pleasant, it were an injury and sullenness against nature not to go out and see her riches, and
					partake in her rejoicing with heaven and earth.' I am not so sullen; I do partake with her, and feel
					that this is a natural joy, which confesses its origin by being sincere and unmixed, and by leaving no bitterness on the palate behind
					it; but, on the contrary, opens, dilates, and warms the heart. I really find myself as inclined to pray, in such a day as this, as
					Petrarch was on the summit of the mountain. Pardon this rant, which, though I felt, I ought perhaps
					to have repressed. The burthen of the song is, 'Go to Switzerland with me, I beseech you.' In the mean time, for I have not a moment to
					lose, I shall venture to bespeak a curate from the first of June to the last of October, and consider of ways and means for a supply
					adequate to my great occasions: but I will go, though twenty St. Gothards were in the way. The geometra fasciaria, I think (ignorant,
					alas! that I was an enemy of the Linnæan faction) flew against me in the twilight yesterday evening; otherwise I have found but few
					insects yet. I have some larvæ in boxes, that I met with under the roots of plants. The mosses require too painful an attention without
					an instructor, so I shall wait for one. I have looked at a few common birds, and this is all. The rest of my time has been taken up
					with Froissart, Guicciardini, &amp;c. I am still reading the latter, and extracting from the former. A thousand thanks for your letter,
					full of information, but giving me a curiosity to see books that I cannot get here. Pray what were the heralds, who seem to have been
					so liberally rewarded, and called in with the minstrels at great entertainments, as well as employed in carrying defiances, &amp;c.
					What is the difference between bannière and pennon? each principal commander (but these are vague
					words) seems to have marched with a bannière peculiar to him, on which his arms were painted, and a pennon seems inferior. I have put
					the story of the Irish Kings, from Froissart, into English; and am now gathering many scattered
					curiosities relating to the manners of the Scotch in that age. I am besides reading at odd times Hall's Chronicle, and my mother and I have just begun the second volume of Robertson's Charles the Fifth, because we know
					something about him already from Rapin and Lord Herbert, and I from Guicciardin. I long for a book often quoted by Lord Herbert, and
					that should be curious; Sandoval especially, as I can now read Spanish pretty easily, for I have
					finished Don Quixote. Temple desires a plan for modern history, not confined to any particular
					period, but beginning as early as you think proper, and continued as late;– if you think this an immodest request, you may do as
					much or as little of it as you please; but whatever you may do will be a kindness to him (whose only consolation consists in his books
					and a few friends who wish him well, without being able to do more) and received with great joy and gratitude. I believe my house will
					be continued to me on the present footing. De Bonstetten in one of the flying scraps says, 'M.
						Freundenrich mon ami qui est dans votre pays cherche quelque homme de Lettres qui veuille le prendre
					en pension pour cet Eté.–Vous ferez quelque chose de ce pauvre homme, il a des talens, son education a été négligé. Je vous
					supplie de vous interesser à cette affaire.' But by what means? For he has not told me where he is to be found; nor do I perfectly
					understand what le prendre en pension means. Is it that he would board with some one who would instruct him in English and other
					matters? Perhaps M. Freundenrich is a person that he has mentioned to you, and thinks I know him of course. Do you know a book that De
					Bonstetten recommends to me, Danielis Eremitæ Vita, &amp;c. with a voyage to Switzerland at the end?
					Pray let me hear soon. My mother's compliments. The post is forbid to send letters cross.
				</p>
         <closer>
            <signed>N. N.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
