<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> August 1752)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 169, vol. i, 363-365
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=169</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 392-393
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 180, vol. ii, 123-125
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/123</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XCVII, vol. i, 218-220
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/218</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXIX, vol. ii, 217-218
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/217</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXXVI, vol. iii, 87-88
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/87</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXXII, vol. i, 171-172
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/171</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 60-61
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=60</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter VIII, vol. i, 548-549
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/548</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0191">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1752-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Dodsley, Robert, 1703-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Speed, Henrietta Jane, 1728-1783</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="edition">Designs by Mr. R. Bentley (1753)</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">[Tophet]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">The Progress of Poesy. A Pindaric Ode</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">A Long Story</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Stoke Poges</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Esher</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0191">
      <body>
         <p>Your pen was too rapid to mind the common form of a direction, and so, by omitting the words <hi rend="italic">near Windsor,</hi>
					your letter has been diverting itself at another Stoke, near Ailesbury, and came not to my hands till
					to-day. The true original chairs were all sold, when the Huntingdons broke; there are nothing now but
						Halsey-chairs, not adapted to the squareness of a Gothic dowager's rump. And by the way I do not see
					how the uneasiness and uncomfortableness of a coronation-chair can be any objection with you: every chair that is easy is modern, and
					unknown to our ancestors. As I remember, there were certain low chairs, that looked like ebony, at Esher, and were old and pretty. Why should not Mr. Bentley improve upon them?– I do not wonder at
						Dodsley. You have talked to him of six <hi rend="italic">odes,</hi> for so you are pleased to call
					every thing I write, though it be but a receipt to make apple-dumplings. He has reason to gulp when he finds one of them only a long
						story. I don't know but I may send him very soon (by your hands) an ode to his own tooth, a high
					Pindarick upon stilts, which one must be a better scholar than he is to understand a line of, and the
					very best scholars will understand but a little matter here and there. It wants but seventeen lines of having an end, I don't say of
					being finished. As it is so unfortunate to come too late for Mr. Bentley, it may appear in the fourth volume of the
						Miscellanies, provided you don't think it execrable, and suppress it. Pray, when the fine book is to
					be printed, let me revise the press, for you know you can't; and there are a few trifles I could wish
					altered.</p>
         <p>I know not what you mean by hours of love, and cherries, and pine-apples. I neither see nor hear
					anything here, and am of opinion that is the best way. My compliments to Mr. Bentley, if he be with you. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am yours ever,</salute>
            <signed>T. GRAY.</signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I desire you would not show that epigram I repeated to you, as mine. I have heard of it twice already as coming from you.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
