<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to John Chute (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 6 October 1746)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Sherborne St John</settlement>
                  <institution key="VYNE">The Vyne</institution>
                  <collection>Chute of The Vyne, Sherborne St John</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 122, vol. i, 245-247
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=122</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXVIII, vol. i, 144-145
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:144</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XI, vol. iii, 19-20
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:19</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0140">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1746-10-06"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/6079515">Chute, John, 1701-1776</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011376">Fareham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0140">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>John Chute Esq</addrLine>
               <addrLine>at Mr Whithed's of Southwick</addrLine>
               <addrLine>near Fareham in Hampshire</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>My God! Mr Chute in England? what &amp; have you seen him? and did he say nothing to you? not a
					Word of me! such was my Conversation, when I first heard News so surprising, with a Person, that
					(when I reflect) it is indeed no great Wonder You did not much interrogate concerning me, as you knew nothing of what has past of
						late.
				</p>
         <p>But let me ask you yourself, have a few Years totally erased me from your Memory? You are generous enough perhaps to forget all the
					Obligations I have to you, but is it Generosity to forget the Person you have obliged too? while I remember myself, I can not but
					remember you; &amp; consequently can not but wonder, when I find no where one Line, one Syllable, to tell me you are arrived. I will
					venture to say, there is no body in England however nearly connected with you, that has seen you with more real Joy &amp; Affection
					than I shall. You are, it seems, gone into the Country whither (had I any Reason to think you wish'd to see me) I should immediately
					have follow'd you: as it is, I am returning to Cambridge; but with Intention to come back to Town again, whenever you do; if you will
					let me know the Time, &amp; Place. </p>
         <p>I readily set Mr Wh:d free from all Imputations. he is a fine young Personage in a Coat all over
					Spangles just come over from the Tour of Europe to take Possession, &amp; be married: &amp;
					consequently can't be supposed to think of any Thing, or remember any body. but You —! however I don't altogether clear him. he
					might have said something to one, who remembers him when he was but a Pout. nevertheless I desire my
					hearty Gratulations to him, &amp; say I wish him more Spangles, &amp; more Estates, &amp; more Wives.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! my dear Sr, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
            <dateline>London–Oct: .. To T:G: of Peterhouse, Cambridge.</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P:S: My Compliments to Mrs Chute (who once did me the Honour to write to me) &amp; say, I give her
						Joy very sincerely of your Return.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
