<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (18 January 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 286, vol. ii, 603-610
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=286</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XLI, first part 167-171, second part 66-75
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:167</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 215-224
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:215</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXXII, vol. ii, 69-72
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:69</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0331">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1759-01-18"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Whitehead, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Voltaire</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Smart, Christopher</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Metastasio</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hill, Aaron</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dryden, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dodsley, Robert</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Portugal</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Lisbon</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0331">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You will think me either dead, or in that happy state (wch is that of most People alive) of forgetting every thing they ought to
					remember: yet I am neither one, nor the other. I am now in Town, having taken leave of Stoke, &amp; hoping to take leave of my other
						incumbrances in a few months time. I send you in short my opinion of Caractacus, so far (I mean) as I have seen of it. I shall only tell you farther, that I am charmed with the Idea you
					give me of your 4th Ode. it is excellently introduced, &amp; the specimen, you send me, even sublime. I am <hi rend="italic">wrap'd</hi> in it; but the last line of the Stanza falls off, &amp; must be changed, <hi rend="italic">Courage was in his van,</hi>
					&amp;c: for it is <hi rend="italic">ordinary,</hi> when compared with the rest. to be sure the immortality of ye Soul, &amp; the
					happiness of dieing in battle are Druid doctrines: you may dress them at pleasure, so they do but look
					wild &amp; British.</p>
         <p>I have little to say from hence but that Cleone has succeeded very well at Covent-Garden, &amp; that
					People, who despised it in Manuscript, went to see it &amp; confess, they cried. so for fear of crying too I did not go. poor Smart is not dead, as was said, &amp; Merope is acted for his benefit this week with a new Farce, the Guardian. here is
					a very agreeable Opera of Cocchi's, the Cyrus, wch gave me some
					pleasure. do you know, I like both Whithed's Odes in great measure, but no body else does.</p>
         <p>I hear matters will be made up with the Dutch, &amp; there will be no war. the K: of Portugal has slily introduced troops into Lisbon under pretence of clearing away the rubbish, &amp; seized the unsuspecting Conspirators in their own houses. they are
					Men of principal note, in particular the family of <hi rend="italic">Tavora,</hi> who have some pretentions to ye Crown; &amp; it is
					thought the Jesuits have made use of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> ambition to execute their own revenge. the story of ye King's gallantries, &amp; the jealousy of some Man of Quality, who contrived the assassination, is said to be all
						false. Adieu! I rejoice to hear you use your eyes again. write to me at Dr Wharton's, for perhaps I may go to Cambridge for some
						weeks, &amp; he will take care I shall have your letter. </p>
         <closer>
            <dateline>Jan: 18. 1758.<lb/>London. </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P: 2. I liked the opening, as it was originally, better than I do now. tho' I never throughly
						understood how <hi rend="italic">blank</hi> he frowns. &amp; as to <hi rend="italic">black</hi> stream, it gives me the Idea of a
						river of mud: I should read, <hi rend="italic">dark</hi> stream, imagining it takes its hue only from the rocks &amp; trees, that
						overhang it. <hi rend="italic">these cliffs, these yawning</hi> &amp;c: comes in very well, where it stood at first, &amp; you have
						only reserved it to another place, where by being somewhat more diffused, it appears weaker. you have introduced no new image in your
						new beginning, but one, <hi rend="italic">utters deep wailings,</hi> which is very well; but as to a trickling <hi rend="italic">runlet</hi> I never heard of such a thing, unless it were a runlet of brandy.</p>
            <p>Yet I have no objection at all to the reflection Didius makes on the power objects of ye sight have over ye soul: it is in its
						place, &amp; might be even longer, but then it should be more choicely &amp; more feelingly express'd. he must not talk of <hi rend="italic">dells</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">streams</hi> only, but of something more striking &amp; more corresponding to the
						scene before him. <hi rend="italic">intellect</hi> is a word of Science, &amp; therefore inferior to any more common word.</p>
            <p>P: 3. For the same reason I reject <hi rend="italic">Philosophy,</hi> &amp; read <q>
                  <p>Studious they measure: save when
								Contemplation &amp;c: </p>
               </q> &amp; here you omitt two lines, relating to Astronomy, for no cause that I discern. </p>
            <p>P: 4. What is your quarrel to <hi rend="italic">Shallops</hi>? I like <hi rend="italic">go bid thine Eagles soar,</hi> perhaps from
						obstinacy, for I know you have met with some wise Gentleman, who says it is a false thought, &amp; informs you that these were not
						real Eagles, but made of metal or wood painted.</p>
            <p>The word <hi rend="italic">Seers</hi> comes over too often, &amp; here besides it sounds ill. Elidurus need not be so fierce. <hi rend="italic">dost thou insult us, Roman,</hi> was better before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Sure-plan'd</hi> is a nasty stiff word.</p>
            <p>P: 6. It must be <hi rend="italic">Cæsar &amp; Fate.</hi> the name of Claudius carries contempt with it.</p>
            <p>P: 7. Brother, I <hi rend="italic">spurn</hi> it. better, than I <hi rend="italic">scorn</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Misjudging</hi> Boy is weakly. he calls him <hi rend="italic">Coward,</hi> because such a reproach was the most
						likely to sting him. <hi rend="italic">I'll do the deed</hi> myself is bolder, more resolute, more hasty, than the alteration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Lead forth the saintly</hi> &amp;c: better, shorter, &amp; more lively at first. what have I to do with <hi rend="italic">purple</hi> robes &amp; <hi rend="italic">arraignments,</hi> like a tryal at York-Assizes?</p>
            <p>P: 8. Try, if '<hi rend="italic">twill bring</hi> her deluging &amp;c: better so: only I do not like <hi rend="italic">strait</hi>
						Justice. modest <hi rend="italic">mounds</hi> is far worse.</p>
            <p>P: 9. Do <hi rend="italic">this &amp; prosper.</hi> but pray thee &amp;c: oh! how much superior to the cold lines, for wch you would
						omitt them. it is not <hi rend="italic">You,</hi> but somebody else, that has been busy both here &amp; elsewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Come</hi> from their caves. I read <q>
                  <p>Are issuing from their Caves. hear'st thou yon signal?</p>
               </q> &amp; put
							<hi rend="italic">aweful,</hi> where it was before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">I'll wait the closing</hi> &amp;c: leave it, as it was. <hi rend="italic">Do thou, as likes thee best. betray, or
							aid me.</hi> it is shorter &amp; more <hi rend="italic">sulky.</hi> Elidurus too must not go off in silence, &amp; what can he say
						better?</p>
            <p>P: 10. I do not dislike the Idea of this Ceremony, but the execution of it is careless &amp; hasty. the reply of the Semichorus is
						stolen from Dryden's Oedipus, wch perhaps you never saw nor I, since I was a Boy, at wch time it left an impression on my fancy. pray
						look at it. this <hi rend="italic">dread ground</hi> breaks my teeth. Be it <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Aske</hi>
						or <hi rend="italic">Toad.</hi> these are things for Fairies to make war upon, but not Druids: at least they must not name them. an
							<hi rend="italic">Aske</hi> is somewhat I never heard of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Full five Fathom under ground.</hi> consider five fathom is but 30 feet. many a Cellar lies deeper.</p>
            <p>I read <hi rend="italic">Gender'd by</hi> the autumnal moon. by its light I mean. <hi rend="italic">conjoin</hi> is a bad word. <hi rend="italic">supernal art profound</hi> is negligent. indeed I do not understand the image; how the snakes in copulation should <hi rend="italic">heave</hi> their egg to <hi rend="italic">ye sky</hi>: you will say, it is an old British fancy. I know it of old; but then it must be made picturesque, &amp; look almost as if it were true.</p>
            <p>P: 13. Befit such <hi rend="italic">station</hi>: the verse wants a syllable.</p>
            <p>Ev'n in the <hi rend="italic">breast</hi> of Mona. read the <hi rend="italic">heart</hi> of Mona.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Catches fresh grace.</hi> the Simile is good, but not this expression. the Tower is more majestic, more venerable,
						not more <hi rend="italic">graceful.</hi> I read –</p>
            <q>
               <p>He looks, as doth the Tower <lb/> After the conflict of Heav'n's angry bolts: <lb/> Its nodding walls, its shatter'd battlements
							<lb/> Frown with a dignity unmark'd before <lb/> Ev'n in its prime of strength— </p>
            </q>
            <p>P: 13. I do not desire, he should return the Druid's salute so politely. let him enter with that reflection, <hi rend="italic">This
							holy place</hi> &amp;c: &amp; not stand upon ceremony. it required no alteration, only I hate the word vegetate, &amp; would read</p>
            <q>
               <p>—tell me, Druid, <lb/> Is it not better to be such, as these, <lb/> Than be the thing I am? </p>
            </q>
            <p>I read too Nor <hi rend="italic">shew a Prætor's</hi> edict &amp;c: &amp; <hi rend="italic">pestilent glare,</hi> as they were
						before. add too <q>
                  <p>See to the altar's base <hi rend="italic">the Victims</hi> led &amp;c:</p>
               </q> and then, whether they were Bulls
						or Men, it is all one. I must repeat again, that the word <hi rend="italic">Seers</hi> is repeated for ever.</p>
            <p>P: 17. <hi rend="italic">I know it, rev'rend Fathers,</hi> &amp;c: this speech is sacred with me, &amp; an example of <hi rend="italic">dramatic</hi> poetry: touch not a hair of its head, as you love your honour.</p>
            <p>P: 18. I had rather some of these Personages, Resignation, Peace, Revenge, Slaughter, Ambition, were strip'd of their allegoric
						Garb: a little simplicity here in the expression would better prepare the high &amp; fantastic strain, &amp; all the unimaginable
						harpings, that follow. I admire all from <hi rend="italic">eager to snatch thee</hi> &amp;c: down to the first Epode of ye Chorus.</p>
            <p>you give these miltonic stanza's up so easily, that I begin to waver about Mador's song. if you have wrote it, &amp; it turn out the
						finest thing in the world, I rejoice &amp; say no more: let it come, tho' it were in the middle of a Sermon. but if not, I do confess
						at last, that the Chorus may break off, &amp; do very well without a word more. don't be angry at the trouble I have given you. and
						now I have found the reason, why I could not be pleased with Mador's philosophic song. the true Lyric style with all its flights of
						fancy, ornaments &amp; heightening of expression, &amp; harmony of sound, is in its nature superior to every other style. wch is just
						the cause, why it could not be born in a work of great length, no more than the eye could bear to see all this scene, that we
						constantly gaze upon, the verdure of the fields &amp; woods, the azure of the sea &amp; skies, turn'd into one dazzling expanse of
						gems. the Epic therefore assumed a style of graver colours, &amp; only stuck on a diamond (borrow'd from her Sister) here &amp; there,
						where it best became her. when we pass from the diction, that suits this kind of writing, to that wch belongs to the former: it
						appears natural, &amp; delights us. but to pass on a sudden from the lyric glare to the epic solemnity (if I may be allow'd to talk
						nonsense) has a very different effect: we seem to drop from verse into mere prose, from light into darkness. another thing is, the
						pauses proper to one, &amp; the other, are not at all the same; the ear therefore loses by the change. do you think, if
							Mingotti stop'd in the middle of her best air, &amp; only repeated the remaining verses, (tho' the
						best Metastasio ever wrote,) that they would not appear very cold to you, &amp; very heavy?</p>
            <p>P: 24. <hi rend="italic">Boldly</hi> dare, is tautology.</p>
            <p>P: 27. <hi rend="italic">Brigantum.</hi> there was no such place.</p>
            <p>P: 28. The sacred <hi rend="italic">Hares.</hi> you might as well say, the sacred <hi rend="italic">Hogs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P: 29. There is an affectation in so often using the old phrase of <hi rend="italic">Or e'er</hi> for <hi rend="italic">before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P: 30. <hi rend="italic">Rack</hi> is the course of ye clouds. <hi rend="italic">wreck</hi> is ruin &amp; destruction. wch do you
						mean?</p>
            <p>I am not yet entirely satisfied with the conclusion of this fine Allegory. <hi rend="italic">that blest prize redeem'd</hi> is
						flatly express'd, &amp; her <hi rend="italic">sticking the pages</hi> over the arch of her bower is an Idea a little burlesque.
						besides are we sure the whole is not rather too long for the place it is in, where all the interests of the scene stand still for it?
						&amp; this is still drawn out farther by the lines you have here put into the mouth of Caractacus. do not mistake me, I admire part of
						it, &amp; approve almost all, but consider the time &amp; place.</p>
            <p>P: 31. <hi rend="italic">Pensive Pilgrim.</hi> why not? there is an impropriety in <hi rend="italic">wakeful Wanderer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have told you my thoughts of this Chorus already. the whole scheme is excellent, the 2d Strophe &amp; Antistrophe divine. money (I
						know) is your motive, &amp; of that I wash my hands. fame is your second consideration; of that I am
						not the dispenser. but if your own approbation (for every one is a little conscious of his own talents) &amp; mine, have any weight
						with you, you will write an Ode or two every year, till you are turn'd of fifty, not for the World, but for us two only. we will now
						&amp; then give a little glimpse of them, but no copies.</p>
            <p>P: 37. I do not like <hi rend="italic">Maidenhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>38. Why not <hi rend="italic">smoke</hi> in vain, as before? the word <hi rend="italic">meek</hi> is too often repeated.</p>
            <p>P: 42. The only reason why you have alter'd my favourite speech is, that <hi rend="italic">surging &amp; plunging, main &amp;
							domain</hi> come too near each other. but could not you correct these without spoiling all? I read <q>
                  <p>Cast his broad eye upon the wild of Ocean, <lb/> And calm'd it with a glance: then plunging deep <lb/> His mighty arm, pluck'd
								from its dark domain &amp;c: </p>
               </q> pray, have done with your <hi rend="italic">piled stores &amp; coral floors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>43. the <hi rend="italic">Dies</hi> of Fate, that is, the <hi rend="italic">Dice</hi> of Fate. find out another word.</p>
            <p>44. I can not say I think this scene improved. I had no objection before, but to, <hi rend="italic">harm a poor wretch, like
						me</hi>; &amp; what you have inserted is (to me) inferior to what it was meant to replace, except p: 47. <hi rend="italic">And why
							this silence,</hi> wch is very well. the end of ye scene is one of my favourite passages.</p>
            <p>49. Why scratch out, Thou, <hi rend="italic">gallant Boy</hi>?</p>
            <p>I do not know to what other scene you have transfer'd these rites of lustration, but methinks they did very well here. Arviragus's
						account of himself I always was highly pleased with. </p>
            <p>51. <hi rend="italic">Fervid</hi> is a bad word.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
