<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (17 December 1752)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/56</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 170, vol. i, 366-367
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=170</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 181, vol. ii, 125-127
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/125</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 61-62
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=61</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0196">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1752-12-17"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Dodsley, Robert, 1703-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="edition">Designs by Mr. R. Bentley (1753)</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Voltaire</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Maintenon, Mme de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Birch, Thomas</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Biographia Britannica</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bayle, Pierre</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0196">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Hon<hi rend="super">ble</hi> Horace Walpole Esq</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Arlington Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>SAFFRON WALDEN 18 DE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Camb:ge Dec: 17. Sunday.</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I sent to Dodsley some time since, who wrote to me by your order, what little alterations I had to
					make, &amp; should be glad to know, whether you thought them for the better or the worse. he tells me now, he could finish in a
					fortnight, if I were in town, but this would be very inconvenient to me at present, so I must have the Sheets sent me to correct
					hither, &amp; I suppose, it may come out in less than a Month ....</p>
         <p>[ ] . . . you may imagine, I do not expect any thing very particular on either of these subjects,
					but some sort of satisfaction you will easily know how to give me in a letter; as it will be a good while, before I can see you.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Have you read Mad: Maintenon's Letters? or the Micromegas, or
						the dull Life of Dr Tillotson. I have gone thro' the 3d Vol: of the Biographia, wch will be a great Relief to you after Bayle's pedantic bawdy: all the
						Lives, mark'd with an E or a C, have something curious in them, those with a G are abominable foolish.</p>
            <p>I have just received the first Proofs from Dodsly. I thought it was to be a Qto, but it is a little Folio. the Stanzas are number'd, wch I do not like.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
