<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray and Horace Walpole to Richard West (16 April 1740)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 83, vol. i, 148-151
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=83</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. iv, 444-446
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 114, vol. i, 283-288
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915i/1/283</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, postscript, letter no. XXXVI, vol. i, 62-63
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/62</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XXI, vol. ii, 83-87
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/83</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XXI, vol. ii, 99-103
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/99</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 206-211
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=206</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0095">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000874">Rome, Italy</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1740-04-16"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">Rome</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Porto-Bello</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Ludovisi, Villa</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0095">
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Rome, April 16, 1740. N.S. </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I'll tell you, West, because one is amongst new things, you think one can always write new things. When I first came abroad, every
						thing struck me, and I wrote its history; but now I am grown so used to be surprised, that I don't perceive any flutter in myself when
						I meet with any novelties; curiosity and astonishment wear off, and the next thing is, to fancy that other people know as much of
						places as one's self; or, at least, one does not remember that they do not. It appears to me as odd to write to you of St. Peter's, as
						it would do to you to write of Westminster-abbey. Besides, as one looks at churches, &amp;c. with a book of travels in one's hand, and
						sees everything particularized there, it would appear transcribing, to write upon the same subjects. I know you will hate me for this
						declaration; I remember how ill I used to take it when anybody served me so that was travelling.–Well, I will tell you
						something, if you will love me: You have seen prints of the ruins of the temple of Minerva Medica; you shall only hear its situation,
						and then figure what a villa might be laid out there. 'Tis in the middle of a garden: at a little distance are two subterraneous
						grottos, which were the burial-places of the liberti of Augustus. There are all the niches and covers of the urns with the
						inscriptions remaining; and in one, very considerable remains of an ancient stucco ceiling with paintings in grotesque. Some of the
						walks would terminate upon the Castellum Aquæ Martiæ, St. John Lateran, and St. Maria Maggiore, besides other churches; the walls of
						the garden would be two aqueducts, and the entrance through one of the old gates of Rome. This glorious spot is neglected, and only
						serves for a small vineyard and kitchen-garden. </p>
            <p>I am very glad that I see Rome while it yet exists: before a great number of years are elapsed, I question whether it will be worth
						seeing. Between the ignorance and poverty of the present Romans, every thing is neglected and falling to decay; the villas are
						entirely out of repair, and the palaces so ill kept, that half the pictures are spoiled by damp. At the villa Ludovisi is a large
						oracular head of red marble, colossal, and with vast foramina for the eyes and mouth:–the man that showed the palace said it
						was <hi rend="italic">un ritratto della famiglia.</hi> The cardinal Corsini has so thoroughly pushed
						on the misery of Rome by impoverishing it, that there is no money but paper to be seen. He is reckoned to have amassed three millions
						of crowns. You may judge of the affluence the nobility live in, when I assure you, that what the chief princes allow for their own
						eating is a testoon a day; eighteen pence: there are some extend their expense to five pauls, or half a crown: cardinal Albani is called extravagant for laying out ten pauls for his dinner and supper. You may imagine they never have
						any entertainments: so far from it, they never have any company. The princesses and duchesses particularly lead the dismallest of
						lives. Being the posterity of popes, though of worse families than the ancient nobility, they expect greater respect than my ladies
						the countesses and marquises will pay them; consequently they consort not, but mope in a vast palace with two miserable tapers, and
						two or three monsignori, whom they are forced to court and humour, that they may not be entirely deserted. Sundays they do issue forth
						in a vast unwieldy coach to the Corso.</p>
            <p>In short, child, after sunset one passes one's time here very ill; and if I did not wish for you in the mornings, it would be no
						compliment to tell you that I do in the evening. Lord! how many English I could change for you, and yet buy you wondrous cheap! And
						then French and Germans I could fling into the bargain by dozens. Nations swarm here. You will have a great fat French cardinal
						garnished with thirty abbés roll into the area of St. Peter's, gape, turn short, and talk of the chapel of Versailles. I heard one of
						them say t'other day, he had been at the <hi rend="italic">Capitale.</hi> One asked of course how he liked it–<hi rend="italic">Ah! il y a assez de belles choses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell Asheton I have received his letter, and will write next post; but I am in a violent hurry and have no more time; so Gray
						finishes this delicately— </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>Not so delicate; nor indeed would his conscience suffer him to write to you, till he received de vos nouvelles, if he had not the
						tail of another person's letter to use by way of evasion. I sha'n't describe, as being in the only place in the world that deserves
						it; which may seem an odd reason–but they say as how it's fulsome, and every body does it (and I suppose every body says the
						same thing); else I should tell you a vast deal about the Coliseum, and the Conclave, and the Capitol, and these matters. A-propos du
						Colisée, if you don't know what it is, the prince Borghese will be very capable of giving you some account of it, who told an
						Englishman that asked what it was built for: 'They say 'twas for Christians to fight with tigers in.' We are just come from adoring a
						great piece of the true cross, St. Longinus's spear, and St. Veronica's handkerchief; all which have been this evening exposed to view
						in St. Peter's. In the same place, and on the same occasion last night, Walpole saw a poor creature naked to the waist discipline
						himself with a scourge filled with iron prickles, till he had made himself a raw doublet, that he took for red satin torn, and showing
						the skin through. I should tell you, that he fainted away three times at the sight, and I twice and a half at the repetition of it.
						All this is performed by the light of a vast fiery cross, composed of hundreds of little crystal lamps, which appears through the
						great altar under the grand tribuna, as if hanging by itself in the air. All the confraternities of the city resort thither in solemn
						procession, habited in linen frocks, girt with a cord, and their heads covered with a cowl all over, that has only two holes before to
						see through. Some of these are all black, others parti-coloured and white: and with these masqueraders that vast church is filled, who
						are seen thumping their breast, and kissing the pavement with extreme devotion. But methinks I am describing:–'tis an ill
						habit; but this, like everything else, will wear off. We have sent you our compliments by a friend of yours, and correspondent in a
						corner, who seems a very agreeable man; one Mr. Williams: I am sorry he staid so little a while in
						Rome. I forget Porto Bello all this while; pray let us know where it is, and whether you or Asheton
						had any hand in the taking of it. Duty to the admiral. Adieu!</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Ever yours, </salute>
               <signed>T. GRAY. </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
