<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Richard West to Thomas Gray (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 12 April 1742)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 104, vol. i, 194-195
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=104</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter v, section iii, 142-144
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:142</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 145, vol. ii, 30-33
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:30</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section II, letter no. 37, 160-163
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:160</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section III, letter V, vol. ii, 130-132
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:130</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section III, letter V, vol. ii, 155-158
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:155</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LIII, vol. i, 119-122
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:119</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section III, letter V, vol. i, 261-263
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:261</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0120">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown">Pope's, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1742-04-12"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0120">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>April</dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>To begin with the conclusion of your letter, which is Greek, I desire that you will quarrel no more with your manner of passing your
					time. In my opinion it is irreproachable, especially as it produces such excellent fruit; and if I, like a saucy bird, must be pecking
					at it, you ought to consider that it is because I like it. No una litura I beg you, no unravelling of your web, dear Sir! only pursue
					it a little further, and then one shall be able to judge of it a little better. You know the crisis of a play is in the first act; its
					damnation or salvation wholly rests there. But till that first act is over, every body suspends his vote; so how do you think I can
					form, as yet, any just idea of the speeches in regard to their length or shortness? The connexion and symmetry of such little parts
					with one another must naturally escape me, as not having the plan of the whole in my head; neither can I decide about the thoughts
					whether they are wrong or superfluous; they may have some future tendency which I perceive not. The style only was free to me, and
					there I find we are pretty much of the same sentiment: For you say the affectation of imitating Shakespear may doubtless be carried too
					far; I say as much and no more. For old words we know are old gold, provided they are well chosen. Whatever Ennius was, I do not consider Shakespear as a dunghill in the least: On the contrary, he is a mine of antient ore,
					where all our great modern poets have found their advantage. I do not know how it is, but his old expressions have more energy in them
					than ours, and are even more adapted to poetry; certainly, where they are judiciously and sparingly inserted, they add a certain grace
					to the composition; in the same manner as Poussin gave a beauty to his pictures by his knowledge in
					the antient proportions: But should he, or any other painter, carry the imitation too far, and neglect that best of models Nature, I am
					afraid it would prove a very flat performance. To finish this long criticism: I have this further notion about old words revived, (is
					not this a pretty way of finishing?) I think them of excellent use in tales; they add a certain drollery to the comic, and a romantic
					gravity to the serious, which are both charming in their kind; and this way of charming Dryden understood very well. One need only read
					Milton to acknowledge the dignity they give the Epic. But now comes my opinion that they ought to be used in Tragedy more sparingly,
					than in most kinds of poetry. Tragedy is designed for public representation, and what is designed for that should certainly be most
					intelligible. I believe half the audience that come to Shakespear's plays do not understand the half of what they hear.–But
					finissons enfin.–Yet one word more.–You think the ten or twelve first lines the best, now I am for the fourteen
						last; add, that they contain not one word of antientry.</p>
				     <p>I rejoice you found amusement in Joseph Andrews. But then I think your conceptions of Paradise a little upon the Bergerac. Les Lettres du Seraphim R. a Madame la Cherubinesse de Q. What a piece of extravagance would there be!</p>
				     <p>And now you must know that my body continues weak and enervate. And for my animal spirits, they are in perpetual fluctuation: Some
					whole days I have no relish, no attention for any thing; at other times I revive, and am capable of writing a long letter, as you see;
					and though I do not write speeches, yet I translate them. When you understand what speech, you will own that it is a bold and perhaps a
					dull attempt. In three words, it is prose, it is from Tacitus, it is of Germanicus. Peruse, perpend,
					pronounce.</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
