<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (19 September 1763)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
		                <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 377, vol. ii, 818-819
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=377</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 223, vol. ii, 219-221
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:219</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 129-130
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=129</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0430">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1763-09-19"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0430">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To the Honble Horace Walpole in Arlington Street London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>ROYSTON 20 SE</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				
				
				     <p>Positively I can make nothing of <hi rend="italic">St Islee,</hi>
					 &amp; thought myself sure, it was Chantilly; &amp; even believe so still, not having the book before
					me.</p>
				     <p>To be sure I look'd in Grotius' Epistles the first thing I did: he writes to no body with a name at all similar. but in the little
					book of this Ld Herberts Verses, publish'd by the <hi rend="italic">Divine Herbert</hi>
					 after his death, is a thing addressed, to <hi rend="italic">Tilenus after the fatal defluxion upon
						my arm.</hi> Now <hi rend="italic">Daniel Tilenus</hi>
					 was a great theological Writer of that time: he wrote <hi rend="italic">about Antichrist,</hi> &amp;
						<hi rend="italic">Animadversions on the Synod of Dort,</hi> &amp;c: &amp; some of his works were publish'd (I see) at Paris. he was
					however a Silesian, &amp; his true name might well be <hi rend="italic">Tieleners</hi>; &amp; as Grotius was also a deep Divine, he
					might well be acquainted with him, as well as Ld Herbert.</p>
				     <p>Do not lay your learning upon me, for I no more desire the title of <hi rend="italic">Clarissimus &amp; Celeberrimus,</hi> than you
					do. a Collecter of Antiquities, whose work (yet unpublish'd) I have before me, cites you under the name of <hi rend="italic">the lively
						Editor of the</hi> Cat: of Noble Authors. will that satisfy you better?</p>
				     <p>I give you many thanks for your political riddles: before I print them, I shall send you a List of my doubts &amp; difficulties, for
					I don't understand a word of the matter. I wonder, you should think folly less entertaining than wisdom. you, who live next door to the
					Theatre, may be as fastidious as you please, &amp; disdain to cast an eye on Garrick above once in a
					year. I, who live in the country, am excusable, if I go every night to see a troop of Strollers in a barn, as long as they stay.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, I am ever<lb/> Yours.</salute>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
