<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (18 September 1754)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 63-64</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">203 mm x 161 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 192, vol. i, 406-411
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=192</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xix, section iv, 230-231
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:230</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 175-177
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:175</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXIV, vol. i, 250-255
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:250</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XLIV, vol. ii, 247-251
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:247</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LI, vol. iii, 121-126
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:121</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXXVII, vol. ii, 3-4
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:3</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XIX, vol. i, 340-341
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:340</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0223">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1754-09-18"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0223">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton M:D:</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Pancras Lane near Cheapside</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>20 SE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Stoke, Sept: 18. 1754. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I rejoice to find you at last settled to your heart's content, &amp; delight to hear you talk of
						<hi rend="italic">giving your house some Gothic ornaments</hi> already. if you project any thing, I hope it will be entirely within
					doors; &amp; don't let me (when I come gaping into Coleman-street) be directed to the Gentleman's at
					the ten Pinnacles, or with the Church-porch at his door. I am glad you enter into the Spirit of Strawberry-Castle. it has a purity
					&amp; propriety of Gothicism in it (with very few exceptions,) that I have not seen elsewhere. the eating-room &amp; library were not compleated, when I was there, &amp; I want to know, what effect they have. my Ld Radnor's
						Vagaries (I see) did not keep you from doing justice to his situation, wch far surpasses every thing
					near it, &amp; I do not know a more <hi rend="italic">laughing</hi> Scene, than that about Twickenham &amp; Richmond. Dr
						Akenside (I perceive) is no Conjurer in Architecture, especially
					when he talks of the Ruins of Persepolis, wch are no more Gothic, than they are Chinese. the Egyptian Style (see Dr Pococke, not his discourses, but his prints) was apparently the Mother of ye Greek; &amp; there is such a similitude
					between the Egyptian, &amp; those Persian Ruins, as gave room to Diodorus to affirm, that the old
					buildings of Persia were certainly perform'd by Egyptian Artists. as to the other part of his opinion, that the Gothic manner is the
					Saracen or Moorish, he has a great Authority to support him, that of Sr Christ:r Wren, &amp; yet (I
					can not help thinking) is undoubtedly wrong. the Palaces in Spain I never saw but in description, wch gives us little or no Idea of
					things; but the Doge's Palace at Venice I have seen (wch is in the Arabesque manner) &amp; the houses
					of Barbary you may see in Dr Shaw's book, not to mention abundance of other eastern Buildings in
					Turky, Persia, &amp;c: that we have views of, &amp; they seem plainly to be corruptions of the Greek Architecture, broke into little
					parts indeed, &amp; cover'd with little ornaments, but in a taste very distinguishable from that we call Gothic. there is one thing,
					that runs thro' the Moorish Buildings, that an Imitator would certainly have been first struck with, &amp; would have tried to copy,
					&amp; that is the Cupola's, wch cover everything, Baths, Apar[t]ments, &amp; even Kitchens. yet who ever saw a Gothic Cupola? it is a
					thing plainly of Greek original. I do not see any thing but the slender Spires, that serve for steeples, wch may perhaps be borrowed
					from the Saracen Minarets on their Mosques.</p>
         <p>I was in Northamptonshire, when I received your Letter, but am now returned hither. I have been at
					Warwick, wch is a place worth seeing. the Town is on an eminence surrounded every way with a fine cultivated Valley, thro' wch the Avon
					winds, &amp; at the distance of 5 or 6 miles, a circle of hills well wooded, &amp; with various objects crowning them, that close the
					Prospect. out of the town on one side of it rises a rock, that might remind one of your rocks at Durham, but that it is not so savage,
					or so lofty, &amp; that the river, wch washes its foot, is perfectly clear, &amp; so gentle, that its current is hardly visible. upon
					it stands the Castle, the noble old residence of the Beauchamps &amp; Neville's, &amp; now of Earl Brooke. he has sash'd the great Appartment, that's to be sure, (I can't help these things) &amp; being since told,
					that square sash-windows were not Gothic, he has put certain whim-wams withinside the glass, wch appearing through are to look like
					fretwork. then he has scooped out a little Burrough in the massy walls of the place for his little self &amp; his children, wch is hung with Paper &amp; printed Linnen, &amp; carved chimney-pieces, in the exact manner of
					Berkley-square or Argyle-Buildings. what in short can a Lord do now a days, that is lost in a great old solitary Castle, but sculk
					about, &amp; get into the first hole he finds, as a Rat would do in like case. a pretty long old stone-bridge leads you into the town
					with a Mill at the end of it, over wch the rock rises with the Castle upon it with all its battlements &amp; queer ruin'd towers, &amp;
					on your left hand the Avon strays thro' the Park, whose ancient Elms seem to remember Sr Philip Sidney, (who often walk'd under them) and talk of him to this day. the Beauchamp Earls of Warwick lie
					under stately Monuments in the Choir of the great Church, &amp; in our Lady's Chappel adjoining to it. there also lie Ambrose Dudley,
					E: of Warwick; &amp; his Brother, the famous Ld Leicester, with Lettice, his Countess. this Chappel is preserved entire, tho' the Body of the Church was burnt down 60 years ago, &amp; rebuilt by
					Sr C: Wren. I had heard often of Guy-Cliff two miles from the town, so I walked to see it; &amp; of all improvers commend me to Mr
						Greathead, its present Owner. he shew'd it me himself, &amp; is literally a fat young Man with a
					head &amp; face much bigger than they are usually worn. it was naturally a very agreeable rock, whose Cliffs cover'd with large trees
					hung beetleing over the Avon, wch twists twenty ways in sight of it. there was the Cell of Guy, Earl of Warwick, cut in the living
					stone, where he died a Hermit (as you may see in a penny History, that hangs upon the rails in
						Moorfields) there were his fountains bubbling out of the Cliff; there was a Chantry founded to his
					memory in Henry the 6th's time. but behold the Trees are cut down to make room for flowering shrubs,
					the rock is cut up, till it is as smooth &amp; as sleek as sattin; the river has a gravel-walk by its side; the Cell is a Grotta with
						cockle-shells and looking-glass; the fountains have an iron-gate before them, and the Chantry is a
					Barn, or a little House. even the poorest bits of nature, that remain, are daily threatned, for he
					says (&amp; I am sure, when the Greatheads are once set upon a thing, they will do it) he is determined, it shall be <hi rend="italic">all new.</hi> These were his words, &amp; they are Fate. I have also been at Stow, at Woburn (the Du[ke] of Bedford's), and at Wroxton (Ld Guilford's) but I defer
					these Chapt[ers] till we meet. I shall only tell you for your Comfort, that th[e] part of Northampt:re, where I have been, is in
					fruits, in flowers [&amp; in] corn very near a fortnight night behind this part of Buckinghamshire, that they have no nightingales,
					&amp; that the other birds are almost as silent, as at Durham. it is rich land, but upon a Clay, &amp; in a very bleak, high, exposed
					situation. I hope, you have had some warm weather, since you last complained of the South. I have thoughts of seeing you about
					Michaelmas, tho' I shall not stay long in town. I should have been at Camb:ge before now, if the D: of Newc:le &amp; his
						foundation-stone would have let me, but I want them to have done before I go. I am sorry Mr Brown should be the only one, that has stood upon Punctilio's with me, &amp; would not write
					first. pray tell him so. Mason is (I believe) in town, or at Chiswick. [no news of Tuthill]: I wrote a long letter to him in answer to one he wrote me, but no reply.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am ever Yrs,</salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Brown call'd here this morning, before I was up, &amp; breakfasted with me. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
