<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (4 April 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 94</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 514, vol. iii, 1115-1116
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=514</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLVIII, vol. iii, 269-270
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/269</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXVI, vol. v, 104-106
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843v/1/104</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0588">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-04-04"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Shakespeare, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Gruner, Gottlieb Sigmund</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Clark, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Calais</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Boulogne</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Abbéville</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0588">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk By Yarmouth</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>4 April. 1770. P: Hall: </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>At length, my dear Sr, we have lost our poor de B:n I pack'd him up with my own hands in the Dover-machine at 4 o'clock in the
					morning on Friday, 23 March, the next day at 7 he sail'd &amp; reach'd <hi rend="italic">Calais</hi>
					by noon, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Boulogne</hi> at night. the next night he reach'd <hi rend="italic">Abbeville,</hi> where he had
					letters to Mad: Vanrobais, to whom belongs the famous manufacture of cloth there. from thence he wrote to me, &amp; here am I again to pass my solitary evenings, wch hung much lighter on my hands, before I knew him.
					this is your fault! pray let the next you send me, be halt &amp; blind, dull, unapprehensive &amp; wrong-headed. for this (as Lady
					Constance says) <hi rend="italic">Was never such a gracious Creature born!</hi>
					 &amp; yet–but no matter! burn my letter that I wrote you,
					for I am very much out of humour with myself &amp; will not believe a word of it. you will think, I have caught madness from him (for
					he is certainly mad) &amp; perhaps you will be right. oh! what things are Fathers &amp; Mothers! I thought they were to be found only
					in England, but you see.</p>
         <p>Where is Capt: Clarke's Translation? where is your journal? do
					you still haggle for me to save sixpence, you Niggard? why now I have been in Town &amp; brought no franks with me yet. the translation
					of <hi rend="italic">Gruner</hi>
					 can not be had this month or six weeks, so I am destitute of all things. this place never appear'd
					so horrible to me, as it does now. could not you come for a week or fortnight? it would be sunshine to me in a dark night! even Dr
						Hallifax wishes, you would come. at least write to me out of hand, for I am truly &amp;
					faithfully</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>'Vous ne voyez plus que de la misere &amp; de la gayeté. les villages sont plus rares, plus petits: le silence dans ces deserts
						annonce par tout un Maitre. il me sembloit, que je devois demander a ces hommes en guenilles, qui leur avoit pris leurs habits, leurs
						maisons; quelle peste avoit ravagé la nation. mais ils ont le bonheur de ne penser point, &amp; de jouer jusqu'au moment qu'on les
						egorge. </p>
            <p>'Mais gardons notre indignation pour çeux qui sont si stupides, qu'ils prennent de pareilles mœurs pour modeles.'
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
