<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Richard West to Thomas Gray (4 July 1737)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 38, vol. i, 61-64
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=38</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter vii, section i, 18-22
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:18</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 58, vol. i, 139-142
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:139</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section II, letter no. 14, 95-98
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:95</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section I, letter VII, vol. ii, 13-16
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:13</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section I, letter VII, vol. ii, 15-18
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:15</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter VII, vol. i, 15-19
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:15</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section I, letter VII, vol. i, 148-152
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:148</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0041">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011931">Oxford, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1737-07-04"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0041">
			   <body>
				
				     <p>I have been very ill, and am still hardly recovered. Do you remember Elegy 5th, Book the 3d, of Tibullus, Vos tenet, &amp;c. and do
					you remember a letter of Mr Pope's, in sickness, to Mr Steele? This melancholy elegy and this melancholy letter I turned into a more
					melancholy epistle of my own, during my sickness, in the way of imitation; and this I send to you and my friends at Cambridge, not to
					divert them, for it cannot, but merely to show them how sincere I was when sick: I hope my sending it to them now may convince them I
					am no less sincere, though perhaps more simple, when well. </p>
				     <p>AD AMICOS.</p>
				     <p>Yes, happy youths, on Camus' sedgy side, <lb/> You feel each joy that friendship can divide; <lb/> Each realm of science and of art
					explore, <lb/> And with the antient blend the modern lore. <lb/> Studious alone to learn whate'er may tend <lb/> To raise the genius
					or the heart to mend; <lb/> Now pleas'd along the cloyster'd walk you rove, <lb/> And trace the verdant mazes of the grove, <lb/>
					Where social oft, and oft alone, ye chuse <lb/> To catch the zephyr and to court the muse. <lb/> Mean time at me (while all devoid of
					art <lb/> These lines give back the image of my heart) <lb/> At me the pow'r that comes or soon or late, <lb/> Or aims, or seems to
					aim, the dart of fate; <lb/> From you remote, methinks, alone I stand <lb/> Like some sad exile in a desert land; <lb/> Around no
					friends their lenient care to join <lb/> In mutual warmth, and mix their heart with mine. <lb/> Or real pains, or those which fancy
					raise, <lb/> For ever blot the sunshine of my days; <lb/> To sickness still, and still to grief a prey, <lb/> Health turns from me
					her rosy face away. </p>
				     <p>Just heav'n! what sin, ere life begins to bloom, <lb/> Devotes my head untimely to the tomb; <lb/> Did e'er this hand against a
					brother's life <lb/> Drug the dire bowl or point the murd'rous knife? <lb/> Did e'er this tongue the slanderer's tale proclaim,
					<lb/> Or madly violate my Maker's name? <lb/> Did e'er this heart betray a friend or foe, <lb/> Or know a thought but all the world
					might know? <lb/> As yet just started from the lists of time, <lb/> My growing years have scarcely told their prime; <lb/> Useless,
					as yet, through life I've idly run, <lb/> No pleasures tasted, and few duties done. <lb/> Ah, who, ere autumn's mellowing suns
					appear, <lb/> Would pluck the promise of the vernal year; <lb/> Or, ere the grapes their purple hue betray, <lb/> Tear the crude
					cluster from the mourning spray. <lb/> Stern Power of Fate, whose ebon sceptre rules <lb/> The Stygian deserts and Cimmerian pools,
					<lb/> Forbear, nor rashly smite my youthful heart, <lb/> A victim yet unworthy of thy dart; <lb/> Ah, stay till age shall blast my
					withering face, <lb/> Shake in my head, and falter in my pace; <lb/> Then aim the shaft, then meditate the blow, <lb/> And to the
					dead my willing shade shall go.</p>
				     <p>How weak is Man to Reason's judging eye! <lb/> Born in this moment, in the next we die; <lb/> Part mortal clay, and part ethereal
					fire, <lb/> Too proud to creep, too humble to aspire. <lb/> In vain our plans of happiness we raise, <lb/> Pain is our lot, and
					patience is our praise; <lb/> Wealth, lineage, honours, conquest, or a throne, <lb/> Are what the wise would fear to call their own.
					<lb/> Health is at best a vain precarious thing, <lb/> And fair-fac'd youth is ever on the wing; <lb/> 'Tis like the stream, beside
					whose wat'ry bed <lb/> Some blooming plant exalts his flowry head, <lb/> Nurs'd by the wave the spreading branches rise, <lb/> Shade
					all the ground and flourish to the skies; <lb/> The waves the while beneath in secret flow, <lb/> And undermine the hollow bank
					below; <lb/> Wide and more wide the waters urge their way, <lb/> Bare all the roots and on their fibres prey. <lb/> Too late the
					plant bewails his foolish pride, <lb/> And sinks, untimely, in the whelming tide.</p>
				     <p>But why repine, does life deserve my sigh? <lb/> Few will lament my loss whene'er I die. <lb/> For those the wretches I despise or
					hate, <lb/> I neither envy nor regard their fate.<lb/> For me, whene'er all-conquering Death shall
					spread <lb/> His wings around my unrepining head, <lb/> I care not; though this face be seen no more, <lb/> The world will pass as
					chearful as before, <lb/> Bright as before the day-star will appear, <lb/> The fields as verdant, and the skies as clear;<lb/> Nor storms nor comets will my doom declare, <lb/> Nor signs on earth, nor portents in the air; <lb/>
					Unknown and silent will depart my breath, <lb/> Nor Nature e'er take notice of my death. <lb/> Yet some there are (ere spent my vital
						days)<lb/> Within whose breasts my tomb I wish to raise. <lb/> Lov'd in my life, lamented in my
					end, <lb/> Their praise would crown me as their precepts mend: <lb/> To them may these fond lines my name endear, <lb/> Not from the
					Poet but the Friend sincere.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <dateline>Christ Church, July 4, 1737.</dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
