<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 1 April 1742)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 101, vol. i, 188-189
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=101</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter ii, section iii, 122-123
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/122</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 131-132
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/NoC_1911/1/131</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 141, vol. ii, 20-22
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/20</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LI, vol. i, 94-96
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/94</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section III, letter II, vol. ii, 122-123
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/122</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section III, letter II, vol. ii, 146-147
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/146</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter L, vol. i, 112-114
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/112</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section III, letter II, vol. i, 243-244
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/243</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0117">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1742-04-01"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="poem">Agrippina, a Tragedy</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Tacitus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pope, Alexander</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Lee, Nathaniel</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0117">
      <body>
         <p>I trust to the country, and that easy indolence you say you enjoy there, to restore you your health and spirits; and doubt not but,
					when the sun grows warm enough to tempt you from your fire-side, you will (like all other things) be the better for his influence. He
					is my old friend, and an excellent nurse, I assure you. Had it not been for him, life had often been to me intolerable. Pray do not
					imagine that Tacitus, of all authors in the world, can be tedious. An annalist, you know, is by no means master of his subject; and I
					think one may venture to say, that if those Pannonian affairs are tedious in his hands, in another's they would have been
					insupportable. However, fear not, they will soon be over, and he will make ample amends. A man, who could join the <hi rend="italic">brilliant</hi> of wit and concise sententiousness peculiar to that age, with the truth and gravity of better times, and the deep
					reflection and good sense of the best moderns, cannot choose but have something to strike you. Yet what I admire in him above all this,
					is his detestation of tyranny, and the high spirit of liberty that every now and then breaks out, as it were, whether he would or no. I
					remember a sentence in his Agricola that (concise as it is) I always admired for saying much in a little compass. He speaks of
					Domitian, who upon seeing the last will of that General, where he had made him Coheir with his Wife and Daughter, 'Satis constabat
					lætatum eum, velut honore, judicioque: tam cæca &amp; corrupta mens assiduis adulationibus erat, ut nesciret a bono patre non scribi
					hæredem, nisi malum principem'.
				</p>
         <p>As to the Dunciad, it is greatly admired: the Genii of Operas and Schools, with their attendants, the pleas of the Virtuosos and Florists, and the
					yawn of dulness in the end, are as fine as anything he has written. The Metaphysicians' part is to me the worst; and here and there a few ill-expressed lines, and some hardly intelligible.</p>
         <p>I take the liberty of sending you a long speech of Agrippina; much too long, but I could be glad you
					would retrench it. Aceronia, you may remember, had been giving quiet counsels. I fancy, if it ever be finished, it will be in the
					nature of Nat. Lee's Bedlam Tragedy, which had twenty-five acts and some odd scenes.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
