<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (20 May 1771)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <condition>
                           <p>two thirds of the letter are missing including the address on the envelope</p>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 108</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 552, vol. iii, 1186-1188
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=552</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xi, section v, 393-394
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/393</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXXXIII, vol. iii, 318-319
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/318</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XLI, vol. v, 139-141
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843v/1/139</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0635">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1771-05-20"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Clark, John</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0635">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>London. 20 May. 1771. <lb/> at Frisby's, Jermyn-Street.</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I received your letter inclosing that of poor T: the night before I set out for London. I would by
					all means wish you to comply with his request. you may say many things to Ld L: with a better grace,
					than he can. I trust to the cause, &amp; to the warmth of your own kindness, for inspiration: there is little of management required,
					nothing to conceal, but the full persuasion (I trust) we both have, that Ld L: knows the distress of his circumstances at least as well
					as we do. this doubtless must be kept out of sight, lest it carry too keen a reproach with it. in all the rest you are at full liberty
					to expatiate on his good qualities, the friendship you have long had for him, the pious imprudence, that has produced his present
					uneasy situation, &amp; above all your profound respect for Lord L:s character &amp; sensibility of heart.
				</p>
         <p>who knows what may be the consequence? Men sometimes catch that feeling from a Stranger, wch should have originally sprung from their
					own heart. as to the means of helping him, his own schemes are perhaps too wild for you to mention them to Ld L: &amp; (if they are to
					separate him from his Wife &amp; family) what is to come of them in the mean time? I have a notion that the Chaplainship at Leghorn is
					still vacant by the death of a young Mr Byrom. at least I have never heard it was fill'd up. it depends on recommendation to the
					principal Italian Merchants, wch seems much in Ld L:s power. The Bp of Derry (I apprehend) is at
					Nice, or somewhere in Italy, for his health: it is true he has a great patronage in Ireland, &amp; sometimes (from vanity) may do a
					right thing. the other projects do not strike me as any thing, but (if Ld L: can be brought to mean him well) many different means will
					occur, by wch he may serve him.</p>
         <p>I shall pass a fortnight here, &amp; perhaps within that time may see you in Town, at least I would wish so to do. I am but indifferently well, &amp; think, all things consider'd, it is best not to keep you in suspense
					about my journey. the sense of my own duty, which I do not perform,
					my own low spirits (to which this consideration not a little contributes) &amp; (added to these) a bodily indisposition make it
					necessary for me to deny myself that pleasure, which perhaps I have kept too long in view. I shall see however with your eyes, &amp;
					accompany you at least in idea. write or come, or both soon.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am ever yours sincerely,</salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>My respects to Mrs Nicholls. Clarke (I hear) is in town at Claxton's.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
