<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs. (Dorothy) Gray (13 October 1739)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 71, vol. i, 121-123
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=71</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter viii, section ii, 58-60
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:58</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XXIV, vol. i, 38-39
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:38</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter VIII, vol. ii, 52-54
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:52</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter VIII, vol. ii, 60-62
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:60</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXVI, vol. i, 52-55
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:52</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter VIII, vol. i, 185-186
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:185</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0081">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008772">Lyon, France</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1739-10-13"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Gray, Mrs. (Dorothy), 1685-1753</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0081">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Lyons, Oct. 13, N. S. 1739. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>It is now almost five weeks since I left Dijon, one of the gayest and most agreeable little cities of France, for Lyons, its reverse
					in all these particulars. It is the second in the kingdom in bigness and rank, the streets excessively narrow and nasty; the houses
					immensely high and large; (that, for instance, where we are lodged, has twenty-five rooms on a floor, and that for five stories) it
					swarms with inhabitants like Paris itself, but chiefly a mercantile people, too much given up to commerce, to think of their own, much
					less of a stranger's diversions. We have no acquaintance in the town, but such English as happen to be passing through here, in their
					way to Italy and the South, which at present happen to be near thirty in number. It is a fortnight since we set out from hence upon a
					little excursion to Geneva. We took the longest road, which lies through Savoy, on purpose to see a famous monastery, called the grand
						Chartreuse, and had no reason to think our time lost. After having travelled [two] days very slow (for we did not change horses, it being impossible for a chaise to go post in these roads) we
					arrived at a little village, among the mountains of Savoy, called Echelles; from thence we proceeded on horses, who are used to the
					way, to the mountain of the Chartreuse: It is six miles to the top; the road runs winding up it, commonly not six feet broad; on one
					hand is the rock, with woods of pine-trees hanging over head; on the other, a monstrous precipice, almost perpendicular, at the bottom
					of which rolls a torrent, that sometimes tumbling among the fragments of stone that have fallen from on high, and sometimes
					precipitating itself down vast descents with a noise like thunder, which is still made greater by the echo from the mountains on each
					side, concurs to form one of the most solemn, the most romantic, and the most astonishing scenes I ever beheld: Add to this the strange
					views made by the craggs and cliffs on the other hand; the cascades that in many places throw themselves from the very summit down into
					the vale, and the river below; and many other particulars impossible to describe; you will conclude we had no occasion to repent our
					pains. This place St. Bruno chose to retire to, and upon its very top founded the aforesaid Convent, which is the superior of the whole
					order. When we came there, the two fathers, who are commissioned to entertain strangers, (for the rest must neither speak one to
					another, nor to any one else) received us very kindly; and set before us a repast of dried fish, eggs, butter, and fruits, all
					excellent in their kind, and extremely neat. They pressed us to spend the night there, and to stay some days with them; but this we
					could not do, so they led us about their house, which is, you must think, like a little city; for there are 100 fathers, besides 300
					servants, that make their clothes, grind their corn, press their wine, and do every thing among themselves: The whole is quite orderly
					and simple; nothing of finery, but the wonderful decency, and the strange situation, more than supply the place of it. In the evening
					we descended by the same way, passing through many clouds that were then forming themselves on the mountain's side. Next day we
					continued our journey by Chamberry, which, though the chief city of the Dutchy, and residence of the king of Sardinia, when he comes into this part of his dominions, makes but a very mean and insignificant appearance; we lay at
					Aix, once famous for its hot baths, and the next night at Annecy; the day after, by noon, we got to Geneva. I have not time to say any
					thing about it, nor of our solitary journey back again. [...]</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
