<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (13 October 1764)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HSPO">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</institution>
		                <repository>Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 393, vol. ii, 844-847
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=393</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXXXV, 323-327
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:323</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXI, vol. iii, 43-46
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:43</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0446">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011385">Southampton, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1764-10-13"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0446">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Brown, President of Pembroke Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>Southampton 13 OC</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Oct: 13. . Southampton.</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Since I have been here, I have received from you, &amp; by your means, five letters. that from Pa:
					I could wish, you had open'd; as I know, you by your good will would have done. the sum of it is, that he is at Geneva with the Rhone
					tumbling its blew &amp; green tide directly under his window. that he has pass'd a fortnight in the Pais de Vaux, &amp; the Cantons of
					Bern, Fribourg, &amp; Soleurre, &amp; return'd by the Lake of Neufchatel. that the whole country &amp; particularly the last-named
					appear'd to him astonishingly beautiful. he enquired much after Rousseau, but did not meet with him.
					his residence is at <hi rend="italic">Moitier</hi>
					
					       <hi rend="italic">au Travers</hi> about 4 Leagues from Neufchatel, where he lives in great plenty, the Booksellers at the Hague being
					his Bank, &amp; ready to answer any sum he draws for. it is amazing, what he got by his two last books. he is often flying about from village to village, generally wears a sort of Armenian dress, &amp;
					posses for a kind of Misanthrope, but is held in great veneration by the people.</p>
				     <p>He says, he saw all the matters that come in course in France, &amp; was greatly disappointed. the only thing he mentions is the
					Church at Amiens, wch was really fine. they set out in a few days (his date is 19 Sept:) &amp; go by Chamberry to Turin, from whence he
					will write to you. his letter (he says) is not worth the postage, but it is the abundance, &amp; not the want, of matter, that makes it
					so poor.
				</p>
				     <p>After this what shall I say to you of my Lilliputian travels? on Monday I think to see Salisbury,
					&amp; to be sure Wilton, &amp; Amesbury &amp; Stone-henge. this will take up three days, &amp; then I come back hither, &amp; think to
					be in London on Saturday or Monday after. for the weather grows untoward, &amp; the Sea (that is this
					little miniature of it, Southampton-River) rages horribly, &amp; looks as if it would eat one. else I should have gone to Lymington
					&amp; Christchurch, &amp; call'd upon Mr Mansfield in the New-forest to see the Bow, that kill'd
					William Rufus, wch he pretends to possess. (say not a word of Andover! ) my Ld Delawar has erected a
					little monument on the spot, where according to ancient tradition that King was slain, &amp; another
					in Gods-House Chappel, where the Earl of Cambridge, Ld Scroop &amp;
					Sr Thomas Grey were inter'd by Henry 5th, after he had cut off their heads: it is in this Town, &amp; now the French Church. here lives
					Dr St Andre, famous for the affair of the Rabbit-Woman, &amp; for
					marrying Lady Betty Molyneux, after they had disposed of her first Husband. She died not long since in the odour of sanctity. he is 80
					years old, &amp; is now building a Palazzino here hard by in a delightful spot call'd <hi rend="italic">Bellevue,</hi> &amp; has lately
					produced a natural Son to inherit it. what do you say to poor Iwan, &amp; the last Russ Manifesto?
					will no body kill me that Dragoness? must we wait, till her Son
					does it himself.</p>
				     <p>Mr St: has been at Glamis. he tells me no news. he only confutes a piece of news I sent him, wch I
					am glad to hear, is a lye. I must tell you a small anecdote I just hear, that delights me. Sr F: Norton has a mother living in a town in Yorkshire in a very indifferent lodging. a good house was to be
					sold there the other day. he thought in decency he ought to appear willing to buy it for her. when the people, to whom it belongs,
					imagined that every thing was agreed on, he insisted on having two pictures as fixtures, wch they value at 60£. so Mrs Norton lives,
					where she did.</p>
				     <p>I am sorry for the D: of Devonshire! the cause, I fear is losing ground; &amp; I know the Person
					(where Mr T: has lately been) look'd upon all as gone, if this event should happen. Adieu! when I get
					to Town, I shall pick up something to tell you.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am ever Yours.</salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I know nothing of Mason but that he is well.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
