<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (23 February 1738)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
		                <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 49, vol. i, 79-80
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=49</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 76, vol. i, 178-180
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:178</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 151-152
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=151</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0053">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1738-02-23"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0053">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Honble Horace Walpole Esq</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>at the Treasury St James</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>SAFFRON WALDEN 24 FE</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>My best Horace</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I confess, I am amazed: of all likely things this is the last I should have believed would come to pass: however I congratulate you upon being able at this time to talk of Clytemnæstra, &amp; Mrs Porter: I wish, you have not admired this last-mention'd Gentlewoman long enough to catch a little of her art from
					her, for if I'm not mistaken, you are a very different person behind the Scenes, &amp; whatever face you set upon the matter, I guess
					– but perhaps I guess wrong; I wish I may for your sake; perhaps you are as cool as you would seem: either way I may wish you
					joy; of your Dissimulation, or Philosophy: I long extremely to see you, but till I have that pleasure, me-thinks you might be a little
					more open in writing; have pity a little upon my curiosity: if you distrust my faith (I won't say Honour; that's for Gentlefolks) and imagine I would shew your letters to any one; yet rely upon my vanity, which won't suffer me to do an
					ill thing; if you fear the common fate of loose papers, I give you my word to sacrifice to the fire immediately (no small sacrifice, I
					assure you) all I shall receive, if you desire it: I don't wonder at the new study you have taken a likeing to; first because it
					diverts your thoughts from disagreeable objects, next, because it particularly suits your Genius, &amp; lastly, because I believe it
					the most excellent of all sciences, to which in proportion as the rest are subservient, so great a degree of estimation they ought to
					gain: would you believe it, 'tis the very thing I would wish to apply to, myself? ay! as simple as I stand here: but then the Apparatus necessary to it costs so much; nay, part of it is wholly out of one's power to
					procure; and then who should pare one, &amp; burnish one? for they would have more trouble &amp; fuss with me, than Cinderaxa's sisters had with their feet, to make 'em fit for the little glass Slipper: oh yes! to be sure one must be
					lick'd; now to lick oneself I take to be altogether impracticable, &amp; to ask another to lick one, would not be quite so civil; Bear
					I was born, &amp; bear, I believe, I'm like to remain: consequently a little ungainly in my fondnesses, but I'll be bold to say, you
					shan't in a hurry meet with a more loving poor animal, than</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>your faithful Creature,</salute>
					       <signed>BRUIN. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P: S: I beg you to continue your Essay: &amp; tell Zeph: when you
						see him to expect a letter in Rabbinical Hebrew from me, unless he writes directly.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
