<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray and Horace Walpole to Thomas Ashton (14 May 1740)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <institution key="PRIV">Private collection</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a MS transcript is at the British Library, Add. MSS 32562, ff. 128-134; a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 85, vol. i, 152-155
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=85</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section I, letter no. 6, 49-54
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:49</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 117, vol. i, 293-297
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:293</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, postscript, letter no. XXXVII, vol. i, 63-65
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:63</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 214-218
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=214</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0097">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000874">Rome, Italy</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1740-05-14"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227197">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0097">
			   <body>
				     <div type="part">
					       <opener>
						
						         <dateline>Rome, May 14, 1740. N.S. </dateline>
					       </opener>
					       <p>Boileau's Discord dwelt in a College of Monks. At present the Lady is in the Conclave. Cardinal
							Corsini has been interrogated about certain Millions of Crowns that are absent from the Apostolic
						Chamber; He refuses giving Account, but to a Pope: However he has set several Arithmeticians to work, to compose Summs, &amp; flourish
						out Expenses, which probably never existed. Cardinal Cibo pretends to have a Banker at Genoa, who
						will prove that he has received three Millions on the Part of the Eminent Corsini. This Cibo is a madman, but set on by others. He had
						formerly some great office in the government, from whence they are generally rais'd to the Cardinalate. After a time, not being
						promoted as he expected, he resign'd his Post, and retir'd to a Mountain where He built a most magnificient Hermitage. There He
						inhabited for two years, grew tir'd, came back and received the Hat. </p>
					       <p>Other feuds have been between Card. Portia and the Faction of Benedict the Thirteenth, by whom He was made Cardinal. About a month ago, he was within three Votes of being Pope. he did not apply
						to any Party, but went gleaning privately from all &amp; of a sudden burst out with a Number; but too soon, &amp; that threw Him quite
						out. Having been since left out of their Meetings, he ask'd one of the Benedictine Cardinals the reason; who replied, that he never
						had been their Friend, &amp; never should be of their assemblies; &amp; did not even hesitate to call him Apostate. This flung Portia
						into such a Rage that He spit blood, &amp; instantly left the Conclave with all his Baggage. But the great Cause of their Antipathy to
						Him, was His having been one of the Four, that voted for putting Coscia to Death; Who now regains his
						Interest, &amp; may prove somewhat disagreable to his Enemies; Whose Honesty is not abundantly heavier than His Own. He met Corsini
						t'other Day, &amp; told Him, He heard His Eminence had a mind to his Cell: Corsini answer'd He was very well contented with that He
						had. Oh, says Coscia, I don't mean here in the Conclave; but in the Castle St. Angelo.</p>
					       <p>With all these Animosities, One is near having a Pope. Card. Gotti, an Old, inoffensive Dominican,
						without any Relations, wanted yesterday but two voices; &amp; is still most likely to succeed. Card. Altieri has been sent for from
						Albano, whither he was retir'd upon account of his Brother's Death, &amp; his own Illness; &amp;
						where He was to stay till the Election drew nigh. There! there's a sufficient Competency of Conclave News, I think.</p>
					       <p>We have miserable Weather for the Season; Coud You think I was writing to You by my fireside at Rome in the middle of May? the
						Common People say tis occasion'd by the Pope's Soul, which cannot find Rest. </p>
					       <p>How goes your War? We are persuaded here of an additional one with France, Lord! it will be dreadfull to return thro Germany. I
						don't know who cooks up the News, here, but we have some Strange Peice every day. One that is much in Vogue, &amp; would not be
						disagreable for US, is, that the Czarina has clap'd the Marquis de la Chetardie in Prison. One must hope till some Months hence tis all contradicted.</p>
					       <p>I am balancing in great Uncertainty, whether to go to Naples or stay here; You know 'twoud be provoking to have a Pope chosen just
						as One's Back was turn'd: and if I wait, I fear the Heats may arrive. I don't know what to do. </p>
					       <p>We are going to-night to a Great Assembly, at One of the Villas just out of the City, whither all the English are invited; amongst the rest, Mr. Stuard and his two Sons. There is one lives with Him
						call'd Lord Dunbar, Murray's brother, who wou'd be his Minister, if
						he had any Occasion for One. I meet him frequently in public places, &amp; like Him. He is very sensible, very agreable &amp; well
						bred.</p>
					       <p>Good night, Child: by the way I have had no letters from England, these two last Posts. </p>
					       <closer>
               <salute>Yrs ever.</salute>
            </closer>
				     </div>
				     <div type="part">
					       <p>I am by trade a Finisher of Letters. don't you wonder at the Conclave? instead of being immured, every one in his proper hutch, as
						one used to imagine: they have the liberty of skuttleing out of one hole into another, &amp; might breed, if they were young enough. I
						do assure you every thing one has heard say of Italy is a Lye, &amp; am firmly of opinion, that no mortal was ever here before us. I
						am writeing to prove there never was any such people as the Romans, that this was antiently a Colony of the Jews, and that the
						Coliseum was built on the model of Solomon's Temple. our people have told so many Stories of them, that they don't believe any thing
						we say about ourselves; Porto Bello is still said to be impregnable &amp; it is reported the Dutch
						have declared War against us. the English Court here brighten up on the News of our Conquests, &amp; conclude all the contrary has
						happen'd. you do not know perhaps, that we have our little good fortune in the Mediterranean, where Adml. Haddock has overturn'd
						certain little Boats carrying troops to Majorca, drown'd a few hundreds of them, &amp; taken a little Grandee of Spain, that commanded
						the expedition: at least so they say at Naples: I'm very sorry, but methinks they seem in a bad
						condition. is West dead to the World in general, or only so to me? for you I have not the impudence to accuse; but you are to take
						this, as a sort of reproof, &amp; I hope you will demean yourself accordingly. you are hereby authorized to make my very particular
						compliments to My Ld. Plymouth, &amp; return him my thanks de l'honneur de son souvenir. so I finish my Postscript with</p>
					       <closer>
               <salute>Yours Ever</salute>
						         <signed>T:G:</signed>
            </closer>
				     </div>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
