<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (26 May 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/3/1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 334, vol. ii, 738-739
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=334</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXVI, 260-262
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:260</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXI, vol. ii, 214-215
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:214</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0385">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-05-26"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Belleisle</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0385">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Brown M:A: President of Pembroke Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>26 MA GR</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I thank you for your kind enquiries &amp; impatience about me. had I not been so often disappointed before, when I thought myself
					sure, I should have informed you before this time of my motions. I thought I was just setting out for Cambridge, when the Man (on whom
					I have a mortgage) gave me notice, that he was ready to pay in his money: so that now I must
					necessarily stay to receive it, &amp; it will be (to be sure) the middle of June before I can see
					Cambridge, where I have long wish'd to be. Montagu had thoughts of going thither with me, but I know not what his present intentions
					may be: he is in real affliction for the loss of Sr W: Williams, who has left him one of his
					Executors, &amp; (as I doubt his affairs were a good deal embarrass'd), he possibly may be detain'd
					in Town on that account. Mason too talk'd of staying part of the summer with me at Pembroke, but this may perhaps be only talk. My
						Lord goes into Yorkshire this summer, so I suppose the Parson must go with him. you will not see any
						advertisement till next winter at soonest. Southwell is going to
					Ireland for two months, much against his will. I have not seen my new Lady E:, but her Husband I
					have; so (I'm afraid) I soon must have that honor. God send Fobus may lie in just about the
					Commencement, or I go out of my wits. that's all .. the news of the surrender of Bellisle is daily
					expected. they have not, nor (they say) possibly can throw in either Men or provisions, so it is look'd upon as ours. I know it will be
					so next week, because I am then to buy into the Stocks.
				</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>God bless you! I am ever <lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
            <dateline>May 26. 1761 </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
