<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (25 February 1768)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 471, vol. iii, 1017-1020
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=471</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 374-376
			</bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 292-293
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:292</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 240, vol. ii, 276-281
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:276</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXIV, vol. iii, 186-190
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:186</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXVI, vol. ii, 496-499
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:496</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLIX, vol. iv, 110-114
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:110</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXVI, vol. ii, 120-124
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:120</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 171-175
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=171</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter XVIII, vol. i, 567-570
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:567</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0527">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1768-02-25"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0527">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Pembroke-college, Feb. 25, 1768. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>To your friendly accusation, I am glad I can plead not guilty with a safe conscience. Dodsley told me in the spring that the plates
					from Mr. Bentley's designs were worn out, and he wanted to have them copied and reduced to a smaller
					scale for a new edition. I dissuaded him from so silly an expense, and desired he would put in no ornaments at all. The <hi rend="italic">Long Story</hi> was to be totally omitted, as its only use (that of explaining the prints) was gone: but to supply the
					place of it in bulk, lest <hi rend="italic">my works</hi> should be mistaken for the works of a flea, or a pismire, I promised to send
					him an equal weight of poetry or prose: so, since my return hither, I put up about two ounces of stuff; viz. The Fatal Sisters, The
					Descent of Odin (of both which you have copies), a bit of something from the Welch, and certain little
					notes, partly from justice (to acknowledge the debt, where I had borrowed any thing), partly from ill temper, just to tell the gentle reader, that Edward I. was not Oliver Cromwell, nor queen Elizabeth the witch of
						Endor. This is literally all; and with all this I shall be but a shrimp of an author. I gave leave
					also to print the same thing at Glasgow; but I doubt my packet has miscarried, for I hear nothing of
					its arrival as yet. To what you say to me so civilly, that I ought to write more, I reply in your own words (like the
						pamphleteer, who is going to confute you out of your own mouth), What has one to do, when <hi rend="italic">turned of fifty,</hi> but really to think of finishing? However, I will be candid (for you seem to be so with me), and
					avow to you, that till fourscore-and-ten, whenever the humour takes me, I will write, because I like it; and because I like myself
					better when I do so. If I do not write much, it is because I cannot. As you have not this last plea, I
					see no reason why you should not continue as long as it is agreeable to yourself, and to all such as have any curiosity of judgment in
					the subjects you choose to treat. By the way let me tell you (while it is fresh) that lord Sandwich, who was lately dining at
					Cambridge, speaking (as I am told) handsomely of your book, said, it was pity you did not know that his cousin Manchester had a genealogy of the kings, which came down no lower than to Richard III. and at the end of it were two
					portraits of Richard and his son, in which that king appeared to be a handsome man. I tell you it as I heard it: perhaps you may think
					it worth enquiring into.
				</p>
				     <p>I have looked into Speed and Leslie. It appears very odd, that Speed in the speech he makes for P.
					Warbeck, addressed to James IV. of Scotland, should three times cite the <hi rend="italic">manuscript proclamation</hi> of Perkin, then
					in the hands of Sir Robert Cotton; and yet when he gives us the proclamation afterwards (on occasion
					of the insurrection in Cornwall) he does not cite any such manuscript. In Casley's Catalogue of the Cotton Library you may see whether this manuscript proclamation still exists or not: if it does, it may be found at the
					Musæum. Leslie will give you no satisfaction at all: though no subject of England, he could not write freely on this matter, as the
					title of Mary his mistress to the crown of England was derived from that of Henry VII. Accordingly, he every where treats Perkin as an
					impostor; yet drops several little expressions inconsistent with that supposition. He has preserved no proclamation: he only puts a
					short speech into Perkin's mouth, the substance of which is taken by Speed, and translated in the end of his, which is a good deal
					longer: the whole matter is treated by Leslie very concisely and superficially. I can easily transcribe it, if you please; but I do not
					see that it could answer any purpose.</p>
				     <p>Mr. Boswell's book I was going to recommend to you, when I received your letter: it has pleased and moved me strangely, all (I mean)
					that relates to Paoli. He is a man born two thousand years after his time! The pamphlet proves what I have always maintained, that any
					fool may write a most valuable book by chance, if he will only tell us what he heard and saw with veracity. Of Mr. Boswell's truth I
					have not the least suspicion, because I am sure he could invent nothing of this kind. The true title
					of this part of his work is, A Dialogue between a Greengoose and a Hero.</p>
				     <p>I had been told of a manuscript in Benet-library: the inscription of it is <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium Fratris Simonis
						Simeonis</hi>
					
					       <hi rend="italic">et Hugonis Illuminatoris,</hi> 1322. Would not one think this should promise something? They were two Franciscan
					friars that came from Ireland, and passed through Wales to London, to Canterbury, to Dover, and so to France in their way to Jerusalem.
					All that relates to our own country has been transcribed for me, and (sorry am I to say) signifies not a halfpenny: only this little
					bit might be inserted in your next edition of the Painters: Ad aliud caput civitatis (Londoniæ) est
					monasterium nigrorum monachorum nomine Westmonasterium, in quo constanter et communiter omnes reges Angliæ sepeliuntur—et eidem
					monasterio quasi immediatè conjungitur illud famosissimum palatium regis, in quo est illa vulgata camera, in cujus parietibus sunt
					omnes historiæ bellicæ totius Bibliæ ineffabiliter depictæ, atque in Gallico completissimè et perfectissimè conscriptæ, in non modicâ
					intuentium admiratione et maximâ regali magnificentiâ.</p>
				     <p>I have had certain observations on your Royal and Noble Authors given me to send you perhaps about three years ago: last week I found
					them in a drawer, and (my conscience being troubled) now enclose them to you. I have even forgot whose they are. </p>
				     <p>I have been also told of a passage in Ph. de Comines, which (if you know) ought not to have been passed over. The book is not at hand
					at present, and I must conclude my letter.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! <lb/> I am ever yours, </salute>
					       <signed>T. GRAY.</signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
