<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (22 January 1758)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 265, vol. ii, 556-558
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=265</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXXII, 135-137
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:135</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section iv, 257-258
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:257</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 200-204
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:200</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXII, vol. ii, 19-22
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:19</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0305">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1758-01-22"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0305">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Sunday – 1758. Janr</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I am almost blind with a great cold, &amp; should not have wrote to you today, if you did not hurry me to send back this
						elegy. my advices are allways at your service to take or to refuse, therefore you should not call
					them <hi rend="italic">severe.</hi> you know I do not love, much less pique myself on criticism, and think even a bad verse as good a
					thing or better, than the best observation, that ever was made upon it. I like greatly what you have now sent me, particularly the
					spirit &amp; sentiment of it. the disposition of the whole too is natural &amp; elegiac. as to the expression I would venture to say
					(did you not forbid me) that it is sometimes too <hi rend="italic">easy.</hi> the last line I protest
					against. (this, you will say, is worse, than blotting out rhymes) the descriptive part is excellent, yet I am sorry for the name of <hi rend="italic">Cutthorpe.</hi>
					 I had rather Vertumnus &amp; Flora did not appear in person. the word <hi rend="italic">lopt</hi>
					sounds like a Farmer, or a Man of taste. <hi rend="italic">a Mountain hoar, the savage</hi> &amp;c: is a very good line, yet I allways
					doubt, if this ungrammatical construction be allowable. in common speech it is usual, but not in writing even prose; &amp; I think,
					Milton (tho' hard-press'd by his short metre in the Penseroso) yet finds a way to bring in his <hi rend="italic">thats,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">whos,</hi> &amp; his <hi rend="italic">whiches. fair unfold The wide-spread</hi> &amp;c: <hi rend="italic">fair</hi> is
					weakly; <hi rend="italic">wide-spread</hi> is contained in <hi rend="italic">unfold.</hi> by <hi rend="italic">amber</hi> mead I
					understand the yellow gleam of a meadow cover'd with marshmarygolds &amp; butterflowers. is not it so? the two first lines (the 2d
					especially) I do not admire. I read <hi rend="italic">Did Fancy</hi> wake not – <hi rend="italic">refuse</hi> one votive strain.
					you will ask me, why? I do not know. as to <hi rend="italic">votive</hi> it is like <hi rend="italic">delegated,</hi> one of the words
					you love. I also read <hi rend="italic">How</hi> well does Mem'ry &amp;c: for the same no reason. <hi rend="italic">Enough, it all was
						his</hi> &amp;c: I like the sense, but it is not sufficiently clear. as to the versification, do not you perceive that you make the
					pause on the fourth syllable in almost every other line?</p>
				     <p>Now I desire, you would neither think me severe, nor at all regard what I say any farther, than it coincides with your own judgement:
					for the Child deserves your partiality, it is a healthy well-made boy with an ingenuous countenance,
					&amp; promises to live long. I would only wash its face, dress it a little, make it walk upright &amp; strong, &amp; keep it from
					learning <hi rend="italic">paw</hi> words.</p>
				     <p>I never saw more than two volumes of Pelloutier, &amp; repent, that I ever read them. he is an idle
					Man of some learning, that would make all the world <hi rend="italic">Celts,</hi> whether they will or no. <hi rend="italic">Locus est
						&amp; pluribus umbris</hi> is a very good Motto; you need look no farther: I can not find the other
					passage, nor look for it with <hi rend="italic">these eyes.</hi>
         </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, dear Mason, I am most sincerely yours</salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>You won't find me a place, like Mr Wood's! </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
