<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mary Antrobus (24 November 1759)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="ROBA">Rosenbach Museum &amp; Library</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 305, vol. ii, 648-649
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=305</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0352">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1759-11-24"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29394522">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0352">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <salute> Dear Mary </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I am not dead, as you probably imagine, but have been employ'd in seeing the gradual approaches of death in poor Lady Cobham, whom I
					went to see at Stoke, &amp; in whose house I have continued at her own desire, after she came to Town for farther advice, till the last
						week. affairs of my own obliged me to come home to Southampton-Row. I have left her growi[ng]
					daily worse &amp; worse, &amp; in a way (I think) ab[solute]ly
					hopeless. what I have been saying is m[erely] as somewhat of an excuse for not having [soo]ner
					answer'd your last letter. your dear A[unt
					 is] upon the point of setting out for Hadham, &amp; only stays till the Lottery has done drawing. I hope you will be very good Neighbours, &amp; pray,
					don't be sparing of your bottled Beer.</p>
				     <p> I am very well satisfied with my new place of abode here. my fatigue of furnishing was soon over,
					for I have no furniture at all but a bed to lie on, half of w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is much at your service. pray come, &amp; we'll
					go every night to the Play, Tuesdays &amp; Saturdays excepted, when there are Operas. the old Chintz-Chairs &amp; Settee cut a figure here, but are mightily at a loss for want of curtains. what must I do? you know, I have but
					one Pair, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> will do to cover a Sofa, or two Great Chairs. now here are three Windows to be provided for. is it
					possible to get a Linnen approaching to the colours &amp; pattern of the Chintz; or will it be absurd to put up some silky thing of a
					plain green suppose, or some uniform colour &amp; a deep fringe, in the same room with the Chairs? do, advise me.</p>
				     <p> I rejoice in the Lye-lye, &amp; snuff up the Idea of it. it is delicious, whenever you please to
					send it: but I insist at the same time in being told exactly, what it stood you in. as to the trouble it has given you, for that I must
					remain your Debtor, &amp; for many other articles. but do, come to see me, <hi>for you are like none of the Family!</hi>
         </p>
				     <p> My Compliments to your Mamma, &amp; [lov]e to our Dolly.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> I am your Friend &amp; Servant<lb/>
					       </salute>
					       <signed> T G: </signed>
					       <dateline>[No]v: 24. 1759. [Sou]thampton-Row.</dateline>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p> [Y]our Friend Graves is married to Mary, &amp; they keep a Shop
						at Stoke in part of Nan's House. I have got a Lad in his room, that can not do any earthly
						thing.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
