<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (8 March 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 268, vol. ii, 565-567
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=268</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxix, section iv, 259-260
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/259</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 204-206
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/NoC_1911/1/204</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXIV, vol. ii, 24-25
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/24</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CI, vol. ii, 30-32
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/2/30</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXX, vol. i, 367-368
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/367</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0310">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1758-03-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Torcy, Marquis de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Swift, Jonathan</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Shenstone, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Miller, Philip</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Home, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dodsley, Robert, 1703-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Akenside, Dr. Mark</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0310">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Cambridge, March 8, 1758. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>It is indeed for want of spirits, as you suspect, that my studies lie among the Cathedrals, and the Tombs, and the Ruins. To think, though to little purpose, has been the chief amusement of my days; and when I would
					not, or cannot think, I dream. At present I find myself able to write a Catalogue, or to read the
					Peerage book, or Miller's Gardening Dictionary, and am thankful that there are such employments and
					such authors in the world. Some people, who hold me cheap for this, are doing perhaps what is not half so well worth while. As to
					posterity, I may ask, (with some body whom I have forgot) what has it ever done to oblige me?</p>
         <p>To make a transition from myself to as poor a subject, the Tragedy of Agis; I cry to think that it
					should be by the Author of Douglas: Why, it is all modern Greek; the story is an antique statue painted white and red, frized, and
					dressed in a negligée made by a Yorkshire mantua-maker. Then here is the Miscellany (Mr Dodsley has
					sent me the whole set gilt and lettered, I thank him). Why, the two last volumes are worse than the four first; particularly Dr
						Akenside is in a deplorable way. What signifies Learning and the Antients, (Mason will say
					triumphantly) why should people read Greek to lose their imagination, their ear, and their mother tongue? But then there is Mr
						Shenstone, who trusts to nature and simple sentiment, why does he do no better? he goes hopping along
					his own gravel-walks, and never deviates from the beaten paths for fear of being lost.</p>
         <p>I have read Dr Swift, and am disappointed. There is nothing of the negotiations that I have not seen
					better in M. de Torcy before. The manner is careless, and has little to distinguish it from common
					writers. I meet with nothing to please me but the spiteful characters of the opposite party and its leaders. I expected much more
					secret history. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
