<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (14 February 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 468, vol. iii, 1006-1009
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=468</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 368-370
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 287-292
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/NoC_1911/1/287</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 238, vol. ii, 264-269
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/264</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXIII, vol. iii, 180-185
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/180</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXV, vol. ii, 492-496
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/492</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLVIII, vol. iv, 104-109
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iv/1/104</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXV, vol. ii, 116-120
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/2/116</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 161-166
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=161</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter XVII, vol. i, 563-567
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/563</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0524">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-02-14"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Algarotti, Francesco, Conte, 1712-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hume, David</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Carte, Thomas</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Algarotti, Francesco, Conte, 1712-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Newmarket</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0524">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Feb. 14, 1768. Pembroke College. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I received the book you were so good to send me, and have read it again (indeed I could hardly be
					said to have read it before) with attention and with pleasure. Your second edition is so rapid in its
					progress, that it will now hardly answer any purpose to tell you either my own objections, or those of other people. Certain it is,
					that you are universally read here; but what <hi rend="italic">we</hi> think, is not so easy to come at. We stay as usual to see the
					success, to learn the judgment of the town, to be directed in our opinions by those of more competent judges. If they like you, we
					shall; if any one of name write against you, we give you up: for we are modest and diffident of ourselves, and not without reason.
					History in particular is not our <hi rend="italic">fort</hi>; for (the truth is) we read only modern books and the pamphlets of the
					day. I have heard it objected, that you raise doubts and difficulties, and do not satisfy them by telling us what was <hi rend="italic">really</hi> the case. I have heard you charged with disrespect to the king of Prussia; and above all
					to king William, and the revolution. These are seriously the most sensible things I have heard said,
					and all that I recollect. If you please to justify yourself, you may.</p>
         <p>My own objections are little more essential: they relate chiefly to inaccuracies of style, which either debase the expression or
					obscure the meaning. I could point out several small particulars of this kind, and will do so, if you think it can serve any purpose
					after publication. When I hear you read, they often escape me, partly because I am attending to the subject, and partly because from
					habit I understand you where a stranger might often be at a loss. </p>
         <p>As to your arguments, most of the principal parts are made out with a clearness and evidence that no one would expect where materials
					are so scarce. Yet I still suspect Richard of the murder of Henry VI. The chronicler of Croyland charges it full on him, though without a name or any mention of circumstances. The interests of Edward were the interests of Richard
					too, though the throne were not then in view; and that Henry still stood in their way, they might well imagine, because, though deposed
					and imprisoned once before, he had regained his liberty, and his crown; and was still adored by the people. I should think, from the
					word <hi rend="italic">tyranni,</hi> the passage was written after Richard had assumed the crown: but, if it was earlier, does not the
					bare imputation imply very early suspicions at least of Richard's bloody nature, especially in the mouth of a person that was no enemy
					to the house of York, nor friend to that of Beaufort? </p>
         <p>That the duchess of Burgundy, to try the temper of the nation, should set up a false pretender to the throne (when she had the true
					duke of York in her hands), and that the queen-mother (knowing her son was alive) should countenance that design, is a piece of policy utterly incomprehensible; being the most likely means to ruin their own scheme, and
					throw a just suspicion of fraud and falsehood on the cause of truth, which Henry could not fail to seize and turn to his own
					advantage.</p>
         <p>Mr. Hume's first query, as far as relates to the queen-mother, will still have some weight. Is it
					probable, she should give her eldest daughter to Henry, and invite him to claim the crown, unless she had been sure that her sons were
					then dead? As to her seeming consent to the match between Elizabeth and Richard, she and her daughters were in his power, which
					appeared now well fixed, his enemies' designs within the kingdom being every where defeated, and Henry unable to raise any considerable
					force abroad. She was timorous and hopeless; or she might dissemble, in order to cover her secret dealings with Richmond: and if this
					were the case, she hazarded little, supposing Richard to dissemble too, and never to have thought seriously of marrying his niece.</p>
         <p>Another unaccountable thing is, that Richard, a prince of the house of York, undoubtedly brave, clear-sighted, artful, attentive to
					business; of boundless generosity, as appears from his grants; just and merciful, as his laws and his pardons seem to testify; having
					subdued the queen and her hated faction, and been called first to the protectorship and then to the crown by the body of the nobility
					and by the parliament; with the common people to friend (as Carte often asserts), and having nothing
					against him but the illegitimate family of his brother Edward, and the attainted house of Clarence (both of them within his
					power);–that such a man should see within a few months Buckingham, his best friend, and almost all the southern and western
					counties on one day in arms against him; that, having seen all these insurrections come to nothing, he should march with a gallant army
					against a handful of needy adventurers, led by a fugitive, who had not the shadow of a title, nor any virtues to recommend him, nor any
					foreign strength to depend on; that he should be betrayed by almost all his troops, and fall a sacrifice;–all this is to me
					utterly improbable, and I do not ever expect to see it accounted for. </p>
         <p>I take this opportunity to tell you, that Algarotti (as I see in the new edition of his works
					printed at Leghorn) being employed to buy pictures for the king of Poland, purchased among others the famous Holbein, that was at Venice. It don't appear that he knew any thing of
					your book: yet he calls it <hi rend="italic">the consul Meyer and his family,</hi>
					 as if it were then known to be so in that city.</p>
         <p>A young man here, who is a diligent reader of books, an antiquary, and a painter, informs me, that
					at the Red-lion inn at Newmarket is a piece of tapestry containing the very design of your marriage of Henry the sixth, only with several more figures in it, both men and women; that he would have bought it of the people, but
					they refused to part with it.</p>
         <p>Mr. Mason, who is here, desires to present his respects to you. He says, that to efface from our annals the history of any tyrant is
					to do an essential injury to mankind: but he forgives it, because you have shown Henry the seventh to be a greater devil than Richard. </p>
         <p>Pray do not be out of humour. When you first commenced an author, you exposed yourself to pit, box and gallery. Any coxcomb in the
					world may come in and hiss, if he pleases; aye, and (what is almost as bad) clap too, and you cannot hinder him. I saw a little squib
					fired at you in a newspaper by some of the <hi rend="italic">house of York,</hi> for speaking lightly of chancellors.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!<lb/> I am ever yours, </salute>
            <signed>T. GRAY.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
