<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (28 May 1759)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="FITZ">Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 294, vol. ii, 622-623
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=294</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XLIX, 195-197
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:195</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXCV, vol. ii, 113-114
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:113</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0339">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1759-05-28"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0339">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Brown, President of Pembroke-Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>29 MA</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>Dear Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> You will receive tomorrow Caractacus piping hot, I hope before any body else has it. observe, it is
					I, that send it, for M: makes no presents to any one whatever, &amp; moreover you are desired to lend it to nobody, that we may sell
					the more of them; for money, not fame, is the declared purpose of all we do. I believe, you will think
					it (as I do) greatly improved: the last Chorus, &amp; the lines that introduce it, are to me one of the best things I ever read, &amp;
					surely superior to any thing he ever wrote. he has had infinite fits of affectation, as the hour approach'd; &amp; is now gone into the
					country for a week, like a new-married Couple.</p>
				     <p>I am glad to find, you are so lapt in Musick at Cambridge, &amp; that Mingotti is to crown the whole. I heard her within this fortnight, &amp; think her voice (wch always had a roughness)
					is considerably harsher, than it was, but yet she is a noble Singer. I shall not partake of these delights, nor I fear be able to see Cambridge for some time yet: but in a week I
					shall know better. Dr Wharton (who desires his love to you) will (I believe) set out for Durham in about three weeks to settle at
						Old-Park: at present his least Girl is ill of the Small-Pox join'd
					with a scarlet Fever, but likely to get over it. yesterday I, &amp; M: dined with Mr Bonfoy: he told me, that the old Lady was eloped from Rippon just at a time, when he seem'd to want her there, &amp; was (I thought) a little ruffled at it. but I (in my
					heart) commended her, &amp; think her very well <hi rend="italic">revenged</hi> upon him. pray, make her my best Compliments. Old
						Turner is very declining, &amp; I was sounded by Dr G: of
						Lincoln
					 about my designs (or so I understood it). I assured him, I should not <hi rend="italic">ask</hi> for
					it, not chusing to be refused. he told me two People had applied already. N:B: (all this is a secret.)
				</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Dear Sr, believe me ever <lb/> Sincerely Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T GRAY </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P:S: The Parcel will come by one of the Flys. there is a Copy for old Pa:, who is outrageous about it. I rejoice in Jack's good fortune.</p>
					       <p>Ld Strathmore is much out of order, but goes abroad. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
