<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Horace Walpole to Thomas Gray (15 February 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New Haven, CT (Beinecke)/Farmington, CT (Lewis Walpole)</settlement>
                  <institution key="YALE">Yale University Library</institution>
                  <repository>The Lewis Walpole Library</repository>
                  <collection>Manuscript Collections</collection>
                  <idno>HW MSS</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Digital facsimile [JPEG] from original letter</title>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 290, vol. ii, 614-616
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=290</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 211, vol. ii, 179-182
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/179</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 355-356
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 103-105
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=103</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0335">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1759-02-15"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Murdin, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hill, Dr. John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Critical Review</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Lincoln</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0335">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Arlington street <lb/>Feb. 15. 1759. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>The inclosed which I have this minute received from Mr Bentley, explains much that I had to say to you – yet I have a question
					or two more.</p>
         <p>Who &amp; what sort of Man is a Mr Sharp of Bennet? I have received a most obliging &amp; genteel
						letter from him, with the very letter of Edw. 6th which you was so good as to send me. I have
					answered his, but shoud like to know a little more about him. Pray thank the Dean of Lincoln too for me; I am much obliged to him for
					his offer, but had rather draw upon his <hi rend="italic">Lincolnship</hi> than his <hi rend="italic">Cambridgehood.</hi>
					 In the library of the former are some original letters of Tiptoft,
					as you will find in my Catalogue. When Dr. Greene is there, I shall be glad if he will let me have them copied.</p>
         <p>I will thank you if you will look in some provincial history of Ireland for Odo (Hugh) Oneil King of Ulster; when did he live? I have got a most curious Seal of his, &amp; know no more of him than of Ouacraw King of
					the Paw-waws.</p>
         <p>I wanted to ask you whether you or anybody that you beleive in, beleive in the Q. of Scots' letter to Q. Elizabeth – If it is
					genuine, I dont wonder she cut her head off – but I think it must be some forgery that was not made use of.</p>
         <p>Now to my distress – you must have seen an Advertisement, perhaps the book itself, the villainous book itself, that has been
					published to defend me against the Critical Review. I have been childishly unhappy about it, &amp; had
					drawn up a protestation or Affidavit of my knowing nothing of it, but my friends woud not let me publish it. I sent to the printer who
					woud not discover the Author – nor coud I guess. They tell me nobody can suspect my being privy to it, but there is an Intimacy
					affected that I think will deceive many – &amp; yet I must be the most arrogant fool living if I coud know &amp; suffer anybody
					to speak of me in that Style – For God's sake do all you can for me, and publish my Abhorrence. Today I am told that it is that
					puppy Dr Hill, who has chosen to make war with the Magazines thro my Sides. I coud pardon him any
					abuse, but I never can forgive this <hi rend="italic">Friendship.</hi>
         </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>adieu!<lb/> Yrs ever </salute>
            <signed>HW.</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
