<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (16 November 1739)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 74, vol. i, 127-129
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=74</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xi, section ii, 65-68
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:65</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 129-131
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:129</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 105, vol. i, 258-261
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:258</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XXVII, vol. i, 43-46
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:43</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XI, vol. ii, 59-61
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:59</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XI, vol. ii, 69-72
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:69</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXIX, vol. i, 60-63
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:60</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XI, vol. i, 191-193
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:191</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0084">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7005688">Turin, Italy</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1739-11-16"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0084">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Turin, Nov. 16, N. S. 1739. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>After eight days journey through Greenland, we arrived at Turin. You approach it by a handsome avenue of nine miles long, and quite
					strait. The entrance is guarded by certain vigilant dragons, called Douaniers, who mumbled us for some time. The city is not large, as
					being a place of strength, and consequently confined within its fortifications; it has many beauties and some faults; among the first
					are streets all laid out by the line, regular uniform buildings, fine walks that surround the whole, and in general a good lively clean
					appearance: But the houses are of brick plaistered, which is apt to want repairing; the windows of oiled paper, which is apt to be
					torn; and every thing very slight, which is apt to tumble down. There is an excellent Opera, but it is only in the Carnival: Balls
					every night, but only in the Carnival: Masquerades, too, but only in the Carnival. This Carnival lasts only from Christmas to Lent; one
					half of the remaining part of the year is passed in remembering the last, the other in expecting the future Carnival. We cannot well
					subsist upon such slender diet, no more than upon an execrable Italian Comedy, and a Puppet-Show, called Rappresentazione d'un' anima
					dannata, which, I think, are all the present diversions of the place; except the Marquise de Cavaillac's Conversazione, where one goes
					to see people play at Ombre and Taroc, a game with 72 cards all painted with suns, and moons, and
					devils and monks. Mr. Walpole has been at court; the family are at present at a country palace, called La Venerie. The palace here in
					town is the very quintessence of gilding and looking-glass; inlaid floors, carved pannels, and painting, wherever they could stick a
					brush. I own I have not, as yet, any where met with those grand and simple works of Art, that are to amaze one, and whose sight one is
					to be the better for: But those of Nature have astonished me beyond expression. In our little journey up to the Grande
						Chartreuse, I do not remember to have gone ten paces without an exclamation, that there was no
					restraining: Not a precipice, not a torrent, not a cliff, but is pregnant with religion and poetry. There are certain scenes that would
					awe an atheist into belief, without the help of other argument. One need not have a very fantastic imagination to see spirits there at
					noon-day: You have Death perpetually before your eyes, only so far removed, as to compose the mind without frighting it. I am well
					persuaded St. Bruno was a man of no common genius, to choose such a situation for his retirement; and perhaps should have been a
					disciple of his, had I been born in his time. You may believe Abelard and Heloïse were not forgot upon this occasion: If I do not
					mistake, I saw you too every now and then at a distance among the trees; il me semble, que j'ai vu ce chien de visage là quelque part.
					You seemed to call to me from the other side of the precipice, but the noise of the river below was so great, that I really could not
					distinguish what you said; it seemed to have a cadence like verse. In your next you will be so good to let me know what it was. The
					week we have since passed among the Alps, has not equalled the single day upon that mountain, because the winter was rather too far
					advanced, and the weather a little foggy. However, it did not want its beauties; the savage rudeness of the view is inconceivable
					without seeing it: I reckoned in one day, thirteen cascades, the least of which was, I dare say, one hundred feet in height. I had Livy
					in the chaise with me, and beheld his 'Nives cœlo propè immistæ, tecta informia imposita rupibus, pecora jumentaque torrida frigore,
					homines intonsi &amp; inculti, animalia inanimaque omnia rigentia gelu; omnia confragosa, præruptaque'. The creatures that inhabit them are, in all respects, below humanity; and most of them, especially women, have the tumidum
						guttur, which they call goscia. Mont Cenis, I confess, carries the permission mountains have of being
						frightful rather too far; and its horrors were accompanied with too much danger to give one time to
					reflect upon their beauties. There is a family of the Alpine monsters I have mentioned, upon its very top, that in the middle of winter
					calmly lay in their stock of provisions and firing, and so are buried in their hut for a month or two under the snow. When we were down
					it, and got a little way into Piedmont, we began to find 'Apricos quosdam colles, rivosque prope sylvas, &amp; jam humano cultu
					digniora loca'. I read Silius Italicus too, for the first time; and wished for you according to
					custom. We set out for Genoa in two days time.
				</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
