<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (June 1738)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 53, vol. i, 85-87
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=53</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xiv, section i, 30-33
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:30</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 79, vol. i, 184-187
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:184</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XI, vol. i, 12-13
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:12</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section I, letter XIV, vol. ii, 25-26
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:25</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section I, letter XIV, vol. ii, 29
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:29</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XIV, vol. i, 27-29
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:27</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section I, letter XIV, vol. i, 159-161
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:159</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0057">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1738-06"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="poem">[Alcaic Fragment]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Ad C: Favonium Aristium</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0057">
      <body>
         <q>
            <p>Barbaras ædes aditure mecum,<lb/> Quas Eris semper fovet inquieta, <lb/> Lis ubi latè sonat, et
						togatum <lb/> Æstuat agmen! <lb/> Dulcius quanto, patulis sub ulmi <lb/> Hospitæ ramis temerè jacentem <lb/> Sic libris horas,
						tenuiqb inertes<lb/> Fallere Musâ? <lb/> Sæpe enim curis vagor expeditâ <lb/> Mente; dum, blandam meditans Camænam, <lb/> Vix malo
						rori, meminive seræ <lb/> Cedere nocti; <lb/> Et, pedes quò me rapiunt, in omni <lb/> Colle Parnassum videor videre <lb/> Fertilem
						sylvæ, gelidamqb in omni<lb/> Fonte Aganippen. <lb/> Risit &amp; Ver me, facilesqb Nymphæ<lb/> Nare captantem, nec ineleganti,
						<lb/> Manè quicquid de violis eundo <lb/> Surripit aura: <lb/> Me reclinatum teneram per herbam; <lb/> Quà leves cursus aqua
						cunque ducit, <lb/> Et moras dulci strepitu lapillo <lb/> Nectit in omni. <lb/> Hæ novo nostrum ferè pectus anno <lb/> Simplices
						curæ tenuere, cœlum <lb/> Quamdiú sudum explicuit Favonî <lb/> Purior hora: <lb/> Otia et campos nec adhuc relinquo, <lb/> Nec
						magis Phœbo Clytie fidelis; <lb/> (Ingruant venti licet, et senescat <lb/> Mollior æstas.) <lb/> Namque, seu, lætos hominum labores
						<lb/> Prataqb &amp; montes recreante curru,<lb/> Purpurâ tractus oriens Eoos <lb/> Vestit, et auro; <lb/> Sedulus servo, veneratus
						orbem <lb/> Prodigum splendoris: amœniori <lb/> Sive dilectam meditatur igne <lb/> Pingere Calpen; <lb/> Usque dum, fulgore magìs
						magìs jam <lb/> Languido circum, variata nubes <lb/> Labitur furtim, viridisqb in umbras<lb/> Scena recessit. <lb/> O ego felix,
						vice si (nec unquam <lb/> Surgerem rursus) simili cadentem <lb/> Parca me lenis sineret quieto <lb/> Fallere letho! <lb/> Multà
						flagranti radiisqb cincto<lb/> Integris ah! quam nihil inviderem, <lb/> Cum Dei ardentes medius quadrigas <lb/> Sentit Olympus?
					</p>
         </q>
         <p>Ohe! amicule noster, et unde, sodes, tu <hi rend="italic">μουσοπάτακτος</hi> adeo repente evasisti?
					jam te rogitaturum credo. Nescio hercle, sic plané habet. Quicquid enim nugarum <hi rend="italic">ἐπὶ</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">σχολῆς</hi> inter ambulandum in palimpsesto scriptitavi, hisce te maxumè impertiri visum est, quippe quem probare,
					quod meum est, aut certè ignoscere solitum probé novi: bonâ tuâ veniâ sit si fortè videar in fine subtristior; nam risui jamdudum
					salutem dixi; etiam paulè mœstitiæ studiosiorem factum scias, promptumque, <hi rend="italic">Καινοῖς</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">παλαιὰ</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">δακρύοις</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">στένειν</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">κακά</hi>.
				</p>
         <q>
            <p>O lachrymarum fons, tenero sacros <lb/> Ducentium ortus ex animo; quater <lb/> Felix! in imo qui scatentem <lb/> Pectore te, pia
						Nympha, sensit. </p>
         </q>
         <closer>
            <salute>Sed de me satis. Cura ut valeas. </salute>
            <dateline>Jun. 1738. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
