<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (1  or 8 October 1764)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Add. MSS 19918, f. 17</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">226 mm x 188 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 392, vol. ii, 843-844
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=392</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXXXVI, 328-330
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:328</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLX, vol. iii, 40-42
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:40</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0445">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011385">Southampton, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" notBefore="1764-10-01"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">How, William Taylor, d. 1777</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Talbot, William, d. 1811</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Winchester</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Southampton</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">St. Cross Hospital</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">New Forest</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Netley Abbey</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Isle of Wight</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Calshot Castle</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0445">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Southampton. at Mr Vining's, Plumber, in High-Street â&#x80;&#x94; â&#x80;&#x94; Monday</dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I received your letter, before I left London, &amp; sit down to write to you after the finest walk in the finest day, that ever
					shone, to Netley-Abbey, my old friend, with whom I long'd to renew my acquaintance. my Ferryman (for
					one passes over a little arm of the sea about 1/2 a mile) assured me, he would not go near it in the night-time for all the world, tho'
					he knew much money had been found there. the sun was <hi rend="italic">all too glaring &amp; too full of gauds</hi>
					 for such a scene, wch ought to be visited only in the dusk of the evening. it stands in a little
					quiet valley, wch gradually rises behind the ruin into a half-circle crown'd with thick wood. before it on a descent is a thicket of
					oaks, that serves to veil it from the broad day &amp; from profane eyes, only leaving a peep on both sides, where the sea appears
					glittering thro' the shade, &amp; vessels with their white sails, that glide across &amp; are lost again. concealed behind the thicket
					stands a little Castle (also in ruins) immediately on the shore, that commands a view over an expanse of sea clear &amp; smooth as
					glass (when I saw it), with Southampton &amp; several villages 3 miles off to the right, Calshot-Castle at 7 miles distance, &amp; the high lands of the Isle of Wight to the left, &amp; in front the deep shades of the New-Forest
					distinctly seen, because the water is no more than three miles over. the Abbey was never very large. the shell of its church is almost
					entire, but the pillars of the iles are gone, &amp; the roof has tumbled in, yet some little of it is left in the transept, where the
					ivy has forced its way thro', &amp; hangs flaunting down among the fretted ornaments &amp; escutcheons of the Benefactors. much of the
					lodgings &amp; offices are also standing, but all is overgrown with trees &amp; bushes, &amp; mantled here &amp; there with ivy, that
					mounts over the battlements.</p>
         <p>In my way I saw Winchester-Cathedral again with pleasure, and sup'd with Dr Balguy, who, I
					perceive, means to govern the Chapter. they give 200Â£ a year to the Poor of the City: his present scheme is to take away this, for it
					is only an encouragement to laziness. but what do they mean to do with it? that indeed I omitted to enquire, because I thought, I knew.
					I saw <hi rend="italic">St Cross</hi> too, the almshouse of <hi rend="italic">noble Poverty</hi> (so it was call'd), founded by Henry
					de Blois, &amp; Cardinal Beaufort. it maintains 9 decay'd <hi rend="italic">Footmen,</hi> &amp; a Master (Chancellor Hoadley) who has 800Â£ a year out of it.</p>
         <p>This place is still full of <hi rend="italic">Bathers.</hi> I know not a Soul, nor have once been at the rooms. the walks all round
					it are delicious, &amp; so is the weather. lodgings very dear &amp; fish very cheap. here is no Coffeehouse, no Bookseller, no
					Pastry-Cook: but here is the Duke of Chandos. I defer my politicks. My service to Mr Talbot, Gould, &amp;c., &amp; to Mr Howe, if
					with you.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu.</salute>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
