<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (<hi rend="it">before</hi> 17 February 1763)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Add. MSS 26889, ff. 23-24</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>1 page
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">226 mm x 186 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 367, vol. ii, 797-798
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=367</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xlv, section iv, 300-301
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:300</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 257-258
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:257</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXLIX, vol. iii, 8-9
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:8</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CVI, vol. ii, 410-411
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:410</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXVII, vol. iv, 6-7
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:6</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXVII, vol. ii, 73-74
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:73</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XLV, vol. i, 402-403
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:402</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0420">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" notAfter="1763-02-17"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0420">
      <body>
         <p>You will make my best acknowledgements to Mr Howe, who not content to rank me in the number of his
					Friends is so polite as to make excuses for having done me that honour.</p>
         <p>I was not born so <hi rend="italic">far from the Sun</hi>
					 as to be ignorant of Count Algarotti's name &amp; reputation; nor am I so far advanced in years or
					in philosophy, as not to feel the warmth of his approbation. the odes in question, as their motto shews, were meant to be <hi rend="italic">vocal to the Intelligent alone.</hi>
					 how few <hi rend="italic">they</hi> were in my own country, Mr Howe can testify; &amp; yet my
					ambition was terminated by that small circle. I have good reason to be proud, if my voice has reach'd the ear &amp; apprehension of a
					Stranger distinguish'd as one of the best Judges in Europe.</p>
         <p>I am equally pleased with the just applause he bestows on Mr Mason, &amp; particularly on the Caractacus, wch is the work of a Man:
					whereas the Elfrida is only that of a Boy, a promising boy indeed, &amp; of no common Genius: yet this is the popular performance with
					us, &amp; the other little known in comparison. </p>
         <p>Neither Count Algarotti, nor Mr Howe (I believe) have heard of <hi rend="italic">Ossian, the Son of Fingal.</hi>
					 if Mr H: were not upon the wing, &amp; on his way homewards, I would send it to him in Italy. he
					would there see, that Imagination dwelt many hundred years agoe in all her pomp on the cold and barren mountains of Scotland. the truth
					(I believe) is that without any respect of climates she reigns in all nascent societies of Men, where the necessities of life force
					every one to think &amp; act much for himself ..</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!</salute>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
