<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (12 November 1756)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 86-87</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">201 mm x 161 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 229, vol. ii, 485-486
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=229</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXXV, vol. i, 310-311
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:310</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LV, vol. ii, 278-279
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:278</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXIII, vol. iii, 156-157
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:156</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0260">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1756-11-12"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0260">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton M:D: in</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>King's Arms Yard Coleman-Street</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>13 NO</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Nov: 12. 1756. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I grow impatient to be in Town, &amp; hope for the pleasure of seeing you on Tuesday next. I must
					confess, the present revolution of affairs, wch are settling so slowly, is some spur to my curiosity,
					tho' my own interests have no more concern in it, than those of any Cottager in the nation. I flatter myself, that necessity will at
					last throw the management of affairs into more capable, if not more honest hands, than usual. my Gazette says, that Mr. P: will be Sec: of State, &amp; has accepted it (tho' ill of the Gout in the
					Country) that the D: of Devonshire has consented (wch was one of the conditions of acceptance) to be
					at the head of the Treasury. Ld Temple of the Admiralty. G: Grenville, Paymaster. Mr Legge Chanc:r of the Exchequer. Sr G: Lee Sec: at
					War. Mr. F: nothing. how far all this is fact, you know by this time. I do not forget your letter,
					when I say this, &amp; to whom it was wrote; but I much doubt, whether you would have received more benefit from his good-offices,
					while he continued in, than now he is in effect out. I am concerned too for another person, who surely can never continue, where he is (if he should, it is a wonderful proof of the force of
					insignificancy) &amp; if he does not, a good Friend of ours must feel it a little in a part very
					tender to most people, his hopes; but he very wisely has been arming it for some time, I believe, with a reasonable insensibility,
					&amp; taking, by way of precaution a dose of my sovereign anodyne Fastidium.</p>
				     <p>Don't fancy to yourself, that I have been doing any thing here. I am as stupid as a Post, &amp; have not added a syllable, but in plain prose am still</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Ever Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
