<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (8 August 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 484, vol. iii, 1043-1044
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=484</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXXII, 420-422
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:420</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXXIV, vol. iii, 206-207
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:206</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0541">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Hornby Castle, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-08-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Lort, Michael, 1725-1790</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Palgrave, William, 1735-1799</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Old Park</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0541">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Thomas Gray Esqr at Mr Roberts Hozier in Jermyn Street London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CATTERICK 12 AV</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Hornby Castle Augst 8th 1768</dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr Professor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I will not congratulate you, for I would not have you think I am glad. &amp; I take for granted you dont think I am, or at least
					would not have me so to be, else you would have given me a line –but no matter. I went the
					other day to Old Park, &amp; read what you had written to the Dr–and he was not so glad neither
					as to hinder him from making Water wch he did all the time I was with him, &amp; continues still to do
					&amp; thinks he shall not give over of some months. Dont be afraid the discharge does not come from his vesicatory but his pecuniary
					Ducts. &amp; I as Physician &amp; Summers as Apothecary hold it to be a most salutary Diabetis.</p>
         <p>I have my good luck too I can tell you, for when I was at Hull I met with a Roman Ossuary of exquisite Sculpture. How I came by it,
					no matter! tis enough that I am possest of it. I send you the inscription wch your Brother Lort or
						Halifax may perhaps help me to construe, for as to Yourself I take for granted that all Your skill in
					the learned Languages transpird in the Kiss wch you gave his Majestys little finger, &amp; you rose up a mere modern Schollar, with
					nothing left but a little Linæan jargon. Be this as it may heres the Inscription literatim. <q rendition="#center">
               <p>PONPONIA PRIMI <lb/> GENIAE <lb/> T PONPONIO FELICI <lb/> P. ET P. PA.</p>
            </q> The first three lines I read Pomponia primigeniae Tito Pomponio Felici. but as to the rest it is all Hebrew Greek to me. Seriously
					if you can make it out for me I shall be obligd to you.</p>
         <p>I go to York on Thursday but I mean to call in my way on Mr Wedell &amp; Proud Palgrave on Wednesday. Remember me kindly to your Brother Mr Professor Shepherd
					&amp; the successor of Mr Professor Mickleborough &amp; beleive me to be Dear Mr Professor</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>yours most truly &amp; sincerely </salute>
            <signed>W MASON </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
