<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Edward Bedingfield (31 October 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>San Marino, CA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HULI">The Huntington</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts</repository>
		                <collection>Huntington Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>HM 21916</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 256, vol. ii, 538-540
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=256</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0291">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-10-31"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Bedingfield, Edward, b. 1730</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0291">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Stoke. Oct: 31. 1757. </dateline>
					       <salute> Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> For the opinion of the South I refer you to the lordly conversation you were present at in the Bookseller's shop during York
						races. we are almost all Lords, &amp; the commonest events of English History are to us impenetrable
					&amp; inexplicable: however here were some different judgements. you saw the verses printed in the London Chronicle, &amp; supposed to
					be M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Garrick's; and (to make you friends with D<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					Warburton) I must tell you, he says, the World never judged so justly of any thing new, as of these Odes, for other compositions they
					have affected to like &amp; dislike, but these they own they do not understand; &amp; he heartily believes them: yet he does not doubt
					but they understand them full as well as Milton or Shakespeare, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> Fashion forces them to admire, this is what
					my Correspondents tell me, &amp; if they have put in a little more flattery, than belongs to the Doctor, I know you will excuse me for
					biting at it so readily. Dodsley, I find, has been as negligent with regard to several other Persons, as to you, but it is in vain to
					scold at a Bookseller, when your writings lie upon his hands by hundreds, as (I suppose) mine do. you see what my <hi>celebrity</hi>
					(that you promised me) is come to. pray, don't tell the People of Durham, to whom I am infinitely obliged, tho' they did not at all
					like me. there are some objections to the tradition you flatter me with: the Churchyard was publish'd
					Feb: 1751, &amp; I did not go thither till Aug: 1753. I met with no weather, that would tempt me to
					sit under a tree; 3<hi rend="super">dly</hi> &amp; lastly, they have no trees to sit under.</p>
				     <p> I have got the old Ballad, on w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> Douglas is founded. it is in my eyes a
					miracle not only of ancient simplicity, but of ancient art. the great rules of Aristotle &amp; Horace are observed in it by a Writer,
					who perhaps had never heard their names. what I say, is a great compliment to the Genius of the Scotch, but a still greater to Horace
					&amp; Aristotle. as to the Play, the single Scene of Matilda's interview with the old Peasant was the thing, that inchanted me; if all
					the rest had been wrote by Aaron Hill, I should have been still inchanted. pray keep
						your—you know what—from interfering with your judgement in poetry. nothing belongs to
					this, but what Men say, &amp; what they do in different situations of life; not what they <hi>ought</hi> to say or do. I wish to God,
					that no good Man, or even no <hi>good Christian</hi>, had ever known what despair was: but I fear they have too often been hurried to
					their own destruction. Providence may have interposed to prevent it, but whether it does <hi>always</hi> interpose, only that
					Providence can tell. however this is <hi>gratis dictum</hi>, for Matilda is distracted, before she executes her purpose. another
					quarrel I have with you about Q: Elizabeth. I know she was a <hi>Bitch</hi>; but it is clear, on what your animosity is founded. indeed
					it runs in the blood. I suppose your ancestor S<hi rend="super">r</hi> H: B: many a time repented,
					that when he was her Keeper, he had not put a little in her cup of what she herself wish'd S<hi rend="super">r</hi> Amias Paulet would put into that of Mary, Q: of Scots. before you offer to condemn her persecutions, let me know, what
					you think of those of her Sister Mary. believe me this topick of hanging &amp; burning is a thing, that no good Catholick ought ever to
					open his mouth about, till the measure on our Side is as full, as it is on yours. if you tell your Confessor this, he will enjoin you
					never to write to me more.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> Adieu, Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>, I am<lb/> Your Friend &amp; humble Servant </salute>
					       <signed> TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p> My best respects to the Ladies. I shall return to Cambridge in a fortnight or less.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
