<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (7 October 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 96-97</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">201 mm x 158 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 251, vol. ii, 531-533
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=251</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section iv, 250, note
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:250</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 196
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:196</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLI, vol. i, 365-368
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:365</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXVI, vol. ii, 296-297
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:296</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXIV, vol. iii, 177-179
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:177</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0286">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-10-07"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0286">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton, M:D:</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>in [...]ngs-Arms Yard, Coleman Street</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>8 OC</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Oct: 7. 1757. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Doctr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I heartily rejoice with you, that your little family are out of danger, &amp; all apprehensions of that kind over with them for
						life. yet I have heard, you were ill yourself, &amp; kept your bed: as this was (I imagine) only by
					way of regimen, &amp; not from necessity; I hope soon to be told, you have no farther occasion for it. yet take care of yourself, for
					there is a bad fever now very frequent. it is among the boys at Eton, &amp; (I am told), is much spread about London too. my notion is,
					that your violent quick pulse, &amp; soapy diet would not suit well with feverish disorders. tho' our party at Slough turn'd out so
					ill, I could not help being sorry, that you were not with us.</p>
				     <p>Have you read Mr. Hurd's (printed) Letter to Mason on the Marks of Imitation? you do not tell me
					your opinion of it. you bid me send you criticisms on myself, &amp; even <hi rend="italic">compliments.</hi> did I tell you, what the
						Speaker says? the 2d Ode, he says, is a good pretty tale, but nothing to the <hi rend="italic">Churchyard.</hi> Mr. Bedingfield in a golden shower of panegyrick writes me word, that at Yorkraces he overheard three People, whom
					by their dress &amp; manner he takes for Lords, say, that I was impenetrable &amp; inexplicable, and they wish'd, I had told them in
					prose, what I meant in verse, &amp; then they bought me (wch was what most displeased him) &amp; put me in their pocket. Dr Warburton is come to Town, &amp; likes them extremely. he says the World
					never pass'd so just an opinion upon any thing as upon them: for that in other things they have affected to like or dislike, whereas
					here they own, they do not understand, wch he looks upon to be very true; but yet thinks, they understand them as well as they do
					Milton or Shakespear, whom they are obliged by fashion to admire. Mr G:k's compliment you have seen; I
					am told it was printed in the Chronicle of last Saturday. the Review I have read, &amp; admire it,
					particularly that observation, that the <hi rend="italic">Bard</hi> is taken from <hi rend="italic">Pastor, cum traheret,</hi>
					 &amp; the advice to be more an <hi rend="italic">original,</hi> &amp; in order to be so, the way is
					(he says) to cultivate the native flowers of the soil, &amp; not introduce the exoticks of another climate.
				</p>
				     <p>I am greatly pleased with M:n s Caractacus in its present state. the contrivance &amp; arrangement of events, the manners of the
					country, the characters &amp; passions, strike me wonderfully. the difficult part is now got over, nothing remains but to polish, &amp;
					retouch a little: yet only the beginning of the first Chorus is done of the lyric part. have you seen it? </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! dear Sr, &amp; believe me ever <lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I shall be in Town probably sooner than you come to stay there. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
