<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (8 February 1747)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
		                <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 131, vol. i, 264-268
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=131</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 162, vol. ii, 69-75
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:69</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iv, section iv, 182-185
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:182</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 144-146
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:144</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXXVI, vol. i, 163-165
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:163</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XI, vol. ii, 172-175
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:172</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XVI, vol. iii, 32-35
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:32</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXIV, vol. i, 141-143
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:141</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 13-18
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=13</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter IV, vol. i, 296-298
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:296</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0149">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1747-02-08"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
			         <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0149">
			   <body>
				
				     <p>I had been absent from this Place a few Days, &amp; at my Return found Cibber's Book upon my Table:
					I return you my Thanks for it, &amp; have already run over a considerable Part, for who could resist Mrs Lætitia Pilkington's Recommendation? (by the Way is there any such Gentlewoman, or has somebody put on the Style of a
					scribbleing Woman's Panegyric to deceive &amp; laugh at Colley?) he seems to me full as pert &amp; as dull as usual. there are whole
					Pages of Common-Place Stuff, that for Stupidity might have been wrote by Dr Waterland or any other
					grave Divine, did not the flirting saucy Phrase give them at a Distance an Air of Youth &amp; Gayety. it is very true, he is often in
					the right with regard to Tully's Weaknesses; but was there any one that did not see them? those, I imagine, that would find a Man after
					God's own Heart, are no more likely to trust the Doctor's Recommendation, than the Player's. &amp; as to Reason &amp; Truth: would they
					know their own Faces, do you think? if they look'd in the Glass, &amp; saw themselves so bedizen'd in tatter'd Fringe &amp; tarnish'd
					Lace, in French Jewels, &amp; dirty Furbelows, the frippery of a Stroller's Wardrobe? </p>
				     <p>Litterature (to take it in its most comprehensive Sense, &amp; include every Thing, that requires Invention, or Judgement, or barely
					Application &amp; Industry) seems indeed drawing apace to its Dissolution; &amp; remarkably since the Beginning of the War. I should be
					glad to know why, if any one will tell me. for I believe there may be natural Reasons discoverable enough without haveing Recourse to
					St John, or St Alexander's Revelations. I remember to have read Mr Spence's pretty Book, tho' (as he then had not been at Rome for the last Time) it must have increased greatly since that in Bulk.
					if you ask me what I read; I protest I don't remember one Syllable; but only in general, that they were the best-bred Sort of Men in
					the World, just the Kind of <hi rend="italic">Frinds</hi> one would wish to meet in a fine Summer's Evening, if one wish'd to meet any
					at all. the Heads &amp; Tails of the Dialogues, publish'd separate in 16mo, would make the sweetest Reading in Natiur for young
					Gentlemen of Family &amp; Fortune, that are learning to dance: I am told, he has put his little Picture before it. I rejoyce to hear, there is such a Crowd of dramatical Performances comeing upon the Stage.
						Agripp:na can stay very well, she thanks you; &amp; be damn'd at Leisure: I hope in God you have not
					mention'd, or shew'd to any Body that Scene (for trusting in it's Badness, I forgot to caution you concerning it) but I heard the other
					Day, that I was writeing a Play, &amp; was told the Name of it, wch no body here could know, I'm sure. the Employment you propose to
					me, much better suits my Inclination. but I much fear our Joynt-Stock would hardly compose a small Volume: what I have, is less considerable than you would imagine; &amp; of that little we should not be willing to
					publish all. there is an Epistle, ad Amicos (that is, to us all at Cambridge) in English, of above
					fourscore Lines: the Thoughts are taken from Tibullus, &amp; from a Letter of Mr Pope's in Prose. it begins</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>While You, where Camus rolls his sedgy Tide &amp;c: </p>
				     </q>
				     <p>2. An Imitation of Horace, Trojani belli scriptorem &amp;c: about 120 Lines, wrote to me.
					begins</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>While haply You (or haply not at all) <lb/> Hear the grave Pleadings in the Lawyer's Hall &amp;c: </p>
				     </q>
				     <p>3. A Translation from Propertius. L: 3. El. 15 ... 50 Lines. begins .. (sent to me at Rheims)</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>Now prostrate, Bacchus, at thy Shrine I bend &amp;c: </p>
				     </q>
				     <p>4. An Elegy, Latin. 34 Lines. begins, Quod mihi tam gratæ &amp;c:</p>
				     <p>5. Another, sent to Florence. 36 Lines.–Ergo desidiæ videor &amp;c:</p>
				     <p>6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. Translation from Posidippus, an Epigram .. Some Lines; on the hard
						Winter: long Verse .. on himself, a little before his Death. long
					Verse. 2 Imitations of Catullus' Basia. English. a little Ode of 5 Stanza's, to the Spring.
				</p>
				     <p>This is all I can any where find. You, I imagine, may have a good deal more. I should not care, how
					unwise the ordinary Sort of Readers might think my Affection for him provided those few, that ever loved any Body, or judged of any
					thing rightly, might from such little Remains be moved to consider, what he would have been; &amp; to wish, that Heaven had granted him
					a longer Life, &amp; a Mind more at Ease. I can't help fancying, that if you could find out Mrs West, &amp; ask her for his Papers of
					that kind (Ashton might do it in your Name) she would be ready enough to part with them, &amp; we might find something more: at least
					it would be worth while to try; for she had 'em in a great Box altogether, I well know. </p>
				     <p>I send you a few Lines, tho' Latin (wch you don't like) for the sake of the Subject. it makes Part of a large Design, &amp; is the Beginning of the fourth Book, wch was intended to treat of the Passions. excuse the 3 first
					Verses: you know Vanity (with the Romans) is a poetical License.</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>Hactenus haud segnis Naturæ arcana retexi <lb/> Musarum interpres, primusqb Britanna per arva<lb/> Romano liquidum deduxi flumine
						rivum. <lb/> Cum Tu opere in medio, spes tanti &amp; causa laboris, <lb/> Linquis, &amp; æternam fati te condis in umbram! <lb/>
						Vidi egomet duro graviter concussa dolore <lb/> Pectora, in alterius non unquám lenta dolorem; <lb/> Et languere oculos vidi &amp;
						pallescere amantem <lb/> Vultum, quo nunquam Pietas nisi rara, Fidesqb <lb/> Altus amor Veri, &amp; purum spirabat Honestum. <lb/>
						Visa tamen tardi demúm inclementia morbi <lb/> Cessare est, reducemqb iterúm roseo ore Salutem<lb/> Speravi, atqb uná tecum, dilecte
						Favonî,<lb/> Credulus heu longos, ut quondam, fallere Soles. <lb/> Heu spes nequicquam dulces, atqb irrita vota,<lb/> Heu mæstos
						Soles, sine te quos ducere flendo <lb/> Per desideria, &amp; questus jam cogor inanes! <lb/> At tu, sancta anima, &amp; nostri non
						indiga luctûs <lb/> Stellanti templo, sinceriqb ætheris igne<lb/> Unde orta es, fruere. atqb oh si secura, nec ultrá<lb/> Mortalis,
						notos olím miserata labores <lb/> Respectes, tenuesqb vacet cognoscere curas:<lb/> Humanam si forté altâ de sede procellam <lb/>
						Contemplere, metus, stimulosqb cupidinis acres,<lb/> Gaudiaqb &amp; gemitus, parvoqb in corde tumultum<lb/> Irarum ingentem, &amp;
						sævos sub pectore fluctus: <lb/> Respice &amp; has lachrymas, memori quas ictus amore <lb/> Fundo; quod possum, proptér lugere
						sepulchrum <lb/> Dum juvat, &amp; mutæ vana hæc jactare favillæ. </p>
				     </q>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P: S: My Love to the Chutheds. pray tell 'em I am learning Whisk, &amp; have sent one of my old Gowns to be made up into full-bottom'd Hoods ... Compliments to Mrs Tr–cy ... </p>
				     </postscript>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Sr, I am<lb/> Yours ever</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
					       <dateline>Cambr: Sunday–</dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
