<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (8 April 1751)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Dorset</settlement>
		                <institution key="KILA">Kingston Lacy</institution>
		                <collection>Autograph collection</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>Roberts, William: "A Letter from Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole". <title>Notes &amp; Queries</title> 47(2) (June 2000), 198-201
			</bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0646">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1751-04-08"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0646">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Hon. Horace Walpole Esq.</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>in Arlington Street,</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>9 Ap</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <dateline>Monday — Cambridge</dateline>
					       <salute>
						    My Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>         From the Time I saw your Letter, I had little Reason to entertain any Hopes of poor M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Whithed's Life, yet have not been at all less struck with the News of his Death. His youth, his fortune, &amp; his
					Expectations, must make it a Subject of Compassion, even to Strangers: his Temper, his many good Qualities, &amp; that Kindness I have
					constantly received from him, will make his Loss particularly sensible to me, who have (God knows) so few Friends to throw away, but I
					own, what most nearly interests me in it, is the Concern of M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Chute, whose Surprize must have been equal to his
					Sorrow, &amp; who perhaps had not Time or Resolution to see a Face he had been so long accustom'd to, till it was hid from him for
					ever. I can not think of troubling him with so useless a Thing as a Letter at such a Time, but must beg of you, if you either see, or
					have occasion to write to him, just to say, how much I feel for him &amp; how eagerly I wish him that Happiness, &amp; Ease of Mind,
						w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> Time only can give him: for his own Reflexion &amp; Good Sense will, I am afraid, but add to his
					Sensibility. You will much oblige me, when you can give me any Account of him, or of any Thing that concerns him, for you see I have no
					body else to apply to; &amp; tho' the Loss you have had in your own Family (w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> I am heartily sorry for) makes
					this an unreasonable Request, yet (I trust) you will find a quarter of an hour to satisfy my Inquietude.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> Adieu, Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>, I am <lb/>Ever Yours
					</salute>
					       <signed>
						T. Gray.
					</signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
