<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Ashton (21 April 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New Haven, CT (Beinecke)/Farmington, CT (Lewis Walpole)</settlement>
                  <institution key="YALE">Yale University Library</institution>
                  <repository>The Lewis Walpole Library</repository>
                  <collection>Manuscript Collections</collection>
                  <idno>Misc. MSS</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a MS transcript is at the British Library, Add. MSS 32562, ff. 153-156</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 61, vol. i, 104-106
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=61</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 89, vol. i, 211-213
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:211</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section I, letter no. 2, 39-41
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:39</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XVI, vol. i, 23-25
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:23</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0068">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008038">Paris, France</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-04-21"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227197">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Conway, Henry Seymour, 1721-1795</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Seine, River</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Paris</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0068">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Ashton,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You and West have made us happy to night in a heap of letters, &amp; we are resolvd to repay you tenfold. Our English perhaps may not
					be the best in the World, but we have the Comfort to know that it is at least as good as our French. So to begin. Paris is a huge round
					City, divided by the Seine, a very near relation (if we may judge from the resemblance) of your old acquaintance, that ancient river,
					the river Cam. Along it on either side runs a key of perhaps as handsome buildings, as any in the World. the view down which on either
					hand from the Pont Neuf is the charming'st Sight imaginable. There are infinite Swarms of inhabitants &amp; more Coaches than Men. The
					Women in general dressd in Sacs, flat Hoops of 5 yards wide nosegays of artificial flowers, on one shoulder, and faces dyed in Scarlet
					up to the Eyes. The Men in bags, roll-upps, Muffs and
						Solitaires. our Mornings have been mostly taken up in Seeing Sights: few Hotels or Churches have
					escapd us, where there is anything remarkable as to building, Pictures or Statues.</p>
         <p>Mr Conway is as usual, the Companion of our travels, who, till we came, had not seen anything at all; for it is not the fashion here
					to have Curiosity. We had at first arrival an inundation of Visits pouring in upon us, for all the English are acquainted, and herd
					much together &amp; it is no easy Matter to disengage oneself from them, so that one sees but little of the French themselves. </p>
         <p>To be introduced to the People of high quality, it is absolutely necessary to be master of the Language, for it is not to be imagind
					that they will take pains to understand anybody, or to correct a stranger's blunders. Another thing is, there is not a House where they
					don't play, nor is any one at all acceptable, unless they do so too .. a professed Gamester being the most advantageous Character a Man
					can have at Paris. The Abbés indeed &amp; Men of learning are a People of easy access enough, but few English that travel have
					knowledge enough to take any great Pleasure in their Company, at least our present Set of travellers have not. We are, I think to
					remain here no longer than Ld Conway stays, and then set out for Rheims, there to reside a Month or two, &amp; then to return hither
					again. this is our present design &amp; very often little hankerings break out, so that I am not sure, we shall not come back
					tomorrow.</p>
         <p>We are exceedingly unsettled &amp; irresolute, don't know our own Minds for two Moments together, profess an utter aversion for all
					Manner of fatigue, grumble, are ill natured &amp; try to bring ourselves to a State of perfect Apathy in which [we] are so far
					advanced, as to declare we have no Notion of caring for any mortal breathing but ourselves. In short I think the greatest <hi rend="italic">evil</hi> [that] could have happen'd to us, is our liberty, for we are not at all capable to determine our own
					actions.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>My dear Ashton I am ever <lb/> Yours sincerely </salute>
            <signed>T: G: </signed>
            <dateline>Paris–Hotel de Luxembourg. Rue des petits Augustins <lb/> April 21. N.S. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
