<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (31 August 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 114-115</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 187 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 277, vol. ii, 584-586
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=277</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXII, vol. ii, 46-49
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:46</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXVI, vol. ii, 318-320
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:318</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXXIV, vol. iii, 202-204
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:202</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0320">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1758-08-31"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Willis, Browne</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Encyclopédie</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Blomefield, Francis</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Stoke Manor House</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0320">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I ought to have informed you sooner, that I had received the Ticket you were so good to buy for me,
					but I have been obliged to go every day almost to Stoke-house, where the Garricks have been all the
					last week. they are now gone, &amp; I am not sorry for it, for I grow so old, that, I own, People in high spirits &amp; gayety
					overpower me, &amp; entirely take away mine. I can yet be diverted with their sallies, but if they appear to take notice of my
					dullness, it sinks me to nothing. I do not know, whether you will blame me, but I found so good an opportunity given me of entering
					into the quarrel between M: and him, that I could not help seizing it, &amp; trying to shew him the
					folly of hearkening to half-witted friends &amp; tale-bearers; and the greater folly of attempting to hurt, or merely to pique, so
					worthy &amp; so estimable a Man. if I did nothing else, I at least convinced him, that I spoke entirely from myself; &amp; that I had
					the most entire good opinion &amp; most unalterable respect as well as kindness for M:n.</p>
         <p>I congratulate you on our successes, &amp; condole with you on our misfortunes: but do you think we
					draw the nearer to any happy conclusion of the war, or that we can bear so great a burthen much longer. the K: of Prussia's situation
					embarrasses me, surrounded as he is, &amp; reduced to the defence of his own little Marquisate.
				</p>
         <p>Your Encyclopedie is the object of my envy. I am reduced to French plays &amp; novels, Willis's
					mitred Abbies, &amp; the History of Norfolk in 3 volumes Folio. these
					latter Authors have, I think, the most wit, tho' the others know rather more of the World.</p>
         <p>I wish the air of Hampstead were not so necessary to you all, but am glad you always know where to find health, &amp; that she lives so near you. I continue better than has been usual for me in the summer, tho' I neither walk, nor take
					any thing: 'tis in mind only, that I am weary &amp; disagreeable. Mrs R: is declining every day, her
					stomach gone, very weak, sometimes giddy, &amp; subject to disorders in her bowels: yet I do not apprehend any immediate danger, but
					believe she will be reduced to keep her bed entirely.</p>
         <p>My best compliments to Mrs Wharton. pray let me hear from you as often as you are in a humour for writing, tho' from hence I can
					requite your kindness with so little to amuse you.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am ever truly <lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
            <dateline>Stoke. Aug: 31. 1758. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
