<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (22 May 1737)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New Haven, CT (Beinecke)/Farmington, CT (Lewis Walpole)</settlement>
                  <institution key="YALE">Yale University Library</institution>
                  <repository>The Lewis Walpole Library</repository>
                  <collection>Manuscript Collections</collection>
                  <idno>Misc. MSS</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <condition>
                           <p>the margins are damaged</p>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 37*, vol. iii, 1315-1319
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Times Literary Supplement</title>, 23 Oct. 1937, 776
			</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0641">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1737-05-22"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011931">Oxford, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Stillingfleet, Benjamin</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pope, Alexander</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0641">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Richard West, Esq.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>at Christ-Church in</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>23 MA</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>My good West </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am qualified with full and ample powers to treat with you in the names of HW and TA ;
					 but as you thought fit to begin with me, I shall think fit to begin with myself: there can be no excuse made for the
					backwardness of my payments, but Poverty; alas! Master, times are so hard, and trading so bad, that now &amp; then a Pepper Corn is all
					[we] can pretend to; but if your Worship would call, as you come this way [you] shall be as welcome to a rasher of Bacon, &amp; a
					pitcher of drink, as the Lord Mayor of London–in short I depend upon seeing you here next month[:] we have indeed nothing to
					shew you, but three old faces, that you have been long used to, tho' perhaps you may find something new even in them; as for me, I
					shall be incessantly painting my eyes, &amp; tiring my head, &amp; looking out at the window in expectation of your wheels; so pray let
					your driving, be as the driving of Jehu, the Son of Nimshi: Mr Conway
					 has been here about a fortnight, &amp; the little Insensible was neither struck with Kings-Chappel, nor moved with
					Trinity-Quadrangle, nor touched with the Senate-house, &amp; even talked of Oxford, as he was walking on Clare-hall Walks; we expect
					you should be moved, struck, &amp; touched with every thing you see here; we have pulled down half my College,
					 that you may have fewer Fibs to tell, when y[ou] begin to praise it; you are to suppose the demolish'd to have been the best
					part of it, &amp; that, that is to be built, you may say all the fine things you please about: we have put our trees in their best
					green Liverys, [or]der'd the Sun to clear our Air, Walpole's Greyhound has got a new Collar, [his?] Cat has learn'd to dance, and all
					this against you come: we can't keep [our] best looks &amp; manners long, so make hast, I charge you: Leonidas, to tell you all that I think of it, not to conceal my judgement in any point, is really, excessively
					—, I particularly admire that noble passage in the —th Book, Line the —th, &amp; then, then the Pathos in that
					speech of — to —, &amp; the Simile concerning the —, so applicable to the present State of Affairs, and most
					people that I have met with, I find perfectly of my opinion in this; for those who admire it, &amp; those, who do not; joyn in thinking
					the above-mention'd passages perfectly fine: what think you of Mr Pope's, Cum tot sustineas &amp;c:
					to me, much preferable to, Flore bono &amp;c: &amp; pray have you read, the Spleen, publish'd sometime ago; bad enough taken altogether perhaps; but if you pull it to pieces, you may find
					pretty picking, &amp; Scraps of great beauty: the Essay on Conversation is by no means contemptible:
					if you direct letters to me out of malice, I will give you all possible provocations; we excuse your Epigram upon condition you always fill up your backsides in the same manner; my backside is too broad to be cover'd
					with an Epigram, so I'll tell you a story; you must know, that Rinaldo was lost, [so?] one Carlo
					&amp; Ubaldo went to look for him, they did not know where; &amp; so</p>
         <q>
            <p>Dismiss'd at length, they break thro' all delay <lb/>
				To tempt the dangers of the doubtfull way: <lb/>
				And first to Ascalon their steps they bend, <lb/>
				Whose walls along the neighbouring Sea extend; <lb/>
				Nor yet in prospect rose the distant Shore, <lb/>
				Scarce the hoarse waves from far were heard to roar; <lb/>
				When thwart the road a river roll'd his flood<lb/>
				Tempestuous, and all further course withstood: <lb/>
				The torrent stream his ancient bounds disdains <lb/>
				Swoln with new force, &amp; late-descending rains: <lb/>
				Irresolute they stand; when lo, appears <lb/>
				A wondrous Sage; vig'rous he seems in years,<lb/>
				Awful his mien, low as his feet there flows <lb/>
				A vestment unadorn'd, tho' white as new fal'n Snows: <lb/>
				Against the stream the wave secure he trod;<lb/>
				His head a chaplet bore, his hand a Rod.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>As on the Rhine, when Boreas' fury reigns, <lb/>
				And winter binds the floods in icy chains; <lb/>
				Swift shoots the village-Maid with rustick play<lb/>
				Smooth, without step adown the shining way, <lb/>
				Fearless in long excursion loves to glide, <lb/>
				And sports, and wantons o'er the frozen tide. <lb/>
				So moved the Seer; but on no harden'd plain, <lb/>
				The river boil'd beneath, &amp; rush'd into the Main:<lb/>
				Where fix'd in wonder stood the warlike pair <lb/>
				His course he turn'd, &amp; thus relieved their care.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Vast, oh my friends, &amp; difficult's the toil<lb/>
				To seek your hero in a distant Soil; <lb/>
				No common helps, no common guide ye need, <lb/>
				Art it requires, &amp; more than winged speed: <lb/>
				What length of Sea remains, what various lands, <lb/>
				Oceans untried, inhospitable Sands?
				<lb/>
				For adverse fate the captive Chief has hurl'd <lb/>
				Beyond the confines of our narrow world: <lb/>Great things &amp; full of wonder in your ears <lb/>
				I shall reveal; but first dismiss your fears,<lb/>
				Nor doubt with me to tread the downward road, <lb/>
				That to the grotto leads, my dark abode.
				</p>
            <p>Scarce had he said, before the warriours eyes <lb/>
				When mountain-high the waves disparted rise; <lb/>
				The flood on either hand its billows rears, <lb/>
				And in the midst a spatious arch appears: <lb/>
				Their hands he seized, &amp; down the Steep he led <lb/>
				Beneath th'obedient rivers inmost bed. <lb/>
				The watry glimm'rings of a fainter day <lb/>
				Discover'd half, &amp; half conceal'd their way, <lb/>
				As when athwart the dusky woods by night <lb/>
				Th' uncertain Crescent gleams a sickly light.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Thro' subterraneous passages they went, <lb/>
				Earth's inmost cells, &amp; [caves o]f deep descent. <lb/>
				Of many a spring they vi[ew]d the secret source,<lb/>
				The birth of rivers, rising t[o] their course; <lb/>
				How infant-springs in mazy wandrings stream<lb/>
				Pregnant of many a tide, &amp; floods of mighty name;<lb/>
				Whate'er with copious train its channel fills, <lb/>
				Floats into lakes, or bubbles into rills: <lb/>
				The Po was there to see, Euphrates' Bed,<lb/>
				And Danube's fount, &amp; Nile's mysterious head.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Further they pass where ripening minerals glow,<lb/>
				And embryon metals undigested flow,<lb/>
				Sulphureous veins, &amp; living Silver shine, <lb/>
				Which soon the parent Suns warm powers refine, <lb/>
				In one rich mass unite the pretious Store, <lb/>
				The parts combine &amp; harden into Oar. <lb/>
				Here gems break thro' the night with glitt'ring beam, <lb/>
				And paint the margin of the costly Stream: <lb/>
				All stones of lustre shoot their vivid ray, <lb/>
				And mix attempred in a various day: <lb/>
				Here the soft emerald smiles of verdant hue <lb/>Here rubies flame with Sapph[ires] heavenly blew; <lb/>
				The diamond there attracts the wondring sight, <lb/>
				Proud in its thousand dies, &amp; luxury of light.</p>
            <p>&amp;c: &amp;c: </p>
         </q>
         <closer>
            <salute>yours, </salute>
            <signed>T: Gray </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Now for Walpole; he bids me tell you, as follows </p>
            <p>[           ]</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>yours, </salute>
               <signed>H: Walpole. </signed>
            </closer>
         </postscript>
         <postscript>
            <p>Now for Ashton, he desires I'd send you word from him that he </p>
            <p>Turn over </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
