<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (28 September 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 250, vol. ii, 527-530
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=250</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXV, 101-109
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:101</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxvii, section iv, 251-256
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:251</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 190-196
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:190</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CL, vol. i, 354-365
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:354</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXV, vol. ii, 291-296
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:291</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXIII, vol. iii, 171-176
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:171</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XCVIII, vol. ii, 21-26
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:21</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXVII, vol. i, 359-363
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:359</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0285">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-09-28"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0285">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Sept: 28. 1757. Stoke. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have (as I desired St:r to tell you) read over Caractacus twice not with pleasure only, but with emotion. you may say what you will, but the contrivance, the manners, the interests, the passions, &amp; the
					expression, go beyond the dramatic part of your Elfrida many many leagues. I even say (tho' you will
					think me a bad judge of this) that the <hi rend="italic">World</hi> will like it better. I am struck with the Chorus, who are not there
					merely to sing &amp; dance, but bear throughout a principal part in the action, &amp; have, (beside the <hi rend="italic">Costume,</hi>
					wch is excellent) as much a character of their own, as any other Person. I am charmed with their priestly pride &amp; obstinacy, when
					after all is lost, they resolve to confront the Roman General, &amp; spit in his face: but now I am going to tell you, what touches me
					most, from the beginning. the first opening is greatly improved: the curiosity of Didius is now a very
					natural reason for dwelling on each particular of the scene before him, nor is the description at all too long. I am glad to find the
					two young Men are Cartismandua's Sons. they interest me far more. I
					love People of Condition. they were Men before, that no body knew: one could not make them a bow, if one had met them at a publick
					place.</p>
				     <p>I always admired that interruption of the Druids to Evelina,
					<hi rend="italic">Peace, Virgin, peace</hi> &amp;c: &amp; chiefly the <hi rend="italic">abstract Idea personified</hi> (to use the
					words of a Critick) at the end of it. that of Caractacus <hi rend="italic">would save my Queen,</hi> &amp;c: &amp; still more that, <hi rend="italic">I know it reverend Fathers, 'tis Heav'ns high will</hi> &amp;c: to <hi rend="italic">I've done. begin the rites!</hi>
					this latter is exemplary for the expression (always the great point with me) I do not mean by expression the mere choice of words, but
					the whole dress, fashion, &amp; arrangement of a thought. here in particular, it is the brokenness, the ungrammatical position, the
					total subversion of the period, that charms me. all that ushers in the Incantation from <hi rend="italic">Try we yet, what holiness can
						do</hi> I am delighted with in quite another way, for this is pure poetry, as it ought to be, forming the proper transition, &amp;
					leading on the mind to that still purer poetry, that follows it. You have somehow mistaken my meaning about the <hi rend="italic">sober
						Sisters</hi>: the verb <hi rend="italic">nod</hi> before only seem'd to be a verb neuter; now you have made it absolutely such, wch
					was just my objection to it. but it is easily alter'd, for if the accusative case come first, there is no danger of ambiguity. I
					read</p>
				     <q>
					       <p>See! their gold &amp; ebon rod <lb/> Where the sober Sisters nod, <lb/> And greet in whispers sage &amp; slow. <lb/> Snowden
						mark! 'tis Magick's hour; <lb/> Now the mutter'd spell hath power, <lb/> Power to rift thy ribs of rock, <lb/> To burst thy base
						with thunder's shock, <lb/> But &amp;c: &amp;c: <lb/> —— than those, that dwell <lb/> In Musick's &amp;c: </p>
				     </q>
				     <p>you will laugh at my <hi rend="italic">to</hi>ses &amp; <hi rend="italic">those</hi>s, but they strike my ear better. what Mador
					sings, must be the finest thing, that ever was wrote; &amp; the next Chorus, where they all go to sleep, must be finer still.</p>
				     <p>In the beginning of the succeeding Act, I admire the Chorus again, <hi rend="italic">Is it not now the hour, the holy hour,</hi>
					&amp;c: &amp; their evasion of a lie, Sayst thou, proud Boy, &amp;c: &amp; <hi rend="italic">sleep with the unsun'd silver,</hi> wch is
					an example of a <hi rend="italic">dramatic</hi> Simile. the sudden appearance of Caractacus, the pretended respect &amp; admiration of
					Vellinus, &amp; the probability of his story, the distrust of the Druids, &amp; their reasoning with Caractacus, &amp; particularly
					that, <hi rend="italic">'Tis meet thou should'st, thou art a King,</hi> &amp;c: &amp; <hi rend="italic">Mark me, Prince, the time will
						come, when Destiny,</hi> &amp;c: are well, &amp; happily imagined. a-propos of the last striking passage I have mention'd, I am going
					to make a digression.</p>
				     <p>When we treat a subject, where the manners are almost lost in antiquity, our stock of Ideas must needs be small, &amp; nothing
					betrays our poverty more, than the returning to, &amp; harping frequently on one Image. it was therefore I thought you should omitt
					some lines before, tho' good in themselves, about <hi rend="italic">the scythed Carr,</hi> that the passage now before us might appear
					with greater lustre, when it came; and in this I see, you have complied with me. but there are other Ideas here &amp; there still, that
					occur too often, particularly about <hi rend="italic">the Oaks,</hi> some of wch I would discard to make way for the rest.</p>
				     <p>But the subjects I speak off to compensate (&amp; more than compensate) that unavoidable poverty, have one great advantage when they
					fall into good hands. they leave an unbounded liberty to pure imagination, &amp; fiction (our favourite provinces) where no Critick can
					molest, or Antiquary gainsay us. &amp; yet (to please me) these fictions must have some affinity, some seeming connection with that
					little we really know of the character &amp; customs of the People. for example I never heard in my days, that Midnight &amp; the Moon
					were Sisters, that they carried rods of ebony &amp; gold, or met to whisper on the top of a mountain: but now I could lay my life, it
					is all true; &amp; do not doubt, it will be found so in some Pantheon of the Druids, that is to be discover'd in the Library at
					Herculaneum. the <hi rend="italic">Car of Destiny &amp; Death</hi> is a very noble invention of the same class, &amp; as far as that
					goes, is so fine, that it makes me more delicate, than perhaps I should be, about the close of it. <hi rend="italic">Andraste sailing
						on the wings of Fame,</hi> that snatches the wreaths from Oblivion to hang them on her loftiest Amaranth, tho' a clear and beautiful
					piece of <hi rend="italic">unknown</hi> Mythology, has too <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> an air to give me perfect satisfaction.</p>
				     <p>Now I proceed. the preparation to the Chorus, tho' so much akin to that in the former act, is excellent. the remarks of Evelina &amp;
					her suspicions of the Brothers, mix'd with a secret inclination to ye younger of them (tho', I think, her part throughout wants
					retouching) yet please me much. and the contrivance of the following scene much more. <hi rend="italic">Masters of Wisdom, no,</hi>
					&amp;c: I always admired; as I do the rocking stone, &amp; the distress of Elidurus. Evelina's examination of him is a well-invented
					scene, &amp; will be with a little pains a very touching one: but the introduction of Arviragus is
					superlative. I am not sure, whether those few lines of his short narrative, <hi rend="italic">My strength repair'd, it boots not, that
						I tell,</hi> &amp;c: do not please me as much, as any thing in the whole Drama. the sullen bravery of Elidurus, the menaces of the
					Chorus, that <hi rend="italic">Think not,</hi> Religion &amp;c: the Trumpet of the Druids; that <hi rend="italic">I'll follow him, tho' in my chains</hi> &amp;c:; <hi rend="italic">Hast thou a Brother, no</hi> &amp;c: the placability
					of the Chorus, when they see the motives of Elidurus' obstinacy, give me great contentment. so do the reflections of the Druid on the
					necessity of lustration, &amp; the reasons for Vellinus' easy escape. but I would not have him <hi rend="italic">seize on a spear,</hi>
					nor <hi rend="italic">issue hasty thro' the</hi> Cavern's mouth.
					 why should he not steal away, unmark'd &amp; unmiss'd, till the hurry of passions in those, that
					should have guarded him, was a little abated? but I chiefly admire the two speeches of Elidurus, Ah Vellinus, is this then &amp;c: and,
						<hi rend="italic">Ye do gaze on me,</hi> Fathers! &amp;c: the manner, in wch the Chorus reply to him,
					is very fine, but the image at the end wants a little mending. the next scene is highly moving! it is so very good, that I must have it
					made yet better.</p>
				     <p>Now for the last Act. I do not know, what you would have, but to me the design &amp; contrivance of it is at least equal to any part
					of the Whole. the short-lived triumph of the Britons, the address of Caractacus to the Roman Victims, Evelina's discovery of the
					ambush, the mistake of the Roman fires for the rising Sun, the death of Arviragus, the interview between Didius, &amp; Caractacus, his
					mourning over his dead Son, his parting speech (in wch you have made all the use of Tacitus, that your Plan would admitt) every thing
					in short, but that little dispute between Didius &amp; him. <hi rend="italic">'Tis well. &amp; therefore to encrease that
						reverence</hi> &amp;c: down to, <hi rend="italic">Give me a moment</hi> (wch must be omitted, or put in the mouth of the Druids) I
					approve in the highest degree. if I should find any fault with the last act, it could only be with trifles &amp; little expressions. if
					you make any alteration, I fear, it will never improve it, I mean, as to the Plan. I send you back the two last sheets, because you bid
					me. I reserve my nibblings and <hi rend="italic">minutiæ</hi> for another day.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, I am most truly<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I have had a printed Ode sent me, call'd Melpomene. pray, who wrote it? I suspect Mr
							Bedingf:d, Montagu young Pitt, or
							Delap. do, say, I like it. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
