<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (19 November 1764)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 45</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 397, vol. ii, 851-855
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=397</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter vi, section v, 380-382
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:380</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXIV, vol. iii, 51-54
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:51</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXV, vol. ii, 436-438
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:436</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXVI, vol. iv, 36-39
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:36</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter I, vol. v, 57-60
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:57</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLVI, vol. ii, 167-170
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:167</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter VI, vol. i, 473-475
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:473</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0449">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1764-11-19"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010052">Ripon, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0449">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To Norton Nicholls Esq at Charles Floyer's Esq of Hollinclose-Hall near Rippon Yorkshire</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>20 NO</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <dateline>Monday. 19 Nov: 1764. </dateline>
					       <salute>Sr.</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I received your letter at Southampton, &amp; as I would wish to treat every body according to their own rule &amp; measure of
					good-breeding, have against my inclination waited till now, before I answer'd it, purely out of fear &amp; respect, &amp; an ingenuous
					diffidence of my own abilities. if you will not take this as an excuse, accept it at least as a well-turn'd period, wch is always my
					principal concern. </p>
				     <p>So I proceed to tell you, that my health is much improved by the sea; not that I drank of it, or bathed in it, as the <hi rend="italic">common people</hi> do: no! I only walk'd by it, &amp; look'd upon it. the climate is remarkably mild, even in Octob:
					&amp; November. no snow has been seen to lie there for these 30 years past. the myrtles grow in the ground against the houses, &amp;
					Guernsey-Lillies bloom in every window. the Town clean &amp; well-built, surrounded by its old stone-walls with their towers &amp;
					gateways, stands at the point of a peninsula, &amp; opens full south to an arm of the sea, wch having form'd two beautiful bays on each
					hand of it stretches away in direct view till it joins the British Channel. it is skirted on either side with gently-rising grounds
					cloath'd with thick wood, &amp; directly cross its mouth rise the high lands of the Isle of Wight at distance, but distinctly seen. in
					the bosom of the woods (conceal'd from profane eyes) lie hid the ruins of Netteleyabbey. there may be
					richer &amp; greater houses of religion, but the Abbot is content with his situation. see there at the top of that hanging meadow under
					the shade of those old trees, that bend into a half-circle about it, he is walking slowly (good Man!) &amp; bidding his beads for the
					souls of his Benefactors, interr'd in that venerable pile, that lies beneath him. beyond it (the meadow still descending) nods a
					thicket of oaks, that mask the building, &amp; have excluded a view too garish, &amp; too luxuriant for a holy eye, only on either hand
					they leave an opening to the blew glittering sea. did not you observe how, as that white sail shot by &amp; was lost, he turn'd &amp;
					cross'd himself, to drive the Tempter from him, that had thrown that distraction in his way. I should tell you, that the Ferryman, who
					row'd me, a lusty young Fellow, told me, that he would not for all the world pass a night at the Abbey, (there were such things seen
					near it,) tho' there was a power of money hid there. from thence I went to Salisbury, Wilton, &amp; Stone-Henge, but of these things I say no more: they will be publish'd at the University-Press.</p>
				     <p>I have been at London this month, that tiresome dull place! where all people under thirty find so much amusement. the Opera with
						Manzuoli in it opens on Saturday, &amp; I go to C: the Wednesday preceding. the Ministry are all
					together by the ears, so are the Opposition: the only doubt is wch will be the weakest: I am afraid, I know. the sentence of
						Alma-Mater, of the North-Briton, &amp; of D'Eon are defer'd. in the mean time Du-Vergy, the Adventurer, who enraged D'Eon
					almost to madness, &amp; has been in jail (for debt) eversince December last, having regain'd his liberty by the help (he says) of his
					countrymen declares upon oath, that he was sent from France with a half-promise of being declared Secretary to the Embassy, that he
					might <hi rend="italic">se servir de son epée,</hi> if occasion were, against D'Eon, or at least urge him to do something, that might
					for ever disgrace him. he gives a detail of all his private conversations with G: &amp; others on
					this head. Mons: de G: is (I hear) much troubled, declares the whole a lye, but what is he to do? must he have another <hi rend="italic">Plaidoyer</hi> in our Courts against this Scoundrel? and indeed from his own narrative he appears to be no better, tho'
					it is interlarded with fine French sentiment about justice &amp; virtue, &amp; honour, &amp; such like.</p>
				     <p>I had prepared a finer period than the other to finish with, but d – mn it! I have somehow mislaid it among my papers. you shall certainly have it next summer. how can people subscribe such a devil of a name (I warrant) you
					call it a <hi rend="italic">christian</hi>-name, to their letters as you do? I always thought at
					times I had a small matter of aversion for you mechanically arising in me, &amp; doubtless this was the reason. fie, fie, put on a
					white satten-mantle, &amp; be carried to church again. however, I forgive you for your Rippon-history's sake. Adieu! I shall almost be glad to see you again.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <signed>T G:</signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Your friend Dr. M: came very kindly to see me, as soon as he had taken possession of his new
						Mastership, &amp; return'd me his thanks for my civilities to you. so never say any more on that head: you see I am paid.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
