<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (8 December 1734)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/4</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 4, vol. i, 9-11
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=4</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 4, vol. i, 12-15
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915i/1/12</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 65-67
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=65</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0004">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1734-12-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="poem">[Lines Spoken by the Ghost of John Dennis at the Devil Tavern]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dennis, John</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0004">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Honble Horatio Walpole Esq</addrLine>
               <addrLine>at the house of the right honble Sr Robert Walpole</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in St James's Square London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 9 DE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute> [           ]</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I (tho' I say it) had too much modesty to venture answering your dear, diverting Letter, in the Poetical Strain myself: but, when I
					was last at the DEVIL, meeting by chance with the deceased Mr Dennis
					there, he offer'd his Service, &amp;, being tip'd with a Tester, wrought, what follows–
				</p>
         <q>
            <p>From purling Streams &amp; the Elysian Scene, <lb/> From Groves, that smile with never-fading Green <lb/> I reascend; in Atropos'
					despight <lb/> Restored to Celadon, &amp; upper light:<lb/> Ye gods, that sway the Regions under
					ground, <lb/> Reveal to mortal View your realms profound; <lb/> At his command admit the eye of Day; <lb/> When Celadon commands,
					what God can disobey? <lb/> Nor seeks he your Tartarean fires to know, <lb/> The house of Torture, &amp; th' Abyss of Woe; <lb/> But
					happy fields &amp; Mansions free from Pain,<lb/> Gay Meads, &amp; springing flowers best please ye
					gentle Swain: </p>
            <p>That little, naked, melancholy thing <lb/> My Soul, when first she tryed her flight to wing; <lb/>Began
					with speed new Regions to explore, <lb/> And blunder'd thro' a narrow Postern door; <lb/> First most devoutly having said its
					Prayers, <lb/> It tumbled down a thousand pair of [Stairs],<lb/> Thro' Entries long, thro' Cellars
					vast &amp; deep, <lb/> Where ghostly Rats their habitations keep, <lb/> Where Spiders spread their Webs, &amp; owlish Goblins sleep.
					<lb/> After so many Chances had befell, <lb/> It came into a mead of Asphodel: <lb/> Betwixt the Confines of ye light &amp; dark
					<lb/> It lies, of 'Lyzium ye St James's park: <lb/> Here Spirit-Beaux flutter along the Mall, <lb/> And shadows in disguise scate
					o'er ye Iced Canal: <lb/> Here groves embower'd, &amp; more sequester'd Shades, <lb/> Frequented by ye Ghosts of Ancient Maids,
					<lb/> Are seen to rise: the melancholy Scene <lb/> With gloomy haunts, &amp; twilight walks between<lb/> Conceals the wayward band: here spend their time <lb/> Greensickness Girls, that died in youthful prime, <lb/> Virgins
					forlorn, all drest in Willow-green-i <lb/> With Queen Elizabeth and Nicolini.</p>
            <p>More to reveal, or many words to use <lb/> Would tire alike your patience &amp; my muse. <lb/> Believe, that never was so faithful
					found <lb/> Queen Proserpine to Pluto under ground, <lb/> Or Cleopatra to her Marc-Antony <lb/> As Orozmades to his Celadony.</p>
            <p>P:S: <lb/> Lucrece for half a crown will shew you fun,<lb/> But Mrs Oldfield is become a Nun.<lb/> Nobles &amp; Cits, Prince Pluto &amp; his Spouse <lb/> Flock to the Ghost of
					Covent-Garden house: <lb/> Plays, which were hiss'd above, below revive; <lb/> When dead applauded, that were damn'd alive: <lb/>
					The People, as in life, still keep their Passions, <lb/> But differ something from the world in Fashions. <lb/> Queen
						Artemisia breakfasts on Bohea.<lb/> And Alexander wears a Ramilie.</p>
         </q>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
