<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (24 July 1753)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="MOLI">Morgan Library &amp; Museum</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Literary and Historical Manuscripts (LHMS)</repository>
		                <idno>PML 16518 (extra-illustrated copy of Gray's Odes), 5</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <msContents>
		                <p>
                     <cit>
                        <quote>"In the 1753 letter he gives details of his trip to Durham and the surroundings there;"</quote>
			                     <bibl>Nelson, Christine, "extra-illustrated copy of Gray's Odes". E-mail to the editor, 14 November 2006</bibl>
                     </cit>
		                </p>
	              </msContents>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford. Both Mitford (1853) and Tovey (1900) erroneously give Mason as the addressee.</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 179, vol. i, 379-380
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=179</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter III, 13-16
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:13</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CVI, vol. i, 235-236
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:235</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0208">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1753-07-24"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0208">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Revd Mr Brown, M:A:</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>President of Pembroke Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>By Caxton</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>DURHAM</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Durham. July 24. Tuesday</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> We perform'd our journey, a very agreeable one, within the time appointed, &amp; left out scarce any thing worth seeing in or near our way. the Doctor &amp; Mrs Wharton had expected
					us about two hours when we arrived at Studley on Friday; we passed that night at Rippon, &amp; the
					next at Richmond, and on Sunday Evening got to Durham. I can not now enter into the particulars of my
					travels, because I have not yet gather'd up my Quotations from the Classicks to intersperse, like Mr Addison: but I hope to be able soon to entertain you with a dish of very choice erudition. I have another reason
					too, wch is, that the Post is just setting out. suffice it to tell you, that I have one of the most beautiful Vales here in England to
					walk in with prospects that change every ten steps, &amp; open something new wherever I turn me, all rude &amp; romantic, in short the
					sweetest Spot to break your neck or drown yourself in that ever was beheld. I have done neither yet, but I have been twice at the
						Races, once at the Assembly, have had a visit from Dr Chapman
					&amp; dined with the Bishop. I am very shabby, for Stonhewer's Box with my Coat in it, wch went by
						Sea is not yet arrived. you are desired therefore to send Lee the Bedmaker at Pet: house to the
					Master of the Lynn-boats to enquire, what Vessel it was sent by, &amp; why it does not come. it was
					directed to Dr Stonhewer of Houghton to be left with the Rector of Sunderland. another trouble I have
					to give you, wch is to order Barnes to bring any Letters Stonhewer or I may have to you, &amp; direct 'em hither. the Doctor &amp; Mrs
					Wh: desire their particular Compliments to you, &amp; are sorry you could not be with us.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, I am ever Sincerely<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P:S: I have left my Watch hanging (I believe) in my bed-room. will you be so good to ask after it. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
