<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs Jennings (27 October 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="SALO">Society of Antiquaries of London</institution>
                  <repository>Library</repository>
                  <collection>Cely-Trevilian Bequest V, 138-139</collection>
                  <idno>MS 444</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 304*, vol. ii, 647-648
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=304*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0351">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1759-10-27"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Jennings, Mrs, 1703-1790</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">Stoke Manor House</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0351">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Oct: 27. 1759.<lb/> Hanover-Square</dateline>
            <salute> Madam </salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I have stay'd thus long, that I might be the better able to say something more determinate on the cause of Lady Cobham's illness
					&amp; the probability of her recovery: but find myself after all very little the wiser in either point. no day has pass'd, but she has gone ten or twelve miles &amp; more in her chaise, &amp; never the worse for so much exercise.
					almost always an appetite both at dinner &amp; supper, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> in my mind she satisfies, as usual, a little too
					freely. her breath at times short (particularly in the evening,) &amp; sinking of the spirits by fits: but none of those convulsive
					gaspings, nor that bar across the stomach she complain'd of at Stoke. the great malady now is want of sleep, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi>
					I can not say, she has enjoy'd in a natural way (except for an hour or two at most, &amp; that in the day-time) since we came to Town.
					she has taken draughts with Laudanum in them over night; but they have succeeded only twice or thrice in procuring quiet slumber, after
						w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> the whole following day she has appear'd, as one in perfect health. the rest of her nights are pass'd in
					continual inquietude. her medecines have been several times changed: these three last days she has left off Laudanum &amp; every thing
					else, and taken crude Quicksilver in the morning only. it seems to take some effect; at least she is certainly not the worse for it,
					&amp; flatters herself, she is rather better. if any new symptom of consequence should follow, I will take care to inform you. D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Duncan is still the Man.</p>
         <p> Our small Family present their best Compliments to Yourself &amp; Miss Jennings.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute> I am<lb/> Madam<lb/> Your most humble Servant </salute>
            <signed> T Gray </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
