<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (29 October 1769)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 193-194</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>4 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">223 mm x 177 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 506, vol. iii, 1078-1081
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=506</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iv, section v, 354-357
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:354</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, journal 2, vol. iii, 235-238
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:238</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, journal 2, vol. ii, 523-527
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:523</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLIV, vol. ii, 143-146
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:139</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0565">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1769-10-29"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0565">
			   <body>
				     <div type="journal">
					
					       <p rendition="#center">Journal continued. 1 Oct: 1769.</p>
					       <p>The figure of <hi rend="italic">Ulz-water</hi> nothing resembles that laid down in our maps: it is 9 miles long, &amp; (at widest)
						under a mile in breadth. after extending itself 3 m: &amp; ½ in a line to S: W: it turns at the foot of <hi rend="italic">Place-Fell,</hi> almost due West, and is here not twice the breadth of the Thames at London. it is soon again interrupted by the
						roots of <hi rend="italic">Helvellyn,</hi> a lofty &amp; very rugged mountain, &amp; spreading again turns off to S: E:, &amp; is lost
						among the deep recesses of the hills. to this second turning I pursued my way about four miles along its borders beyond a village
						scatter'd among trees &amp; call'd <hi rend="italic">Water-malloch,</hi>
						 in a pleasant grave day, perfectly calm &amp; warm, but without a gleam of sunshine: then the sky
						seeming to thicken, the valley to grow more desolate, &amp; evening drawing on, I return'd by the way I came to <hi rend="italic">Penrith.</hi>
					       </p>
					       <p>Oct: 2. Wd at S: E:, sky clearing, <hi rend="italic">Cross-fell</hi> misty, but the outline of the other hills very distinct. set
						out at 10 for <hi rend="italic">Keswick,</hi> by the road we went in 1767. saw <hi rend="italic">Greystock</hi>-town &amp; castle to the right, wch lie only 3 miles (over the Fells) from <hi rend="italic">Ulz-water.</hi> pass'd
						through <hi rend="italic">Penradock</hi>
						 &amp; <hi rend="italic">Threlcot</hi>
						 at the feet of <hi rend="italic">Saddleback,</hi> whose furrow'd sides were gilt by the noon-day
						Sun, while its brow appear'd of a sad purple from the shadow of the clouds, as they sail'd slowly by it. the broad &amp; green valley
						of <hi rend="italic">Gardies</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Low-side,</hi> with a swift stream glittering among the cottages &amp; meadows
						lay to the left; &amp; the much finer (but narrower) valley of St <hi rend="italic">John's</hi> opening into it: <hi rend="italic">Hill-top</hi> the large, tho' low, mansion of the Gaskarths, now a Farm-house, seated on an
						eminence among woods under a steep fell, was what appear'd the most conspicuous, &amp; beside it a great rock like some antient tower
						nodding to its fall. pass'd by the side of <hi rend="italic">Skiddaw</hi> &amp; its cub call'd <hi rend="italic">Latter-rig,</hi>
						 &amp; saw from an eminence at two miles distance the Vale of Elysium in all its verdure, the sun
						then playing on the bosom of the lake, &amp; lighting up all the mountains with its lustre.</p>
					       <p>Dined by two o'clock at the Queen's Head, &amp; then straggled out alone to the <hi rend="italic">Parsonage,</hi> fell down on my
						back across a dirty lane with my glass open in one hand, but broke only my knuckles: stay'd nevertheless, &amp; saw the sun set in all
						its glory.</p>
					       <p>Oct: 3. Wd at S: E:, a heavenly day. rose at seven, &amp; walk'd out under the conduct of my Landlord to <hi rend="italic">Borrodale.</hi> the grass was cover'd with a hoar-frost, wch soon melted, &amp; exhaled in a thin blewish
						smoke. cross'd the meadows obliquely, catching a diversity of views among the hills over the lake &amp; islands, &amp; changing
						prospect at every ten paces, left <hi rend="italic">Cockshut</hi> &amp; Castle-hill (wch we formerly mounted) behind me, &amp; drew
						near the foot of <hi rend="italic">Walla-crag,</hi> whose bare &amp; rocky brow, cut perpendicularly down above 400 feet, as I guess,
						awefully overlooks the way: our path here tends to the left, &amp; the ground gently rising, &amp; cover'd with a glade of scattering
						trees &amp; bushes on the very margin of the water, opens both ways the most delicious view, that my eyes ever beheld. behind you are
						the magnificent heights of <hi rend="italic">Walla</hi>-crag; opposite lie the thick hanging woods of Ld Egremont, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Newland</hi>-valley with green &amp; smiling fields embosom'd in the dark cliffs;
						to the left the jaws of <hi rend="italic">Borodale,</hi> with that turbulent Chaos of mountain behind mountain roll'd in confusion;
						beneath you, &amp; stretching far away to the right, the shining purity of the <hi rend="italic">Lake,</hi> just ruffled by the breeze
						enough to shew it is alive, reflecting rocks, woods, fields, &amp; inverted tops of mountains, with the white buildings of <hi rend="italic">Keswick, Crosthwait</hi>-church, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Skiddaw</hi> for a back-ground at distance. oh Doctor! I never
						wish'd more for you; &amp; pray think, how the glass played its part in such a spot, wch is called <hi rend="italic">Carf-close-reeds</hi>: I chuse to set down these barbarous names, that any body may enquire on the place, &amp; easily find the
						particular station, that I mean. this scene continues to <hi rend="italic">Barrow-gate,</hi> &amp; a little farther, passing a brook
						called <hi rend="italic">Barrow-beck,</hi> we enter'd <hi rend="italic">Borodale.</hi> the crags, named <hi rend="italic">Lodoor-banks</hi> now begin to impend terribly over your way; &amp; more terribly, when you hear, that three years since an immense
						mass of rock tumbled at once from the brow, &amp; bar'd all access to the dale (for this is the only road) till they could work their
						way thro' it. luckily no one was passing at the time of this fall; but down the side of the mountain &amp; far into the lake lie
						dispersed the huge fragments of this ruin in all shapes &amp; in all directions. something farther we turn'd aside into a coppice,
						ascending a little in front of <hi rend="italic">Lodoor</hi> water-fall. the height appears to be about 200 feet, the quantity of
						water not great, tho' (these three days excepted) it had rain'd daily in the hills for near two months before: but then the stream was
						nobly broken, leaping from rock to rock, &amp; foaming with fury. on one side a towering crag, that spired up to equal, if not
						overtop, the neighbouring cliffs (this lay all in shade &amp; darkness) on the other hand a rounder broader projecting hill
							shag'd with wood &amp; illumined by the sun, wch glanced sideways on the upper part of the cataract.
						the force of the water wearing a deep channel in the ground hurries away to join the lake. we descended again, &amp; passed the stream
						over a rude bridge. soon after we came under <hi rend="italic">Gowder-crag,</hi> a hill more formidable to the eye &amp; to the
						apprehension than that of <hi rend="italic">Lodoor</hi>; the rocks atop, deep-cloven perpendicularly by the rains, hanging loose &amp;
						nodding forwards, seem just starting from their base in shivers: the whole way down &amp; the road on both sides is strew'd with piles
						of the fragments strangely thrown across each other &amp; of a dreadful bulk. the place reminds one of those passes in the Alps, where
						the Guides tell you to move on with speed, &amp; say nothing, lest the agitation of the air should loosen the snows above, &amp; bring
						down a mass, that would overwhelm a caravan. I took their counsel here and hasten'd on in silence. </p>
					       <q>
						         <p>Non ragioniam di lor; ma guarda, e passa!
						</p>
					       </q>
				     </div>
				     <div type="part">
					       <opener>
						         <salute>Dear Dr </salute>
					       </opener>
					       <p>Have you lost the former part of my journal? it was dated from <hi rend="italic">Aston,</hi> 18 Oct:. How does Stonhewer doe? will his Father's condition allow him to return as yet? I beg my respects to all the family at
						Old-Park, &amp; am ever</p>
					       <closer>
						         <salute>Yours </salute>
						         <signed>T G: </signed>
						         <dateline>29 Oct: 1769. Cambridge. </dateline>
					       </closer>
				     </div>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
