<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (27 April 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge, MA</settlement>
                  <institution key="HARV">Harvard University</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library</repository>
                  <idno>fMS Eng 870 (52a)</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 476, vol. iii, 1030-1032
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=476</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXX, 415-417
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:415</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXVII, vol. iii, 195-197
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:195</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0532">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-04-27"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Palgrave, William, 1735-1799</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Thrandeston</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hertfordshire</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0532">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Southampton Row, April 27, 1768.</dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>By this time I conclude, you are return'd to Cambridge: tho' I thought it a long time, before I heard of you from Thrandeston, and could have wish'd you had stay'd longer with Palgrave: perhaps you are in Hertfordshire, however I write
					at a venture. I went to Mr. Mann's, and (tho' he is in Town) not finding him at home, left a note with
					an account of my business with him, and my direction. I have had no message in answer to it: so possibly he has written to you, and
					sent the papers. I know not.</p>
         <p>Mr. Precentor is still here, and not in haste to depart, indeed I do not know whether he has not a fit of the Gout: it is certain, he
					had a pain yesterday in his foot, but whether owing to Bechamel and Claret, or to cutting a corn, was
					not determined: he is still at Stonhewer's house, and has not made his journey to Eton and to Bath
					yet, tho' he intends to do it.</p>
         <p>We have had no mobs, nor illuminations yet, since I was here. Wilkes's speech you have seen; the Court was so surprised at being contemn'd to its face,
					and in the face of the World, that the Chief in a manner forgot the matter in hand, and enter'd into an apology for his own past
					conduct, and so (with the rest of his Assessors) shuffled the matter off, and left the danger to the officers of the Crown, that is
					indeed, to the Ministry. Nobody had ventured, or would venture to serve the <hi rend="italic">Capias</hi>
					 upon him. I cannot assure, it is done yet; tho' yesterday I heard it was, and (if so) he comes again
					to-day into Court. He professes himself ready to make any submissions to the K., but not to give up
					his pursuit of Ld. HI. The Delavals attend very regularly, and take
					notes of all that passes. His writ of Error on the Outlawry must come to a decision before the House of Lords.
				</p>
         <p>I was not among the Coal-heavers at Shadwell, tho' seven people lost their lives in the fray: Nor
					was I in Goodmans Fields where the Bawdy-house was demolish'd. The
					Ministry (I believe) are but ticklish in their situation: they talk of Grenville and his Brother,
					again. Lord forbid! it must be dreadful necessity indeed, that brings them back.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I am ever yours,</salute>
            <signed>T. G. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>If you are at Cambridge, pray let me know.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
