<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (18 October 1769)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 191-192</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 182 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 505, vol. iii, 1074-1078
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=505</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iv, section v, 350-354
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:350</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, journal 1, vol. iii, 232-234
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:232</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, journal 1, letter VI, vol. ii, 519-522
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:519</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section V, letter VII, vol. iv, 143-148
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:143</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLIV, vol. ii, 135-165
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:135</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter IV, vol. i, 447-471
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:447</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0564">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7029839">Aston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1769-10-18"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0564">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Thomas Wharton Esq of</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Old-Park near Darlington</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>SHEFFIELD</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="journal">
            <p rendition="#center">Journal. 30 Sept: 1769.</p>
            <p>Wd at N:W. clouds &amp; sunshine. a mile &amp; ½ from Brough on a hill lay a great army
							encamp'd. to the left open'd a fine valley with green meadows &amp; hedge-rows, a Gentleman's house
						peeping forth from a grove of old trees. on a nearer approach appear'd myriads of horses &amp; cattle in the road itself &amp; in all
						the fields round me, a brisk stream hurrying cross the way, thousands of clean healthy People in their best party-color'd apparel,
						Farmers &amp; their families, Esquires &amp; their daughters, hastening up from the dales &amp; down the fells on every side,
						glittering in the sun &amp; pressing forward to join the throng: while the dark hills, on many of whose tops the mists were yet
						hanging, served as a contrast to this gay &amp; moving scene, wch continued for near two miles more along the road, and the crowd
						(coming towards it) reach'd on as far as Appleby. </p>
            <p>On the ascent of the hill above Appleby the thick hanging wood &amp; the long reaches of the Eden (rapid, clear, &amp; full as ever)
						winding below with views of the Castle &amp; Town gave much employment to the mirror: but the sun was
						wanting &amp; the sky overcast. oats &amp; barley cut every where, but not carried in. passed Kirby-thore, Sr W: Dalston's house at Acorn bank, Whinfield-park, Harthorn-oaks, Countess-pillar, Brougham-Castle, Mr Brown (one of ye
						six Clerks) his large new house, cross'd the Eden &amp; the Eimot
						(pronounce <hi rend="italic">Eeman</hi>) with its green vale, &amp; at 3 o'clock dined with Mrs Buchanan, at <hi rend="italic">Penrith</hi> on trout &amp; partridge. in the afternoon walk'd up the <hi rend="italic">Beacon-hill</hi> a mile to the top, saw
						Whinfield and Lowther-parks, &amp; thro' an opening in the bosom of that cluster of mountains, wch the Doctor well remembers, the Lake
						of Ulz-water, with the craggy tops of a hundred nameless hills. these to W: &amp; S:, to the N: a great extent of black &amp; dreary
						plains, to E: <hi rend="italic">Cross-fell</hi> just visible thro' mists &amp; vapours hovering round it.</p>
            <p>Oct: 1. Wd at S:W: a grey autumnal day, air perfectly calm &amp; gentle. went to see <hi rend="italic">Ulz-water</hi> 5 miles
						distant. soon left the Keswick-road &amp; turn'd to the left thro' shady lanes along the Vale of <hi rend="italic">Eeman,</hi> wch
						runs rapidly on near the way, ripling over the stones. to the right is <hi rend="italic">Delmaine,</hi> a large fabrick of pale red
						stone with 9 windows in front &amp; 7 on the side built by Mr Hassel, behind it a fine lawn
						surrounded by woods &amp; a long rocky eminence rising over them. a clear &amp; brisk rivulet runs by the house to join the Eeman,
						whose course is in sight &amp; at a small distance.</p>
            <p>Farther on appears <hi rend="italic">Hatton St John,</hi>
						 a castle-like old mansion of Mr Huddleston. approach'd <hi rend="italic">Dunmallert,</hi> a fine
						pointed hill, cover'd with wood planted by old Mr Hassle beforemention'd, who lives always at home &amp; delights in planting. walk'd
						over a spungy meadow or two &amp; began to mount this hill thro' a broad &amp; strait green alley among the trees, &amp; with some
						toil gain'd the summit. from hence saw the Lake opening directly at my feet majestic in its calmness, clear &amp; smooth as a blew
						mirror with winding shores &amp; low points of land cover'd with green inclosures, white farm-houses looking out among the trees,
						&amp; cattle feeding. the water is almost every where border'd with cultivated lands gently sloping upwards till they reach the feet
						of the mountains, wch rise very rude &amp; aweful with their broken tops on either hand. directly in front at better than 3 mile's
						distance, <hi rend="italic">Place-Fell,</hi>
						 one of the bravest among them, pushes its bold broad breast into the midst of the Lake &amp; forces
						it to alter it's course, forming first a large bay to the left &amp; then bending to the right.</p>
            <p>I descended <hi rend="italic">Dunmallert</hi> again by a side avenue, that was only not perpendicular, &amp; came to <hi rend="italic">Barton</hi>-bridge over the <hi rend="italic">Eeman,</hi> then walking thro' a path in the wood round the bottom of the
						hill came forth, where the <hi rend="italic">Eeman</hi> issues out of the lake, &amp; continued my way along it's western shore close
						to the water, &amp; generally on a level with it. Saw a cormorant flying over it &amp; fishing.... (to be continued)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Aston. 18 Oct: 1769.</dateline>
               <salute>Dear Dr </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I hope you got safe and well home after that troublesome night: I long to hear you say so. for me I have continued well, been so
						favour'd by the weather, that my walks have never once been hinder'd till yesterday, (that is during a fortnight &amp; 3 or 4 days,
						&amp; a journey of 300 miles, &amp; more) &amp; am now at Aston for two days. tomorrow I go towards Cambridge: Mason is not here, but
						Mr Alderson receives me. my best respects to the family!</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Adieu! I am ever <lb/> Yours (pray, tell me about Stonhewer).
						</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
