<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to John Chute (23 November 1746)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Sherborne St John</settlement>
		                <institution key="VYNE">The Vyne</institution>
		                <collection>Chute of The Vyne, Sherborne St John</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 126, vol. i, 252-254
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=126</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>A History of the Vyne in Hampshire.</title> By Chaloner William Chute. Winchester: Jacob &amp; Johnson, 1888, 102-104
			</bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXX, vol. i, 147-149
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:147</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section III, letter no. 2, 181-183
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:181</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0144">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1746-11-23"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/6079515">Chute, John, 1701-1776</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0144">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>John Chute Esq</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>at the House of Francis Whithed Esq</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>in New Bond Street</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Westminster</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 24 NO</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Cambridge .. Sunday </dateline>
					       <salute>Lustrissimo</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> It is doubtless highly reasonable, that two young Foreigners come into so distant a Country to acquaint themselves with strange
					Things should have some Time allowed them to take a View of the King (God bless him) &amp; the Ministry, &amp; the Theatres, &amp;
					Westminster Abbey &amp; the Lyons, &amp; such other Curiosities of the Capital City: you civilly call
					them Dissipations; but to me they appear Employments of a very serious Nature, as they enlarge the Mind, give a great Insight into the
					Nature &amp; Genius of a People, keep the Spirits in an agreeable Agitation, and (like the True Artificial Spirit of Lavender)
					amazingly fortify &amp; corroborate the whole nervous System. but as all Things sooner or later must pass away, &amp; there is a
					certain Period, when (by the Rules of Proportion) one is to grow weary of every Thing: I may hope at length a Season will arrive, when
					you will be tired of forgetting me. 'tis true you have a long Journey to make first, a vast Series of Sights to pass thro'. let me see!
					you are at Lady Brown already. I have set a Time, when I may say, oh! he is now got to the Waxwork in
						Fleetstreet: there is nothing more but Cupid's Paradise, &amp; the
					Hermaphrodite from Guinea, &amp; the Original Basilisk Dragon, &amp; the Buffalo from Babylon, &amp; the New Chimpanzee, &amp; then I. have a Care, you had best, that I come in my Turn: you know in whose Hands I have deposited
					my little Interests. I shall infallibly appeal to my <hi rend="italic">best invisible</hi> Friend in
					the Country.</p>
				     <p>I am glad Castalio has justified himself &amp; me to You. he seem'd to me more made for Tenderness,
					than Horrour, &amp; (I have Courage again to insist upon it) might make a better Player than any now on the Stage. I have not alone
					received (thank you) but almost got thro' Louis Onze. 'tis very well, methinks, but nothing
					particular. what occasion'd his Castration at Paris, I imagine, were certain Strokes in Defence of
					the Gallican Church &amp; its Liberties–a little Contempt cast upon the Popes, &amp; something here &amp; there on the Conduct
					of the great Princes. there are a few Instances of Malice against our Nation, that are very foolish.</p>
				     <p>My Companion, whom you salute, is (much to my Sorrow) only so now &amp; then. he lives 20 Miles off
					at Nurse, &amp; is not so meagre as when you first knew him, but of a reasonable Plumposity. he shall not fail being here to do the
					Honours, when you make your publick Entry. heigh-ho! when that will be, chi sá? but, mi lusinga il dolce sogno!–I love Mr
					Whithed, &amp; wish him all Happiness. </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Farewell, my dear Sr, I am ever Yours</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Commend me kindly to Mr Walpole. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
