<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mary Antrobus (May 1767)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="ROBA">Rosenbach Museum &amp; Library</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 439, vol. iii, 954-956
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=439</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0495">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1767-05"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29394522">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0495">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>May . . 1767. Jermyn-Street</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mary</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> The note I inclose to you is for money lent by poor Graves, while he lived with me, to a
					pot-companion of his. we look'd upon it long as a desperate debt, but of late have learn'd, that the Man is set up in a way of
					business, &amp; very capable of paying it. the reason I trouble you with it is this. your Cousin <hi>T: Hide</hi> has several times mention'd it to my Servant <hi>Stephen</hi>, &amp; was so
					obliging to offer his assistance in getting the money. if he will really give himself that trouble, it will be a deed of charity, &amp;
					I should be very glad of his success. you will take care of the note, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is already torn &amp; tatter'd with
					age: if any little expence is incur'd, Graves will gladly satisfy it out of the money, &amp; be very thankful.</p>
				     <p> My shirts begin exceedingly to want company, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> (I hope) they may shortly
					expect, &amp; I as much want to get into the North. when you send them, you will please to add a bill of my debts to you, &amp; insert
					the expence you were at for what you bought the morning I set out for Hadham: and I will send the
					money, &amp; thank you. I know not, whether Dolly will want any farther intelligence from me, before I
					go. if she does, let her tell me soon. she has already an account of the rents of Hand-Alley; a state
					of the case with regard to the Conveyance, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> Worlidge ought to have got ready
					&amp; sign'd; &amp; the Extract from M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Rogers's Will. I would wish to send her an account of the Taxes, but
					have it not perfect myself. in the mean time I send her, what appears from the last account (turn over). you will give my service to
					your Mamma, &amp; love to Dolly.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> I am sincerely<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed> T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <table>
						         <row>
							           <cell>1. Tho: Tilson (has a Lease, &amp; pays the Taxes himself) </cell>
							           <cell>£  .  .  S  .  .  D: </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>2. Hurst. </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>3. Tho: Abbis. </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>4. M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Humphreys </cell>
							           <cell>0 - - 12 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>5. West </cell>
							           <cell>0 - - 14 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>6. Crack </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>7. M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Burgess </cell>
							           <cell>0 - - 10 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>8. Terry (will pay no rent, nor quit the house) </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>9. Leach </cell>
							           <cell>0 - - 10 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>10. Davis </cell>
							           <cell>0 - - 10 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>11. Munt, for his house, &amp; stable-yard, has no lease, but pays taxes himself </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>12. Hatton (no house, but a saw-yard) </cell>
							           <cell/>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>13. M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Richardson (has a Lease) </cell>
							           <cell>2 - - 0 - - 0</cell>
						         </row>
					       </table>
					       <p> They all (I think) are allow'd the Tax, except <hi>Tilson, Munt</hi>, &amp; <hi>Hatton</hi>, but in some cases I really do not know
						to what it amounts. observe, that what I set down belongs to M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Olliffe &amp; myself jointly: so that you are
						only to reckon the half of it, as deducted from your part of the rents. the bills brought in by the Workmen amount in the whole (M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Eyres included) to about 105£.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
