<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (20 May 1765)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
		                <institution key="BDLN">Bodleian Library, Oxford University</institution>
		                <repository>Special Collections</repository>
		                <collection>Montagu papers</collection>
		                <idno>MS. Montagu d. 17, fols. 95-96</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">203 mm x 162 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <surrogates>
			                  <bibl>
				                    <title>Digital facsimile [JPEG] from original letter</title>
			                  </bibl>
		                </surrogates>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 403, vol. ii, 874-876
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=403</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0457">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1765-05-20"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0457">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Rev<hi rend="super">d</hi> M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Brown,</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>President of Pembroke Hall</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>20[...]</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I can not help writing a line, whereas you have reason to expect a volume, wch indeed could not contain the history of this
					wonderful period. we are at the eve, I fear, of some great event, &amp; perhaps a very tragical one. the bill of regency brought in by the ministry against their own will, afterwards turn'd by them to serve their own purpose,
					&amp; that purpose afterwards drop'd &amp; aukwardly disavowed by them, are things, that you must have heard already in gross, &amp;
					the detail I have not time to give you. I shall only tell you, that yesterday the D: of C: was sent
					in the morning to Hayes at eleven, &amp; did not come back till past four. when you know he undertook
					the embassy, you will imagine, what the terms were. he carried a Carte Blanche with him, honours, offices, absolute &amp; unlimited
					power. all wch (to the astonishment of all mankind) were sent back as they came, with a peremptory refusal. whether from resentment of
					their former craft &amp; little unworthy dealings with him, or that he may be press'd &amp; intreated in a more <hi rend="italic">submissive</hi> manner to accept the uncontroll'd guidance of the nation, is hard to say. I hope the latter, for then he will yield,
					&amp; if he does not, God knows what may be the consequence. Bedford House is like a fortress
						besieged. soldiers looking over the walls, &amp; patrolling round all the avenues. he immured
					within, &amp; the Dutchess ill with fright. the mob curseing him without &amp; his garrison murmuring
					at the service they are forced to do within. at the time of the great disturbance the Ministers were all there in the house, &amp; had
					not risen from table. had it not been for the Guards, the house had certainly been pull'd down, &amp; all the family murther'd. they
					say, there were few or no weavers among the mob, but in these times of scarcity &amp; general discontent, it is no wonder, if all the
						villainous populace of London should join them. I saw the Weavers at the door of the house of Lords
					on Thursday. as far as my eye can judge, I do not believe, they were 5000, &amp; they neither
					appear'd insolent, nor intimidated. the noise was great, &amp; I assure you, there were many blank faces in fine coaches to be seen,
					&amp; much bowing &amp; smiling, &amp; civil words thrown at random among the ragged regiment. tomorrow is the day, when worse is
					expected, &amp; it is certain numbers are flocking to Town from Norfolk, Essex, &amp;c: the London Militia are order'd out, &amp; no
					one can say, where this may end. if Mr P: accepts, all this may vanish into smoke.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I shall write again very soon. </salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Don't shew my letter to any but Mr Talbot.
					</p>
				     </postscript>
				     <closer>
					       <dateline>Monday. May 20.</dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
