<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (13 October 1766)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 55</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 429, vol. iii, 940-942
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=429</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section v, 344-345
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:344</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXIX, vol. iii, 123-125
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:123</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter IV, vol. v, 65-66
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:65</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0485">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1766-10-13"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010052">Ripon, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0485">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To Norton-Nicholls Esq at Hollin-close near Rippon Yorkshire</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>14 OC</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>My Dear Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have received a second instance of your kindness &amp; confidence in me. and surely you hazard nothing in trusting me with the
					whole of your situation. it appears not to me so new, as it does to you. you well know, the tenour of my conversation (urged perhaps at
					times a little farther than you liked) has been intended to prepare you for this event, to familiarize your mind with this spectre,
					that you call by its worst name: but remember, that <hi rend="italic">Honesta res est læta paupertas.</hi>
					 I see it with respect, &amp; so will every one, whose poverty is not seated in their mind. there is
					but one real evil in it (take my word, who know it well) &amp; that is, that you have less the power of assisting others, who have not
					the same resources to support them. it is this consideration, that makes me remind you, that <hi rend="italic">Ansel</hi>
					 is lately dead, a Lay-fellow of your college. that if Dr M: (whose
					follies let us pardon, because he has some feeling &amp; means us well) be of little use, &amp; if Dr H: (another simple Friend of ours, perhaps with less sensibility) can not serve us in this: yet Dr R:
					is not immortal, you have always said to succeed him was not impracticable. I know it would be creditable, I know it would be
					profitable, I know it would in lieu of a little drudgery bring you freedom. that drudgery would with a little use grow easy. in the
					mean time, if any better prospect present itself, there you are ready to take advantage of the opportunity. in short this was always my
					favourite project, &amp; now more than ever for reasons, that will occur to yourself. in waiting for the accomplishment of it, you will
					take orders, &amp; if your Uncles are slow in their motions, you will accept a Curacy (for a title
					will be requisite) not under every body, that offers, but under some gentlemanlike friendly Man, &amp; in a christian country. a
					profession you must have: why not then accommodate yourself chearfully to its beginnings. you have youth, you have many kind
					well-intention'd people belonging to you, many acquaintance of your own, or familie's, that will wish to serve you. consider, how many
					have had the same, or greater cause for dejection with none of these resources before their eyes. </p>
				     <p>I am in Town for a month or more, &amp; wish to hear from you soon. Mr. W: has indeed been dangerously ill with the gout in his
					stomach, but nothing paralytick, as was said. he is much recover'd, &amp; gone to Bath.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Dear Sr, I am faithfully Yours,</salute>
					       <signed>T G. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I will write again soon. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
