<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (16 April 1751)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/50</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 160, vol. i, 345-346
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=160</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 174, vol. ii, 109-111
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/109</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 49-50
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=49</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0181">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1751-04-16"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Chute, John, 1701-1776</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0181">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Hon<hi rend="super">ble</hi> Horace Walpole Esq</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Arlington Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 17 AP</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Cambridge .. April 16</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I am ashamed, but not astonish'd at poor Mr Whithed's Insensibility. yet I had settled it with
					myself before, that he would give Mr Chute 500£ a Year, wch I thought at least by half too little. but this was just the Thing, in wch
					Mr Chute neither would, nor could, suggest to him what he ought to do; &amp; so he has done accordingly. I hope, it was only negative
					Ingratitude; but (I own to you) I do suspect, there was a little Reflection in it, &amp; that his Conversations with Mr L:, &amp;
					perhaps with another Person, who knows the Value of Money, better than that of Friendship, might have had their Effect upon his Mind. I
					do not wonder, that Mr Chute is satisfied with every Thing: I even believe, that when Time shall convince him, that Whithed has fall'n
					extremely short in his Acknowledgements to him, it will rather add to his Concern, than diminish it. my best Wishes always accompany
					him; &amp; I can only <hi rend="italic">wish,</hi> that they were of more Consequence. what a Change this Loss will make in his future
					Life! I can only guess at the Extent of it. the Brothers are nasty People, that don't deserve
					mentioning. I see <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi> sets himself up in his Brother's Room, wch (I hope in God) will considerably reduce
					his Share in the Inheritance.</p>
         <p>You surprise me with the Account you give me of the Alteration in your own Family. what a Man must my Ld O: have been, who might so easily have prevented it? I am heartily concerned for the Share you must bear in
					it. sure Your Uncle, &amp; Mrs H:, have it in their Power, if not
					to retrieve, at least much to alleviate, this Misfortune; for from the Mother no body would expect
					anything. perhaps the good Qualities you mention in your Nephew may go farther in repairing his Loss,
					than any of his Relations could have done. from the little I had seen &amp; heard of him, it did not seem probable, that he could
					continue long in the thoughtless Ways of Folly. You were very good, when you found Time to let me know, what I am interested in, not
					barely from Curiosity, but because it touches you so nearly. I can return that kindness no otherwise, than by not taking up your
					Attention longer, when it is so fully employed on your own Affairs.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, my dear Sr, I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
