<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs. (Dorothy) Gray (14 June 1740)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 88, vol. i, 162-164
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=88</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxii, section ii, 92-94
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:92</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XL, vol. i, 71-72
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:71</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XXIV, vol. ii, 95-97
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:95</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XXIV, vol. ii, 113-116
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:113</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XL, vol. i, 87-89
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:87</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XXII, vol. i, 216-218
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:216</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0100">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7004474">Naples, Italy</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1740-06-14"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Gray, Mrs. (Dorothy), 1685-1753</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0100">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Naples, June [14], 1740. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Our journey hither was through the most beautiful part of the finest country in the world; and every spot of it, on some account or
					other, famous for these three thousand years past. The season has hitherto been just as warm as one
					would wish it; no unwholesome airs, or violent heats, yet heard of: The people call it a backward year, and are in pain about their
					corn, wine, and oil; but we, who are neither corn, wine, nor oil, find it very agreeable. Our road was through Velletri, Cisterna,
					Terracina, Capua, and Aversa, and so to Naples. The minute one leaves his Holiness's dominions, the face of things begins to change
					from wide uncultivated plains to olive groves and well-tilled fields of corn, intermixed with ranks of elms, every one of which has its
					vine twining about it, and hanging in festoons between the rows from one tree to another. The great old fig-trees, the oranges in full
					bloom, and myrtles in every hedge, make one of the delightfullest scenes you can conceive; besides that, the roads are wide, well-kept,
					and full of passengers, a sight I have not beheld this long time. My wonder still increased upon entering the city, which I think, for
					number of people, outdoes both Paris and London. The streets are one continued market, and thronged with populace so much that a coach
					can hardly pass. The common sort are a jolly lively kind of animals, more industrious than Italians usually are; they work till
					evening; then take their lute or guitar (for they all play) and walk about the city, or upon the sea-shore with it, to enjoy the
					fresco. One sees their little brown children jumping about stark-naked, and the bigger ones dancing with castanets, while others play
					on the cymbal to them. Your maps will show you the situation of Naples; it is on the most lovely bay in the world, and one of the
					calmest seas: It has many other beauties besides those of nature. We have spent two days in visiting the remarkable places in the
					country round it, such as the bay of Baiæ, and its remains of antiquity; the lake Avernus, and the Solfatara, Charon's grotto, &amp;c.
					We have been in the Sybils' cave and many other strange holes under ground (I only name them, because you may consult Sandy's
						travels); but the strangest hole I ever was in, has been to-day at a place called Portici, where his
					Sicilian Majesty has a country-seat. About a year ago, as they were digging, they discovered some
					parts of ancient buildings above thirty feet deep in the ground: Curiosity led them on, and they have been digging ever since; the
					passage they have made, with all its turnings and windings, is now more than a mile long. As you walk you see parts of an amphitheatre,
					many houses adorned with marble columns, and incrusted with the same; the front of a temple, several arched vaults of rooms painted in
					fresco. Some pieces of painting have been taken out from hence, finer than any thing of the kind before discovered, and with these the
					King has adorned his palace; also a number of statues, medals, and gems; and more are dug out every day. This is known to be a Roman
						town, that in the Emperor Titus's time was overwhelmed by a furious eruption of Mount Vesuvius, which
					is hard by. The wood and beams remain so perfect that you may see the grain; but burnt to a coal, and dropping into dust upon the least
					touch. We were to-day at the foot of that mountain, which at present smokes only a little, where we saw the materials that fed the
					stream of fire, which about four years since ran down its side. We have but a few days longer to stay here; too little in conscience
					for such a place. [...]</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
