<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (17 December 1767)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 76</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 456, vol. iii, 980-981
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=456</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXXXIX, vol. iii, 214-215
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:214</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XV, vol. v, 83-85
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:83</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0512">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1767-12-17"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7018903">Richmond, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0512">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To the Revd Mr Nicholls at Richmond in Surrey</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>SAFFRON WALDEN 18 D[E]</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				
				
				     <p>You have indeed brought yourself into a little scrape. I would, if it were my own case, say to Ld L: (supposing you were pressed by
					him) that I had not received yet any letter from T:; in the mean time I would write instantly to him
					in Devonshire, tell him my difficulty, &amp; how I got into it, &amp; desire his consent to shew Ld L: so much of his letter, as might
					be proper. I would then (supposing him not averse) have a cold or the tooth-ach, &amp; be detain'd at Richmond, from whence I would (transcribing so much of this very letter as may be fit for his Ldp to see) send it to
					him in Town, as the substance of what I had <hi rend="italic">just then</hi> received in answer to my own. he will have suspicions (you
					will say) from my not shewing him the original. no matter! you are nothing to Ld L:; perhaps you had written to T: about other affairs,
					that you can not shew him; he will not be so uncivil as to ask for it; in short let him suspect, what he pleases: any thing is better,
					than to shew it him. and yet I would omitt nothing in my copy but what relates to <hi rend="italic">Berwick</hi>
					 and to <hi rend="italic">the addition</hi> that he should have made to the parsonage-house. the kindness express'd for him toward the latter part of the letter will (if he cares for T:) make up for
					all the rest.</p>
				     <p>By the way T: does himself much credit with me by this letter, &amp; I did not (begging his pardon) suspect him of writing so well.
					but yet I must stand up a little for Ld L:. what occasion pray for so many cordial letters (wch, if he were good for nothing at bottom,
					must have cost him some pains of head) &amp; for the bribe of a living, only to gain T:s vote &amp; interest, wch as a Relation &amp;
					Friend he would have had for nothing at all. is not the date he sets to the beginning of Ld L:s coldness to him carried a little too
					far back? did it not really begin a little later, when he had brought his wife to Mamhead, &amp; they did not much like her? these
					indeed are only conjectures, but they may be true. I have to be sure a little prejudice to Madam; but yet I must be candid enough to
					own that the parsonage-house sticks a little in my stomach. </p>
				     <p>My best remembrances to Temple, &amp; tell him, I wish, he would not give too much way to his own sensibilities; &amp; still less (in
					this case) to the sensibilities of <hi rend="italic">other People.</hi> it is always time enough to quarrel with one's Friends.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu!</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>It was Mr Bentley indeed.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
