<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Taylor How (12 January 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Add. MSS 26889, ff. 81-82</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 184 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 462, vol. iii, 995-997
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=462</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter ix, section v, 389-391
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:389</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 284-287
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:284</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXVIII, vol. iii, 173-174
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:173</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXIII, vol. ii, 488-490
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:488</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLIV, vol. iv, 98-100
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:98</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXIII, vol. ii, 112-114
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:112</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter IX, vol. i, 480-481
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:480</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0518">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1768-01-12"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">How, William Taylor, d. 1777</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/1028841">Chipping Ongar, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0518">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>William Taylor-How Esq, at</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Stondon-Place near Ongar</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Essex</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>13 IA</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Cambr: Pemb: Coll: Jan: 12. 1768. </dateline>
            <salute>Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You perceive by Mr Brown's letter, that I pass'd all the summer in the North of England, went from thence to London, &amp; did not
					arrive here till the middle of December, where I found your parcel. since that time I have been
					generally confined to my room, &amp; besides I was willing to go thro' the eight volumes before I
					return'd you an answer. this must be my excuse to you, for only doing now, what in mere civility I ought to have done long ago. first I
					must condole with you, that so neat an edition should swarm in almost every page with errors of the press, not only in notes &amp;
					citations from Greek, French, &amp; English authors, but in the Italian text itself, greatly to the disreputation of the Leghorn
					Publishers. this is the only reason (I think) that could make an edition in England necessary: but I
					doubt you would not find the matter much mended here, our presses, as they improve in beauty, declining daily in accuracy: besides you
					would find the expence very considerable, &amp; the sale in no proportion to it, as in reality it is but few people in England, that
					read currently &amp; with pleasure the Italian tongue; &amp; the fine old editions of their capital Writers are sold at London for a
					lower price, than they bear in Italy. an English translation I can by no means advise. the justness of thought &amp; good sense might
					remain; but the graces of elocution (wch make a great part of Algarotti's merit) would be entirely lost, &amp; that merely from the
					very different genius &amp; complexion of the two languages. </p>
         <p>I rather think these volumes should be handsomely bound, before they are put into the Library: they bind very neatly here; &amp; if
					you approve it, Mr Brown will order it to be done. doubtless there can be no impropriety in making the
					same present to the University, nor need you at all to fear for the reputation of your Friend: he has
					merit enough to recommend him in any country, a tincture of various sorts of knowledge; an acquaintance with all the beautiful arts; an
					easy command, a precision, warmth, &amp; richness of expression; &amp; a judgement, that is rarely mistaken, on any subject to wch he
					applies it. of the Dialogues I have formerly told you my thoughts. the Essays and Letters (many of
					them entirely new to me) <hi rend="italic">on the Arts</hi> are curious &amp; entertaining. those on other subjects (even where the
					thoughts are not new to me, but borrowed from his various reading &amp; conversation) often better put, &amp; better express'd than in
					the originals. I rejoice, when I see Machiavel defended or illustrated, who to me appears one of the wisest Men, that any nation in any
					age has produced. most of the other discourses military or political are well worth reading, tho' that on Kouli-Khan was a mere Jeu
					d'esprit, a sort of historical exercise. the letters from Russia I had read before with pleasure, particularly the narrative of
						Munich &amp; Lascy's campaigns. the detach'd thoughts are often new
					&amp; just; but there should have been a revisal of them, as they are often to be found in his letters repeated in the very same words.
					some too of the familiar letters might have been spared. The Congress of Cythera I had seen, &amp;
					liked before, the <hi rend="italic">Giudicio d'Amore</hi> is an addition rather inferior to it. the verses are not equal to the prose,
					but they are above mediocrity.</p>
         <p>I shall be glad to hear your health is improved, &amp; that you have thoughts of favouring us with your company here.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am Sr your most obedt humble Servant, </salute>
            <signed>THO: GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
