<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Palgrave (6 September 1758)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 278, vol. ii, 586-587
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=278</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxxiii, section iv, 271-272
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:271</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 211-212
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:211</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLXXIII, vol. ii, 49-52
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:49</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXXVII, vol. ii, 320-322
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:320</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXXV, vol. iii, 204-206
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:204</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CIV, vol. ii, 41-42
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:41</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXXIII, vol. i, 376-378
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:376</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0321">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1758-09-06"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Palgrave, William, 1735-1799</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0321">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Stoke, Sept. 6, 1758. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I do not know how to make you amends, having neither rock, ruin, or precipice near me to send you; they do not grow in the south: but
					only say the word, if you would have a compact neat box of red brick with sash windows, or a grotto made of flints and shell-work, or a
					wallnut-tree with three mole-hills under it, stuck with honeysuckles round a bason of gold-fishes, and you shall be satisfied; they
					shall come by the Edinburgh coach.
				</p>
				     <p>In the meantime I congratulate you on your new acquaintance with the <hi rend="italic">savage,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">rude,</hi>
					and the <hi rend="italic">tremendous.</hi> Pray, tell me, is it anything like what you had read in your book, or seen in two-shilling
					prints? Do not you think a man may be the wiser (I had almost said the better) for going a hundred or two of miles; and that the mind
					has more room in it than most people seem to think, if you will but furnish the apartments? I almost envy your last month, being in a
					very insipid situation myself; and desire you would not fail to send me some furniture for my Gothic apartment, which is very cold at
					present. It will be the easier task, as you have nothing to do but transcribe your little red books, if they are not rubbed out; for I
					conclude you have not trusted everything to memory, which is ten times worse than a lead pencil: Half
					a word fixed upon or near the spot, is worth a cart-load of recollection. When we trust to the picture that objects draw of themselves
					on our mind, we deceive ourselves; without accurate and particular observation, it is but ill-drawn at first, the outlines are soon
					blurred, the colours every day grow fainter; and at last, when we would produce it to any body, we are forced to supply its defects
					with a few strokes of our own imagination. God forgive me, I suppose I have done so myself before now, and misled many a good body that
					put their trust in me. Pray, tell me, (but with permission, and without any breach of hospitality), is it so much warmer on the other
					side of the Swale (as some people of honour say) than it is here? Has the singing of birds, the
					bleating of sheep, the lowing of herds, deafened you at Rainton? Did the vast old oaks and thick
					groves of Northumberland keep off the sun too much from you? I am too civil to extend my enquiries beyond Berwick. Every thing,
					doubtless, must improve upon you as you advanced northward. You must tell me, though, about Melross, Rosslin Chapel, and
						Arbroath. In short, your Port-feuille must be so full, that I only desire a loose chapter or two, and
					will wait for the rest till it comes out.</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
