<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (16 July 1740)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 91, vol. i, 167-170
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=91</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxv, section ii, 99-102
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/99</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 124, vol. i, 320-324
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915i/1/320</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XLII, vol. i, 75-78
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/75</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section II, letter fragment, 144
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1890/1/144</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XXVII, vol. ii, 102-105
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/102</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XXVII, vol. ii, 121-126
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/121</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XLIII, vol. i, 94-97
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/94</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XXV, vol. i, 222-225
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/222</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0103">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000457">Florence, Italy</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1740-07-16"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">West, Gilbert</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Naples</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0103">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Florence, July 16, 1740. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>You do yourself and me justice, in imagining that you merit, and that I am capable of sincerity. I
					have not a thought, or even a weakness, I desire to conceal from you; and consequently on my side deserve to be treated with the same
					openness of heart. My vanity perhaps might make me more reserved towards you, if you were one of the heroic race, superior to all human
					failings; but as mutual wants are the ties of general society, so are mutual weaknesses of private friendships, supposing them mixt
					with some proportion of good qualities; for where one may not sometimes blame, one does not much care ever to praise. All this has the
					air of an introduction designed to soften a very harsh reproof that is to follow; but it is no such matter: I only meant to ask, Why
					did you change your lodging? Was the air bad, or the situation melancholy? If so, you are quite in the right. Only, is it not putting
					yourself a little out of the way of a people, with whom it seems necessary to keep up some sort of intercourse and conversation, though
					but little for your pleasure or entertainment, (yet there are, I believe, such among them as might give you both) at least for your
					information in that study, which, when I left you, you thought of applying to? for that there is a certain study necessary to be
					followed, if we mean to be of any use in the world, I take for granted; disagreeable enough (as most necessities are) but, I am afraid,
					unavoidable. Into how many branches these studies are divided in England, every body knows; and between that which you and I had
					pitched upon, and the other two, it was impossible to balance long. Examples shew one that it is not absolutely necessary to be a
					blockhead to succeed in this profession. The labour is long, and the elements dry and unentertaining; nor was ever any body (especially
					those that afterwards made a figure in it) amused, or even not disgusted in the beginning; yet, upon a further acquaintance, there is
					surely matter for curiosity and reflection. It is strange if, among all that huge mass of words, there be not somewhat intermixed for
					thought. Laws have been the result of long deliberation, and that not of dull men, but the contrary; and have so close a connexion with
					history, nay, with philosophy itself, that they must partake a little of what they are related to so nearly. Besides, tell me, Have you
					ever made the attempt? Was not you frighted merely with the distant prospect? Had the Gothic character and bulkiness of those volumes
					(a tenth part of which perhaps it will be no further necessary to consult, than as one does a dictionary) no ill effect upon your eye? </p>
         <p>Are you sure, if Coke had been printed by Elzevir, and bound in twenty neat pocket volumes, instead
					of one folio, you should never have taken him up for an hour, as you would a Tully, or drank your tea over him? I know how great an
					obstacle ill spirits are to resolution. Do you really think, if you rid ten miles every morning, in a week's time you should not
					entertain much stronger hopes of the Chancellorship, and think it a much more probable thing than you do at present? The advantages you
					mention are not nothing; our inclinations are more than we imagine in our own power; reason and resolution determine them, and support
					under many difficulties. To me there hardly appears to be any medium between a public life and a private one; he who prefers the first,
					must put himself in a way of being serviceable to the rest of mankind, if he has a mind to be of any consequence among them: Nay, he
					must not refuse being in a certain degree even dependent upon some men who already are so. If he has the good fortune to light on such
					as will make no ill use of his humility, there is no shame in this: If not, his ambition ought to give place to a reasonable pride, and
					he should apply to the cultivation of his own mind those abilities which he has not been permitted to use for others' service. Such a
					private happiness (supposing a small competence of fortune) is almost always in every one's power, and the proper enjoyment of age, as
					the other is the employment of youth. You are yet young, have some advantages and opportunities, and an undoubted capacity, which you
					have never yet put to the trial. Set apart a few hours, see how the first year will agree with you, at the end of it you are still the
					master; if you change your mind, you will only have got the knowledge of a little somewhat that can do no hurt, or give you cause of
					repentance. If your inclination be not fixed upon any thing else, it is a symptom that you are not absolutely determined against this,
					and warns you not to mistake mere indolence for inability. I am sensible there is nothing stronger against what I would persuade you
					to, than my own practice; which may make you imagine I think not as I speak. Alas! it is not so; but I do not act what I think, and I
					had rather be the object of your pity, than you should be that of mine; and, be assured, the advantage I may receive from it, does not
					diminish my concern in hearing you want somebody to converse with freely, whose advice might be of more weight, and always at hand. We
					have some time since come to the southern period of our voyages; we spent about nine days at Naples. It is the largest and most
					populous city, as its environs are the most deliciously fertile country, of all Italy. We sailed in the bay of Baiæ, sweated in the
					Solfatara, and died in the grotta del Cane, as all strangers do; saw the Corpus Christi procession, and the King and the Queen, and the city underground, (which is a wonder I reserve to tell you of
					another time) and so returned to Rome for another fortnight; left it (left Rome!) and came hither for the summer. You have seen an
					Epistle to Mr. Ashton, that seems to me full of spirit and thought, and a good deal of poetic fire. I
					would know your opinion. Now I talk of verses, Mr. Walpole and I have frequently wondered you should never mention a certain imitation
					of Spencer, published last year by a namesake of yours, with which we are all enraptured and
					enmarvailed.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
