<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (19 December 1756)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 230, vol. ii, 487-490
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=230</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XVI, 57-65
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:57</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXXVI, vol. i, 311-327
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:311</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0261">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1756-12-19"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0261">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Mason</addrLine>
			         </address>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline> Dec: 19. 1756.</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Skroddles </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I vow, I am ashamed to speak it. the nasty Man's Name is – and to a Clergyman too! I am all confusion – it is Joannes
					– Georgius <hi rend="italic">Frickius.</hi> Commentatio de Druidis.
					 accedunt Opuscula quædam rariora, historiam &amp; antiquitates Druidarum illusstrantia, item qb Scriptorum de iisdem Catalogus. it was publish'd at Ulm. 1744. 4to. &amp; in the Nova Acta
						Eruditorum (printed at Leipsick, for 1745.) there is some account of it. the rare little works, wch make the second part of it, are Peter L'Escalopier's Theologia Vett: Gallorum. Cæsar Bulæus, his Historia vett: Academiarum Druidicarum, &amp; two or three more old Flams. I do not know what satisfaction you will
					find in all this, having never seen the Book itself. I find a French Book commended &amp; cited; by Jaques Martin upon the Religion of the ancient Gauls. over leaf you will find a Specimen of my Ld Duke of Norfolk's
					Housekeeping. I desire you would enquire of Mr Noble or somebody, what the same provisions would cost
					now a-days. I send you a modern curiosity enclosed, a Specimen of <hi rend="italic">sturdy begging,</hi>
					 wch cost me half a Guinea. if he writes so to Strangers, what must he do to particular Friends, like
					you? pray, learn a Style &amp; manner against you publish your Proposals. Odikle is not a bit grown,
					tho' it is fine mild open weather. Bell Selby has dream'd that you are a Dean or a Prebendary: I write you word of it, because they say a Whore's dreams are lucky, especially with regard to
					Church-Preferment. you forget Mr Senhouse's Acoustic Warming-Pan: we
					are in a hurry, for I can not speak to him, till it comes. God bless you come &amp; bring it with you, for we are as merry, as the day
					is <hi rend="italic">short.</hi> the Squire is gone. he gave us a Goose, &amp; a Turkey, &amp; two
					puddings of a moderate size.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Dove, I am ever<lb/>Yours </salute>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p> Gaskyn, &amp; the Viper, &amp;c: desire their
						civilities.</p>
					       <p>What Prevys, Marlings, &amp; Ox-birds are, I can not tell, no more than I can how to make Stoke-Fritters. Leche is Blanc-Mange.
						Wardyns are baking Pears. Doyse are Does. do not think they lived thus every day; if you would know, how they eat on Meager-days,
						&amp; in ordinary, I will send you word. I shall only add, that Ld Surry loved butter'd Lyng, &amp; Targets of Mutton for Breakfast;
						&amp; my Lady's Grace used to piddle with a Chine of Beef upon Brewess. </p>
					       <p>You will wonder what I mean by the half Guinea I talk'd of above. it was a Card from Mr Francklin,
						wch I meant to enclose, but can not find it high or low.</p>
					       <table rend="frame" xml:id="Table2">
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>Crystmas-Day </cell>
							           <cell>s </cell>
							           <cell>d  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 35 Malards, 2d1/2 a pece </cell>
							           <cell>7 </cell>
							           <cell>3 1/2  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 55 Wegyns, 2d a pece </cell>
							           <cell>10 </cell>
							           <cell>2  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>Empt: </cell>
							           <cell>{ Item. 38 Teles, 1d1/2 a pece </cell>
							           <cell>4 </cell>
							           <cell>9  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 2 Corlewys </cell>
							           <cell>1 </cell>
							           <cell>0  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 2 Prevys–2d a pece </cell>
							           <cell>0 </cell>
							           <cell>4  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 2 Plovers–2d a pece </cell>
							           <cell>0 </cell>
							           <cell>4  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 8 Woodcoks–3d a pece </cell>
							           <cell>2 </cell>
							           <cell>0  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 42 Marlyngs– 1/2 a pece </cell>
							           <cell>1 </cell>
							           <cell>9  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 42 Rede Shanks– 1/2 a pece </cell>
							           <cell>1 </cell>
							           <cell>9  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 17 Doz: &amp; 1/2 Oxbyrdys, </cell>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell> </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ 3d a doz: </cell>
							           <cell>4 </cell>
							           <cell>4  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 40 grete Byrdys, 1/2, a pece </cell>
							           <cell>1 </cell>
							           <cell>8  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 40 smale Byrdys, 4d a </cell>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell> </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ doz: </cell>
							           <cell>0 </cell>
							           <cell>10  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 11 Pyggs </cell>
							           <cell>3 </cell>
							           <cell>8  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 200 Eggs, 8 1d  </cell>
							           <cell>2 </cell>
							           <cell>8   </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ Item. 31 Cople Conyse, fett at </cell>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell> </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell/>
							           <cell>{ bery </cell>
							           <cell>10 </cell>
							           <cell>4  </cell>
						         </row>
					       </table>
					       <p>Presents .. 10 Cople, Teles. 3 Cople, Wegyns. 4 Cople, Se-Pyse. 8 Malards. 3 Doz: Snytts. 5 Doz: Oxbyrdys. 6 Se-Mewys. 2 Swanys. 2
						Pecoks. 14 Partridges. 4 Woodcoks. 15 Doyse. 4 Gallons Creme. 6 Gall: Cord. a hundred 1/2 of Wardyns. a Bushell Appels. </p>
					       <p>Brekefast, to my Ladyse Grace. Braune, &amp; a Capon stuyd. To my Lords Grace a Crystmas Day, Dyn: First Course. (the Duke, Duchess,
						&amp; 24 Persons to the same) The Borys' Hede. Brawne, Pottage, a stuyd Capon. a bake-Mett with twelve byrdys. Rostyd Vele. a Swane.
						two Rostyd Capons. a Custerde. Stoke-Fretter. Leeche ... (Second Course.) Gely. three Conyse. five Teles. a Pekoke. twelve
						Rede-Shanks. 12 smale Byrdys. 2 Pastyse Venison. a Tarte. Gynger-brede.... (To the Bordys-end). Brawne. a stuyd Capon. a bakyd Cony.
						rostyd Vele. half a Swane. Custerde. Leche .... </p>
					       <p>(Rewarde). Gely. two Conyse. 4 Teles. 12 smale Byrdys. a Pasty Venison. a Tarte. </p>
					       <p>There was also a Table for the Gentlewomen, &amp; 12 Persons to the same. and the Servant's Table, or Tables, at wch sate 28
						Gentlemen, 60 Yeomen, 44 Gromes, &amp; Gentlemen's Servants. the Meats were much the same with the former. one day this Christmas I
						see there were 347 People dined at the lower Tables. the whole expence of the Week (exclusive of Wine, Spices, Salt, &amp; Sauce
						&amp;c:) amounted to £31 - 9 - 6 1/2.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
