<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (25 September 1740)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 94, vol. i, 175-178
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=94</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxvii, section ii, 105-109
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1775/1/105</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 127, vol. i, 333-337
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915i/1/333</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XLV, vol. i, 81-83
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/81</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XXX, vol. ii, 111-113
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/111</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XXX, vol. ii, 133-136
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843ii/2/133</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XLV, vol. i, 100-104
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/1/100</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XXVII, vol. i, 227-231
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/227</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0107">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000457">Florence, Italy</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1740-09-25"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">[The Gaurus]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Ad C: Favonium Zephyrinum</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Sandys, George</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bougeant, Guillaume-Hyacinthe</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0107">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Florence, Sept. 25, N.S. 1740. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>What I send you now, as long as it is, is but a piece of a poem. It has the advantage of all
					fragments, to need neither introduction nor conclusion: Besides, if you do not like it, it is but imagining that which went before, and
					came after, to be infinitely better. Look in Sandy's Travels for the history of Monte Barbaro, and
					Monte Nuovo.
				</p>
         <p>[...]</p>
         <q>
            <p>Nec procul infelix se tollit in æthera Gaurus, <lb/> Prospiciens vitreum lugenti vertice pontum: <lb/> Tristior ille diu, &amp;
						veteri desuetus olivâ <lb/> Gaurus, pampineæqb eheu jam nescius umbræ;<lb/> Horrendi tam sæva premit vicinia montis, <lb/>
						Attonitumqb urget latus, exuritqb ferentem.</p>
            <p>Nam fama est olim, mediâ dum rura silebant <lb/> Nocte, Deo victa, &amp; molli perfusa quiete, <lb/> Infremuisse æquor ponti,
						auditamqb per omnes<lb/> Latè tellurem surdùm immugire cavernas:<lb/> Quo sonitu nemora alta
						tremunt; tremit excita tuto <lb/> Parthenopæa sinu, flammantisqb ora Vesevi.<lb/> At subitò se aperire solum, vastosqb
						recessus<lb/> Pandere sub pedibus, nigrâqb voragine fauces;<lb/> Tum piceas cinerum glomerare sub
						æthere nubes<lb/> Vorticibus rapidis, ardentiqb imbre procellam.<lb/> Præcipites fugere feræ, perqb avia longè<lb/> Sylvarum fugit
						pastor, juga per deserta, <lb/> Ah, miser! increpitans saepè altâ voce per umbram <lb/> Nequicquam natos, creditqb audire
						sequentes.<lb/> Atque ille excelso rupis de vertice solus <lb/> Respectans notasqb domos, &amp; dulcia regna,<lb/> Nil usquàm videt
						infelix præter mare tristi <lb/> Lumine percussum, &amp; pallentes sulphure campos, <lb/> Fumumqb, flammasqb, rotataqb turbine
						saxa.</p>
            <p>Quin ubi detonuit fragor, &amp; lux reddita cælo; <lb/> Mæstos confluere agricolas, pafsuqb videres<lb/> Tandem iterum timido
						deserta requirere tecta: <lb/> Sperantes, si forte oculis, si fortè darentur <lb/> Uxorum cineres, miserorumve ossa parentum, <lb/>
						(Tenuia, sed tanti saltem solatia luctus) <lb/> Uná colligere, &amp; justâ componere in urnâ. <lb/> Uxorum nusquam cineres, nusquam
						ofsa parentum <lb/> (Spem miseram!) assuetosve Lares, aut rura videbunt. <lb/> Quippe ubi planities campi diffusa jacebat; <lb/>
						Mons novus: ille supercilium, frontemqb favillâ<lb/> Incanum ostentans, ambustis cautibus, æquor <lb/> Subjectum, stragemqb suam,
						mæsta arva, minaci<lb/> Despicit imperio, soloqb in littore regnat.</p>
            <p>Hinc infame loci nomen, multosqb per annos<lb/> Immemor antiquæ laudis, nescire labores<lb/> Vomeris, &amp; nullo tellus
						revirescere cultu. <lb/> Non avium colles, non carmine matutino <lb/> Pastorum resonare; adeò undique dirus habebat <lb/> Informes
						latè horror agros, saltusqb vacantes.<lb/> Sæpius et longè
						detorquens navita proram<lb/> Monstrabat digito littus, sævæqb revolvens<lb/> Funera narrabat noctis, veteremqb ruinam.</p>
            <p>Montis adhuc facies manet hirta atqb aspera saxis:<lb/> Sed furor extinctus jamdudum, &amp; flamma quievit, <lb/> Quæ nascenti
						aderat, seu forté bituminis atri <lb/> Defluxere olìm rivi, atque effæta lacuna <lb/> Pabula sufficere ardori, viresqb
						recusat;<lb/> Sive in visceribus meditans incendia jam nunc<lb/> (Horrendùm) arcanis glomerat genti
						esse futuræ <lb/> Exitio, sparsos tacitusqb recolligit ignes.<lb/> Raro per clivos haud secius
						ordine vidi<lb/> Canescentem oleam: longum post tempus amicti <lb/> Vite virent tumuli; patriamqb
						revisere gaudens<lb/> Bacchus in assuetis tenerum caput exerit arvis<lb/> Vix tandem, infidoqb
						audet se credere cœlo.</p>
         </q>
         <p>There was a certain little ode set out from Rome, in a letter of recommendation to you, but possibly
					fell into the enemies' hands, for I never heard of its arrival. It is a little impertinent to enquire after its welfare; but you, that
					are a father, will excuse a parent's foolish fondness. Last post I received a very diminutive letter:
					It made excuses for its unentertainingness, very little to the purpose; since it assured me, very strongly, of your esteem, which is to
					me the thing; all the rest appear but as the petits agrémens, the garnishing of the dish. P. Bougeant,
					in his Langage des Bêtes, fancies that your birds, who continually repeat the same note, say only in plain terms, 'Je vous aime, ma
					chere; ma chere, je vous aime;' and that those of greater genius indeed, with various trills, run divisions upon the subject; but that
					the <hi rend="italic">fond,</hi> from whence it all proceeds, is 'toujours je vous aime'. Now you may, as you find yourself dull or in
					humour, either take me for a chaffinch or nightingale; sing your plain song, or show your skill in music, but in the bottom let there
					be, toujours, toujours de l'Amitié.</p>
         <p>As to what you call my serious letter; be assured, that your future state is to me entirely
					indifferent. Do not be angry, but hear me; I mean with respect to myself. For whether you be at the top of Fame, or entirely unknown to
					mankind; at the Council-table, or at Dick's coffee-house; sick and simple, or well and wise; whatever
					alteration mere accident works in you, (supposing it utterly impossible for it to make any change in your sincerity and honesty, since
					these are conditions sine quâ non) I do not see any likelihood of my not being yours ever.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
