<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (7 June 1760)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 312, vol. ii, 672-676
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=312</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LII, 204-209
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:204</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxxix, section iv, 283-284
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:283</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 231-232
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:231</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCI, vol. ii, 139-143
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:139</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XCIX, vol. iii, 254-259
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:254</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CX, vol. ii, 53-56
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:53</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0360">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1760-06-07"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0360">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>First &amp; foremost pray take notice of the Paper, on wch I am writing to you: it is the first, that ever was made of silk-rags,
					upon the encouragement given by your Society of Arts; &amp; (if this were all the fruits) I think you
					need not regret your two Guineas a-year. the colour &amp; texture you see; &amp; besides I am told, it will not burn (at least will not
					flame) like ordinary paper, so that it may be of great use for hanging rooms. it is uncommonly tough, &amp; tho' very thin, you
					observe, is not transparent. here is another sort of it intended for the uses of Drawing. </p>
				     <p>You have lately had a visit, where you are, that I am sure bodes no good, especially just at the
					time that the D: of C:y, &amp; Mr Blacowe died. we attribute it to
					a <hi rend="italic">Miff</hi> about the Garter, &amp; some other humps &amp; grumps, that he has received. alas! I fear, it will never do. the Conde de Fuentes was much at a loss, &amp; had like to have made a quarrel of it, that he had no body but the D: of N: to introduce him: but Miss Chudleigh has appeased him with a Ball.</p>
				     <p>I have sent Musæus to Mr Fraser, scratched here &amp; there;
					&amp; with it I desired him to inclose a bloody Satyr, written against no less Persons than you &amp; me by name. I concluded at first it was Mr Pottinger, because he is your Friend &amp;
					my humble Servant; but then I thought he knew the World too well to call us the favorite Minions of Taste, &amp; of Fashion, especially as to Odes, for to them his abuse is confined. so it is not Secretary
					Pottinger, but Mr Coleman, nephew to my Lady Bath, Author of the Connoisseur, a Member of some of the
					Inns of Court, &amp; a particular Acquaintance of Mr Garrick. what have you done to him? for I never heard his name before. he makes
					very tolerable fun with me, where I understand him (wch is not every where) but seems more angry with you. least People should not
					understand the humour of the thing (wch indeed to do, they must have our Lyricisms at their finger's ends) he writes letters in Lloyd's
					Evening Post to tell them, who &amp; what it was, that he meant; &amp; says, that it is like to
					produce a <hi rend="italic">great combustion</hi> in the Literary World: so if you have any mind to <hi rend="italic">combustle</hi>
					about it, well &amp; good! for me I am neither so literary, nor so combustible.</p>
				     <p>I am going into Oxfordshire for a fortnight to a place near Henley, &amp; then to Cambridge, if
					that Owl Phobus does not hinder me, who talks of going to fizzle there at the Commencement.
				</p>
				     <p>What do you say to Ld Lyttelton (your old Patron), &amp; Mrs
						Montagu, with their second-hand Dialogues of the Dead? &amp; then
					there is your Friend, the little black Man. he has wrote one supplemental Dialogue, but I did not read it.</p>
				     <p>Do tell me of your health, your doings, your designs, &amp; your golden dreams, and try to love me a little better in Yorkshire than
					you did in Middlesex, for I am ever </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Yours</salute>
					       <signed>T G:</signed>
					       <dateline>London. June 7. 1760. </dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
