<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 15  and 22 May 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 62, vol. i, 106-109
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=62</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iii, section ii, 47-50
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:47</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 125-129
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:125</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 91, vol. i, 217-220
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:217</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XVII, vol. i, 25-28
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:25</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter III, vol. ii, 41-44
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:41</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter III, vol. ii, 46-50
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:46</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXI, vol. i, 41-44
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:41</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter III, vol. i, 175-177
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:175</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0070">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008038">Paris, France</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-05-15"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Racine</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Crébillon fils</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bougeant, Guillaume-Hyacinthe</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Versailles</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Chantilly</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0070">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Paris, May 22, 1739. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>After the little particulars aforesaid I should have proceeded to a journal of our transactions for this week past, should have
					carried you post from hence to Versailles, hurried you through the gardens to Trianon, back again to Paris, so away to Chantilly. But
					the fatigue is perhaps more than you can bear, and moreover I think I have reason to stomach your last piece of gravity. Supposing you
					were in your soberest mood, I am sorry you should think me capable of ever being so dissipé, so evaporé, as not to be in a condition of
					relishing any thing you could say to me. And now, if you have a mind to make your peace with me, arouse ye from your megrims and your
					melancholies, and (for exercise is good for you) throw away your night-cap, call for your jack-boots, and set out with me, last
					Saturday evening, for Versailles–and so at eight o'clock, passing through a road speckled with vines, and villas, and hares, and
					partridges, we arrive at the great avenue, flanked on either hand with a double row of trees about half a mile long, and with the
					palace itself to terminate the view; facing which, on each side of you is placed a semi-circle of very handsome buildings, which form
					the stables. These we will not enter into, because you know we are no jockies. Well! and is this the great front of Versailles? What a
					huge heap of littleness! it is composed, as it were, of three courts, all open to the eye at once, and
					gradually diminishing till you come to the royal apartments, which on this side present but half a dozen windows and a balcony. This
					last is all that can be called a front, for the rest is only great wings. The hue of all this mass is black, dirty red, and yellow; the
					first proceeding from stone changed by age; the second, from a mixture of brick; and the last, from a profusion of tarnished gilding.
					You cannot see a more disagreeable tout-ensemble; and, to finish the matter, it is all stuck over in many places with small busts of a
					tawny hue between every window. We pass through this to go into the garden, and here the case is indeed altered; nothing can be vaster
					and more magnificent than the back front; before it a very spacious terrace spreads itself, adorned with two large basons; these are
					bordered and lined (as most of the others) with white marble, with handsome statues of bronze reclined on their edges. From hence you
					descend a huge flight of steps into a semi-circle formed by woods, that are cut all round into niches, which are filled with beautiful
					copies of all the famous antique statues in white marble. </p>
         <p>Just in the midst is the bason of Latona; she and her children are standing on the top of a rock in the middle, on the sides of which
					are the peasants, some half, some totally changed into frogs, all which throw out water at her in great plenty. From this place runs on
					the great alley, which brings you into a complete round, where is the bason of Apollo, the biggest in the gardens. He is rising in his
					car out of the water, surrounded by nymphs and tritons, all in bronze, and finely executed, and these, as they play, raise a perfect
					storm about him; beyond this is the great canal, a prodigious long piece of water, that terminates the whole: All this you have at one
					coup d'œil in entering the garden, which is truly great. I cannot say as much of the general taste of the place; every thing you behold
					savours too much of art; all is forced, all is constrained about you; statues and vases sowed every where without distinction;
					sugar-loaves and minced-pies of yew; scrawl-work of box, and little squirting jets-d'eau, besides a great sameness in the walks, cannot
					help striking one at first sight, not to mention the silliest of labyrinths, and all Æsop's fables in water; since these were designed
					in usum Delphini only. Here then we walk by moonlight, and hear the ladies and the nightingales sing. Next morning, being Whitsunday,
					make ready to go to the Installation of nine Knights du Saint Esprit, Cambis is one: high mass
					celebrated with music, great croud, much incense, King, Queen,
						Dauphin, Mesdames, Cardinals, and Court: Knights arrayed by his
					majesty; reverences before the altar, not bows, but curtsies; stiff hams; much tittering among the ladies; trumpets, kettle-drums and
					fifes. My dear West, I am vastly delighted with Trianon, all of us with Chantilly; if you would know why, you must have patience, for I
					can hold my pen no longer, except to tell you that I saw Britannicus last Night; all the characters,
					particularly Agrippina and Nero, done to perfection; to-morrow Phædra and Hippolitus. We are making
					you a little bundle of petites pieces; there is nothing in them, but they are acting at present; there are too Crebillon's
						Letters, and Amusemens sur le langage des Bêtes, said to be of one Bougeant, a Jesuit; they are both esteemed, and lately come out. This day se'nnight we go to Rheims.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
