<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Horace Walpole to Thomas Gray (25 March 1771)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New Haven, CT (Beinecke)/Farmington, CT (Lewis Walpole)</settlement>
		                <institution key="YALE">Yale University Library</institution>
		                <repository>The Lewis Walpole Library</repository>
		                <collection>Manuscript Collections</collection>
		                <idno>HW MSS</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <surrogates>
			                  <bibl>
				                    <title>Digital facsimile [JPEG] from original letter</title>
			                  </bibl>
		                </surrogates>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 546, vol. iii, 1175-1177
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=546</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 248, vol. ii, 295-298
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:295</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 188-190
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=188</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0628">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1771-03-25"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0628">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To Mr Gray at Pembroke college Cambridge</addrLine>
			         </address>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Arlington Street <lb/> March 25. 1771. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I am very much pleased with the head of Richardson, and very angry with Bannerman, who shall do nothing for me, since he will not do any thing for me. I only suspend the Bull of
					Excommunication, till I am sure I shall not want Him. If the young Man copies Mezzotinto, as well as he does etching, which is not
					probable, I shall beg you to seize the prints in Bannerman's hands, if it is not inconsistent with the Charters of the City of
					Cambridge, &amp; deliver them to Mr Tyson's Engraver. But as you talked of being in town in March, I
					hope to settle this with you by a verbal negotiation.</p>
				     <p>I have had my House in town broken open, &amp; every thing broken open in my House, &amp; I have not lost to the Value of
						sixpence. The Story is so long, that if I began to tell it you, you woud be here before it was
					finished, tho you shoud not arrive till Christmas. It is talked of more than My Lord Mayor, &amp; My
					Lord Mayor knows as much what to make of it, as any Body does. If you know any Saint that dragged a beautifull young Woman into a Wood
					to ravish her, &amp; after throwing her on her back, &amp; spreading open her Legs, walked quietly away without touching her, to show
					his continence, you have a faint Idea of my House-breakers. Some people have confounded me with my cousin just arrived from France, &amp; imagine they sought for French papers; others say I am Junius– but
					Lord help me! I am no such great Man, nor keep Treason in my glass-case of China. My Miniatures, thank you, are very safe, &amp; so is
					Queen Elizabeth's old face, &amp; all my coins &amp; medals, tho the doors of the Cabinets were
					broken to pieces. you never saw such a Scene of havoc as my first floor was, &amp; yet five pounds will repair all the damage. I have a
					suspicion about the person, whom we are watching, but not the least guess at his Selfdenial. He burst a great hole in the door of the
					Area, &amp; must have had an Iron crow to force open the Chest, for the brass flapper is bent &amp; shivered into seven pieces, but
					contented himself with tumbling the prints &amp; tapestry chairs. Silver candlesticks, linnen, spoons, nothing struck his fancy; yet he
					was in no hurry, for he ransacked the offices, &amp; every room of the first floor, and nobody knows when he came in or went out, tho
					he seems to have taken no precaution not to be heard. There were only the two Maids in town, who were waked by a Passenger that found
					the Street door open between five &amp; six in the Morning. In Short, this is the first Virtuoso that ever visited a collection by main
					force in the middle of the night.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! <lb/> yrs ever </salute>
					       <signed>H WALPOLE </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P.S. Monday night.<lb/>I had sealed my letter, but am forced to open it again &amp; put it in a cover, for I have this minute
						received yours &amp; Thornhill. The Likeness is well preserved &amp; I shall not quarrel with the
						price, but it is too black, &amp; the wig very hard–however as Worlidge's style is
						fashionable, two or three more by the same hand may not displease, therefore pray trouble yourself to give the young Man two more, but
						none to Bannerman. Tell me how I shall send the money I owe you, besides a thousand thanks.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
