<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Edward Bedingfield (10 August 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>San Marino, CA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HULI">The Huntington</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts</repository>
		                <collection>Huntington Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>HM 21915</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 244, vol. ii, 514-515
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=244</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0277">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-08-10"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Bedingfield, Edward, b. 1730</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0277">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <dateline>Stoke. Aug: 10. 1757.</dateline>
					       <salute> Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I have order'd Dodsley long since to send you piping hot from the Press four copies of the Bard &amp; his Companion, three of w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> I take the liberty to offer to Lady Swinburne, M<hi rend="super">rs</hi>
						Bedingfield, &amp; Yourself, and the fourth is intended for Miss Hepburn at Monkridge near Haddington, if there be any such Person, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> I a little doubt. if
					you remember, you promised to take upon you the trouble of conveying it to her. before this time (I hope) they are come safe to your
					hands. you are desired to give me your <hi>honest</hi> opinion about the latter part of the Bard, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> you had not
					seen before, for I know it is weakly in several parts; but it is a mercy, that it ever came to an end at all. there are also six new
					lines at the end of the 2<hi rend="super">d</hi> Antistrophe <hi>Fair laughs the Morn</hi> &amp;c: w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> my Friends
					approve &amp; (to say the truth) so do I. you will do me a favour, if you will inform me what the North says either in good or in bad.
					as to the South, it is too busy &amp; too fastidious to trouble its head about any thing, that has no wit in it. I know, I shall never
					be admired but in Scotland. by the way
					 I am greatly struck with the Tragedy of Douglas, tho' it has infinite faults. the Author seems to me
					to have retrieved the true language of the Stage, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> had been lost for these hundred years; &amp; there is one
					Scene (between Matilda &amp; the old Peasant) so masterly, that it strikes me blind to all the defects in the world.</p>
				     <p> I will not make you any excuses for my <hi>sulkyness</hi> of late, for in reality I have been ill eversince I left Cambridge. I will
					not <hi>deprecate</hi> you with regard to our <hi>Quarrel</hi>, for if any thing escaped me (as you pretend) that seemed
						<hi>strong</hi>, that is, that hurt you a little, I am not conscious of any such meaning, &amp; you would not have me apologize for
					mere words, or an ill-contrived expression.</p>
				     <p> I am highly obliged to you for the two miniatures w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> are exceedingly pretty. I shall preserve them with great
					care, &amp; beg you would kiss (in my name) the fair hand, y<hi rend="super">t</hi> employs itself so
					well, &amp; that honour'd me with them. one of the two seems to be from nature: I desire to know whose house it is, &amp; what river
					runs by it.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> Adieu, Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi> &amp; believe me<lb/> Your Friend &amp; humble Servant </salute>
					       <signed> TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I am at M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Rogers's of Stoke near Windsor Bucks.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
