<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (8 November 1760)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 325, vol. ii, 710-712
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=325</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LIX, 227-230
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:227</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXII, vol. ii, 173-177
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:173</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0375">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1760-11-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hanover</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0375">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You will excuse me, if I write you a little news in this busy time, tho' I have nothing else to write. the Ladies are rejoiced to
					hear, they may probably have a marriage before the Coronation, wch will restore to that pomp all the beauties it would otherwise have
					lost. I hear (but this is <hi rend="italic">sub sigillo</hi>) no very extraordinary account of the
					P:ss of Saxe-Gotha, either as to her person, or temper. I never saw a face of <hi rend="italic">less
						sorrow</hi> than on the late <hi rend="italic">occasion.</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">I do not blame</hi> the inhabitants of a certain great House for not putting on
					that appearance: it would look like affectation. but even the old Servants, &amp; Friends appear insensible, &amp; he is already, as if he never had been. one Person however has behaved with
						<hi rend="italic">firmness</hi> &amp; yet great decency. he walks (at his own desire) Chief Mourner at the solemnity on
						Tuesday, &amp; supposing even the spectacle itself did not touch him, yet it must do so on
					reflection, that he may himself be probably the next that enters that gloomy place,
					 which is far from unlikely. M:n
					walks in the same procession, &amp; as you possibly may see him the next day, he will give you the best account of it. you have heard
					(I suppose) that there are two Wills (not duplicates). he had given to the D: all his jewels, but at the last going to H:r had taken with him all the
					best of them, &amp; made them Crown-Jewels, so that they come to the Successor. he had also given the D: three Millions of Rix-Dollars
					in money, but in the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> will (made since the affair at <hi rend="italic">Closter-Seven</hi>) after an apology to him, as the best Son, that ever lived, &amp; <hi rend="italic">one, that has never
						offended him,</hi> declares, that the expences of the war have consumed all this money. he gives him (&amp; had before done so by a
					deed of gift) all his mortgages in Germany valued at 170,000£, but the French are in possession of part of these lands, &amp; the rest
					are devoured by the war. he gives to Pss Emily, &amp; Mary, about
					37000£ between them, the Survivor to take the whole (I have heard, that the D: was to have a third of this, but has given up his share
					to his Sisters). to Lady Y: a Box, wch is said to have in it 10,000£ in notes. the K: is residuary
					Legatee; what that amounts to, no one will know; &amp; consequently it must remain a doubt, whether he died rich or poor: I incline to
					believe rather the latter, I mean, in comparison of what was expected.
				</p>
         <p>The Archbishop is the most assiduous of Courtiers, standing for ever upright in the midst of a
					thousand Ladies. the other day he trod on the toes of the D:, who turned to him (for he made no sort of excuse) &amp; said aloud, If
					your G: is so eager to make your court, that is the way (pointing towards the King) &amp; then to the Count de Fuentes, You see, Priests are the same in this country as in yours.</p>
         <p>Mr E: Finch (your Representative) has got the place that Sr H: E:
					(my Friend) had, Surveyor (I think) of the Roads, wch is about 600£ a-year. what then (you will ask) is become of my Friend? oh, he is
					a vast Favourite, is restored to his Regiment, &amp; made Groom of the Bed-Chamber. I have not been to see him yet, &amp; am
					half-afraid, for I hear, he has <hi rend="italic">a Levee.</hi> pray, don't tell.</p>
         <p>Ld J: C: is fix'd to come at his time in spite of the World. I hear within the year, you may expect
					a visit from his Majesty in person. the worst I can tell you is that Squit will be a B:p
				</p>
         <p>When the D: of Dev: introduced my Ld Mayor, he desired his Grace would be so kind to tell him, wch
					was my <hi rend="italic">Ld</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Boot</hi>? this must not be told at all; nor any thing else <hi rend="italic">as
						from me.</hi>
         </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!</salute>
            <dateline>London – Nov: 8. 1760. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
