<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Warton (15 April 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a copy of the letter is in Add. MSS 42560, ff. 219-220, Manuscripts collection, British Library, London, UK</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 518, vol. iii, 1122-1125
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=518</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gentleman's Magazine</title>, Feb. 1783, vol. liii, 100
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, appendix D., vol. i, lxxxviii-xc
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816i:lxxxviii</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXII, vol. iii, 276-279
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:276</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0596">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-04-15"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44371601">Warton, Thomas, 1728-1790</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Hurd, Richard, 1720-1808</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Warton, Thomas, 1728-1790</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pope, Alexander</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hurd, Dr. Richard</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0596">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>15 April. 1770 <lb/> Pembroke Hall. </dateline>
            <salute>Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Our Friend Dr. Hurd having long ago desired me in your name to communicate any fragments, or
					sketches of a design, I once had to give a history of English poetry, you may well think me rude or
					negligent, when you see me hesitating for so many months, before I comply with your request, and yet (believe me) few of your friends
					have been better pleased than I to find this subject (surely neither unentertaining, nor unuseful) had fallen into hands so likely to
					do it justice, few have felt a higher esteem for your talents, your taste, &amp; industry. in truth the only cause of my delay has been
					a sort of diffidence, that would not let me send you any thing so short, so slight, &amp; so imperfect, as the few materials I had
					begun to collect, or the observations I had made on them. a sketch of the division &amp; arrangement of the subject however I venture
					to transcribe, and would wish to know, whether it corresponds in any thing with your own plan, for I am told your first volume is
					already in the press.</p>
         <p rendition="#center">INTRODUCTION</p>
         <p>On the poetry of the <hi rend="italic">Galic</hi> (or Celtic) nations, as far back as it can be traced.</p>
         <p>On that of the Goths: its introduction into these islands by the Saxons &amp; Danes, &amp; its duration. on the origin of rhyme among
					the Franks, the Saxons, &amp; Provençaux. some account of the Latin rhyming poetry from its early origin down to the 15th Century. </p>
         <p rendition="#center">P: 1</p>
         <p>On the School of Provence, wch rose about the year 1100, &amp; was soon followed by the French &amp; Italians. their heroic poetry,
					or romances in verse, Allegories, fabliaux, syrvientes, comedies, farces, canzoni, sonnets, balades, madrigals, sestines, &amp;c: </p>
         <p>Of their imitators the <hi rend="italic">French,</hi> &amp; of the first <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> School (commonly call'd the
					Sicilian) about the year 1200 brought to perfection by Dante, Petrarch, Boccace, &amp; others.</p>
         <p>State of Poetry in England from the Conquest (1066) or rather from Henry 2d's time (1154) to the reign of Edward the 3d (1327). </p>
         <p rendition="#center">P: 2</p>
         <p>On <hi rend="italic">Chaucer</hi> who first introduced the manner of the Provençaux improved by the Italians into our country. his
					character &amp; merits at large; the different kinds in wch he excell'd. Gower, Occleve, Lydgate, Hawes, G: Douglas, Lindsay,
					Bellenden, Dunbar, &amp;c: </p>
         <p rendition="#center">P: 3</p>
         <p>Second Italian School (of Ariosto, Tasso, &amp;c:) an improvement on the first, occasion'd by the revival of letters the end of the
					15th century. The lyric poetry of this &amp; the former age introduced from Italy by Ld Surrey, Sr T. Wyat, Bryan, Ld Vaux, &amp;c: in
					the beginning of the 16th century. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Spenser,</hi> his character. Subject of his poem allegoric &amp; romantic, of Provençal invention: but his manner of
						[treating] it borrow'd from the Second Italian School. Drayton, Fairfax, Phin: Fletcher, Golding,
					Phaer, &amp;c: this school ends in Milton.</p>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">third Italian</hi> School, full of conceit, begun in Q: Elizabeths reign, continued under James, &amp; Charles
					the first by <hi rend="italic">Donne,</hi> Crashaw, Cleveland; carried to its height by Cowley, &amp; ending perhaps in <hi rend="italic">Sprat.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rendition="#center">P: 4</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">School of France,</hi> introduced after the Restoration. Waller, Dryden, Addison, Prior, &amp; Pope, wch has
					continued down to our own times.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>You will observe, that my idea was in some measure taken from a scribbled paper of <hi rend="italic">Pope,</hi>
					 of wch (I believe) you have a copy. you will also see that I have excluded <hi rend="italic">dramatic</hi> Poetry entirely wch if you have taken in, it will at least double the bulk &amp; labour of your book.
				</p>
         <p>[           ]</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am, sir, with great esteem, your most humble and obedient servant, </salute>
            <signed>THOMAS GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
