<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (10 October 1751)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 41-42</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">204 mm x 161 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 163, vol. i, 351-354
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=163</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XCVI, vol. i, 215-218
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:215</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXIV, vol. ii, 208-210
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:208</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXXI, vol. iii, 75-78
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:75</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0184">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1751-10-10"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0184">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>My dear Wharton</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>A little kind of Reproach, that I saw the other Day in a Letter of yours to Mr Brown, has made my Guilt fly in my Face, &amp; given
					me Spirit to be a Beast no longer. I desired him to tell you in the beginning of the Summer, that I fear'd my Journey into the North
					would be prevented by the Arrival of my Cousin, Mrs Forster (whom you remember by the Name of
					Pattinson) from India. she came in August; &amp; I continued in Town with her a Month in order to do what little Services I could to a
					Person as strange, &amp; as much to seek, as tho' she had been born in the Mud of the Ganges. after this the Year was too far advanced
					to undertake such an Expedition; &amp; the Thought of seeing you here in the Spring in some measure
					comforts me for the Disappointment; for I depend upon your coming then, when it will be far easier to confer together, &amp; determine
					about a Thing, in wch (I fear) I am too much interes[ted to deserve having] any great share in the
						Determination: for [ ]</p>
				     <p> People. you are aware undoubtedly, that a certain Deference, not to say Servility, to the Heads of Colleges is perhaps necessary to
					a Physician, that means to establish himself here: you possibly may find a Method to do without it. another Inconvenience your Wife,
					rather than you, will feel, the Want of Company of her own Sex; as the Women are few here, squeezy &amp; formal, and little skill'd in
					amusing themselves or other People. all I can say is, she must try to make up for it among the Men, who are not over-agreeable neither.
					I much approve of your settling seriously to your Profession; but as your Father is old, if you should lose him, what becomes of your
					Interest, &amp; to whom is it then to be transfer'd? would you leave London &amp; your Practise again to canvas an Election for
						yourself? it seems to me, that, if you execute your present Scheme, you must (in case of Mr
						Wh:n's Death) entirely lay aside all Views of that Kind. the gradual Transition you propose to make
					thro' Bath or Cambridge to London is very well judged, &amp; likely enough to succeed. for Bath, I am wholly unacquainted with it,
					&amp; consequently can say little to the Purpose. the Way of Life there might be more amusing to Mrs Wharton, than this; but to You, I
					think, would be less satisfactory. I sincerely congratulate you on the good Effects of your new Medecine, wch is indeed a sufficient
					Recompence for any Pains you have taken in that Study. but to make a just Tryal of its Efficacy &amp; of your own Constitution, you
					certainly ought to pass a little Time at London (a Month or so) &amp; that [ ] engaged himself to
					make it up 1000£, in case the Brothers will not do it, &amp; they have (after some Hesitation) refused it. our good Mr Brown goes out of his Office today, of wch he is not a little
					glad. his College, wch had much declined for some time, is picking up again: they have had twelve Admissions this Year; &amp; are just
					filling up two Fellowships with a Mr Cardell, whom I do not know, but they say, he is a good Scholar;
					&amp; a Mr Delaval, a Fellow-Commoner (a younger Son to old Delaval
					of Northumberland) who has taken his Degree in an exemplary Manner, &amp; is very sensible, &amp; knowing. the Appeal, wch has been so long contended for, will, I believe, at last be yielded to with a good Grace, or rather
					bestowed, by the Advice of the D: of N:, &amp; my Lord Ch:r, &amp; will be the best &amp; most
					popular Thing they can do, but you must not mention it, till it is actually done. I am sorry your friend Chapman will lose all the
					Merit of his Pamphlet, wch (by the Way) has been answer'd exceedingly well, &amp; with all due
						Contempt. he seems much mortified, &amp; was preparing a Reply; but this Event, I doubt, will cut
					him short.
				</p>
				     <p>I know of nothing new in the literary Way, but the History of Lewis, 14th, by Voltaire; not that I
					have yet seen it but my Expectations are much raised.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, my dear Wharton, I am ever<lb/> Most truly Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P:S: I am ready to pay my Debts, if you will tell me to whom. my Compliments &amp; good Wishes to Mrs Wharton, &amp; the little
						Gentry. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
