<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Robinson (10 October 1763)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>Princeton, NJ</settlement>
                  <institution key="PRIN">Princeton University Library</institution>
                  <collection>Robert H. Taylor Collection of English and American Literature (RTC01)</collection>
                  <idno>Modern (Unbound) Manuscripts and Correspondence, series III, box 7a, folder 16</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photocopy is at the British Library, RP 2570 (ii)</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 380, vol. ii, 824-825
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=380</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gentleman's Magazine</title>, Dec. 1803, 1107
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLVI, vol. iii, 28
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/28</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXI, vol. ii, 425-426
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/425</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXII, vol. iv, 24-25
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iv/1/24</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0433">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1763-10-10"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Robinson, William, Rev., c. 1726-1803</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">York</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Aston</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0433">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Oct. 10, 1763. Pembroke Hall. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear (Reverend) Billy –</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Having been upon the ramble, I have neglected all my duties, in hopes of finding pleasures in their room; which, after all (as you
					know well), one never finds. My conscience reproaches me with your obliging letter; and would (I really think) carry me into
					Somersetshire, did not poverty and winter stare me in the face, and bid me sit still. I well remember Dr. Ross's kind invitation, and in better days still hope to accept it. Doubt not but my inclinations will be
					quickened by the hopes I entertain of seeing you in so many new lights; the travelled Mr. Robinson, with a thousand important airs and
					graces, so much <hi rend="italic">virtù,</hi> so much <hi rend="italic">scavoir-vivre!</hi> the husband, the father, the rich
					clergyman, warm, snug, and contented as a bishop. My mouth waters: but sure – the family will be in town this winter, and I
					shall see you there in November. Is this the fine autumn you promised me? Oh! I hear you (not curse: you must not, but) ... this
					untoward climate. I doubt not but you write to Mason, though he does not tell me so. There is he, repining at his four-and-twenty weeks
					residence at York, unable to visit his bowers, the work of his own hands, at Aston, except in the depth of winter; and longing for the
					fleshpots and coffee-houses of Cambridge. There is nobody contented but you and I – oh yes, and Dr. Ross; who (I shrewdly
					suspect) is the happiest of the three.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, dear Sir, and believe me sincerely<lb/> Your friend and humble servant, </salute>
            <signed>T. GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Present my compliments to Mrs. Robinson. Some time or other I hope to have the honour of being better known to her. Mr. Brown is
						well, and much obliged to you for your kind remembrance of him. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
