<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (19 July 1767)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 448, vol. iii, 968
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=448</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXIII, 396-397
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:396</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 280-281
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:280</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCVI, vol. iii, 150-151
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:150</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0504">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1767-07-19"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0504">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Sunday. July 19. 1767. Old-Park. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I come forthwith to the epitaph, wch you have had the charity to write at the A:p's request. it will certainly do (for it is both
					touching &amp; new) but yet will require much finishing. I like not the three first lines: it is the Party most nearly concern'd, at
					least some one closely connected, &amp; bearing a part in the loss, that is usually supposed to speak on these occasions: but these
					lines appear to be written by the Chaplain, &amp; have an air of flattery to his Patron. all that is good in them is better expressed
					in the four last verses. <hi rend="italic">Where the cold ashes</hi> &amp;c: these five verses are well, except the word <hi rend="italic">benignant,</hi> &amp; the thought (wch is not clear to me, besides that it is somewhat <hi rend="italic">hardly</hi>
					express'd) of <hi rend="italic">When Beauty only blooms</hi> &amp;c: in gems, that want colour &amp; perfection, a <hi rend="italic">foil</hi> is put under them to add to their lustre: in others, as in diamonds, the foil is black; &amp; in this sense when a pretty
					Woman chuses to appear in publick with a homely one, we say she uses her <hi rend="italic">as a foil.</hi> this puzzles me, as you
					neither mean, that Beauty sets off Virtue by its contrast &amp; opposition to it: nor that her Virtue was so imperfect, as to stand in
					need of Beauty to heighten its lustre. for the rest I read, <hi rend="italic">That sweetest harmony of soul</hi> &amp;c: <hi rend="italic">Such was the Maid,</hi> &amp;c: all this to the end I much approve, except–<hi rend="italic">crown'd with
						truth,</hi> and lightens <hi rend="italic">all their load.</hi> the first is not precise; in the latter you say too much. <hi rend="italic">Spreads his child</hi> too is not the word. when you have corrected all these faults, it will be excellent.
				</p>
         <p>I thank you for your Comments on my inaccurate metaphor. in return I will be sure to shew them to the Parties, who should have wrote them; &amp; who doubtless, when they see them, will acknowledge them for their own. We
					are all much in want of you, &amp; have already put off two journeys, because we thought you were to come on Mondays: pray tell us your
					mind out of hand, least we lose all our future Mondays. Mr Brown has not above another week to stay with us (for Ld St: comes on the
					27th out of Scotland) &amp; must go into the third heaven to see nothing-at-all, 'tall–all.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I am truly<lb/> Yours. </salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>No news of Palgrave [ ]
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
