<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (14 April 1770)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 95</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 517, vol. iii, 1121-1122
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=517</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xi, section v, 393
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:393</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 299
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:299</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXI, vol. iii, 274-276
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:274</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXVII, vol. v, 106-108
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:106</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0595">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1770-04-14"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0595">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk By Yarmouth</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Camb: 14 Apr: 1770. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I thought my mysteries were but too easy to explain, however you must have a little patience, for I
					can hazard only word of mouth. what you say of poor B: is so true, &amp; (let me add) expresses so well my own feelings, that I shall
					transcribe your words, &amp; send them to him: were I in his place, I should be grateful for them! by
					this time I should think, you may have received a letter from him yourself, for in that I received from Abbeville, 31 March, he spoke
					of his intention to write to you. I wrote to you myself as soon as I return'd from London, the 1st (I think) of April.
				</p>
				     <p>I am coming to see you, my good Friend, that is, on Monday se'nnight I mean to call on Palgrave for
					a few days in my way to Blundeston. as to Wales you may do with me, what you please, I care not. there is this inconvenience in our
					way, that I must call on Mason at Aston (&amp; so may you too) for a little while, the last week in May: from thence we strike across to Chester, &amp; enter Wales. for the summer of next year (tho' I
					shall be dead first) I am your Man, only I desire it may be a secret between ourselves, till the time comes, as you love your life.</p>
				     <p>I rejoice to see, you are so great a Gardiner &amp; Botanist: my instructions will be very poor: De B: with five lessons from
						Miller (before he departed for Sumatra) &amp; his own matchless industry, could have told you much
					more than I can. it would be strange if I should blame you for reading Isocrates. I did so myself 20 years ago, &amp; in an edition at
					least as bad as yours. the <hi rend="italic">Panegyrick,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">De Pace, Areopagitic,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Advice to Philip,</hi> are by far the noblest remains we have of this Writer, &amp; equal to most things extant in the Greek tongue:
					but it depends on your judgement to distinguish between his real &amp; occasional opinion of things, as he directly contradicts in one
					place what he has advanced in another, for example in the <hi rend="italic">Panathenaic</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="italic">De Pace,</hi>
					&amp;c: on the naval power of Athens: the latter of the two is undoubtedly his own undisguised sentiment.</p>
				     <p>Talk your fill to me, &amp; spare not. it would perhaps be more flattering, if you lived in the midst of an agreable society: but
					even as it is, I take it in good part, &amp; heartily thank you, for you have given me a late instance of your partiality &amp;
					kindness, that I shall ever remember. </p>
				     <p>I received on ye 10th of this month a long letter from Paris lively &amp; sensible as usual: but you will see it, &amp; I shall hope
					for a sight of such as you have got by you. there are two different directions. A Mons: M:r B: <hi rend="italic">a l'hotel de
						Luxembourg, rue des Petits Augustins, Fauxbourg St Germain, Paris.</hi> the other, to the same, <hi rend="italic">chez Messrs</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">Lullin, Freres, &amp; Rittiel, rue Thevenot, Paris.</hi>
					 the latter seems the safer, but then I am uncertain, whether I read it right. what shall I do? I
					have tried both ways, but do not know yet with what success.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Dear Sr, I am very faithfully<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
