<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (January  or February 1748)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/47</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>however, the MS is incomplete, it starts with "[…] this many Years before" and continues to the end of the postscript; the letter was first printed in full in Toynbee (1915)</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 144, vol. i, 294-303
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=144</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 168, vol. ii, 89-99
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:89</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 393-397
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 152-156
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:152</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. LXXXIV, vol. i, 182-190
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:182</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXX, vol. ii, 219-224
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:219</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXXVII, vol. iii, 88-95
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:88</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXXIII, vol. i, 172-177
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:172</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 34-42
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=34</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter IX, vol. i, 549-552
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:549</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0163">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" notBefore="1748-02"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Chute, John, 1701-1776</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Dodsley, Robert, 1703-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">West, Richard, 1716-1742</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Whalley, John, 1698 or 9-1748</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">[Tophet]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat, Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Ode on a Distant Prospect of Eton College</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">Ode on the Spring</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Montagu, Lady Mary Wortley</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Whitehead, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Tickell, Thomas</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Shenstone, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Seward, Thomas</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Rolle, Mr.</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Ridley, Glocester</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pre-Existence, a Poem</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pope, Alexander</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Nugent, Robert</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Melmoth, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Lyttelton, George Lyttelton, 1st Lord</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Lowth, Robert</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">King Dr. William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Johnson, Samuel</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Jenyns, Soame</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hervey, John Hervey, Lord</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Green, Matthew</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Evans, Dr. Abel</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dyer, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Duclos, Charles Pinot</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dryden, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dodsley, Robert, 1703-1764</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Browne, Isaac Hawkins</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Brown, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Bramston, James</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Boulainvilliers, Henri de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Aston, Hervey</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Addison, Joseph</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0163">
      <body>
         <p>I am obliged to you for Mr. Dodsley's book, and, having pretty well looked it over, will (as you
					desire) tell you my opinion of it. He might, methinks, have spared the Graces in his frontispiece, if
					he chose to be œconomical, and dressed his authors in a little more decent raiment – not in whited-brown paper and distorted
					characters, like an old ballad. I am ashamed to see myself; but the company keeps me in countenance:
					so to begin with Mr. Tickell. This is not only a statepoem (my ancient aversion), but a state-poem on
					the peace of Utrecht. If Mr. Pope had wrote a panegyric on it, one could hardly have read him with
					patience: but this is only a poor short-winded imitator of Addison, who had himself not above three or four notes in poetry; sweet
					enough indeed, like those of a German flute, but such as soon tire and satiate the ear with their frequent return. Tickell has added to
					this a great poverty of sense, and a string of transitions that hardly become a schoolboy. However, I forgive him for the sake of his
						ballad, which I always thought the prettiest in the world. All there is of M. Green here has been printed before: there is a profusion of wit every where; reading would have formed his
					judgment, and harmonized his verse, for even his wood-notes often break out into strains of real poetry and music. The
						Schoolmistress is excellent in its kind, and masterly; and (I am sorry to differ from you, but)
						London is to me one of those few imitations, that have all the ease and all the spirit of an
					original. The same man's verses at the opening of Garrick's theatre are far from bad. Mr. Dyer (here you will despise me highly) has more of poetry in his imagination, than almost any of our number; but
					rough and injudicious. </p>
         <p>I should range Mr. Bramston only a step or two above Dr. King,
					who is as low in my estimation as in yours. Dr. Evans is a furious madman; and Pre-existence is nonsense in all her altitudes. Mr. Lyttelton is a gentle elegiac
					person: Mr. Nugent sure did not write his own ode. I like Mr.
						Whitehead's little poems, I mean the Ode on a tent, the Verses to Garrick, and particularly those to
					Charles Townshend, better than any thing I had seen before of him. I gladly pass over H. Brown, and
					the rest, to come at you. You know I was of the publishing side, and thought your reasons against it none; for though, as Mr. Chute
					said extremely well, the <hi rend="italic">still small voice</hi> of Poetry was not made to be heard in a crowd; yet Satire will be
					heard, for all the audience are by nature her friends; especially when she appears in the spirit of Dryden, with his strength, and
					often with his versification; such as you have caught in those lines on the royal unction, on the papal dominion, and convents of both
					sexes, on Henry VIII. and Charles II. for these are to me the shining parts of your Epistle. There
					are many lines I could wish corrected, and some blotted out, but beauties enough to atone for a thousand worse faults than these. The
					opinion of such as can at all judge, who saw it before in Dr. Middleton's hands, concurs nearly with mine. As to what any one says,
					since it came out; our people (you must know) are slow of judgement; they wait till some bold body saves them the trouble, and then
					follow his opinion; or stay till they hear what is said in town, that is at some bishop's table, or some coffee-house about the Temple.
					When they are determined, I will tell you faithfully their verdict. As for the Beauties, I am their most humble servant. What shall I say to Mr. Lowth, Mr.
						Ridley, Mr. Rolle, the reverend Mr. Brown, Seward, &amp;c.? If I say, Messieurs! this is not the thing; write prose,
					write sermons, write nothing at all; they will disdain me, and my advice. What then would the sickly peer have done, that spends so much time in admiring everything that has four legs, and fretting at his own
					misfortune in having but two; and cursing his own politic head and feeble constitution, that won't let him be such a beast as he would
					wish? Mr. S. Jenyns now and then can write a good line or two – such as these –</p>
         <q>
            <p>Snatch us from all our little sorrows here, <lb/> Calm every grief, and dry each childish tear, &amp;c. </p>
         </q>
         <p>I like Mr. Aston Hervey's fable; and an ode (the last of all) by
					Mr. Mason, a new acquaintance of mine, whose Musæus too seems to carry with it the promise at least
					of something good to come. I was glad to see you distinguished who poor West was, before his charming ode, and called it anything rather than a Pindaric. The town is an owl, if it don't like Lady Mary, and I am surprised at it: we here are owls enough to think her eclogues
					very bad; but that I did not wonder at. Our present taste is sir T. Fitz-Osborne's Letters. I send
					you a bit of a thing for two reasons: first, because it is one of your favourites, Mr. M. Green; and
					next, because I would do justice. The thought on which my second ode turns is manifestly stole from
					hence: – not that I knew it at the time, but, having seen this many Years before, to be sure
					it imprinted itself on my Memory, &amp; forgetting the Author, I took it for my own. the Subject was the Queen's Hermitage.</p>
         <q>
            <p/>
            <p>Tho' yet no Palace grace the Shore <lb/> To lodge the Pair you should adore;<lb/> Nor Abbies
						great in Ruins rise, <lb/> Royal Equivalents for Vice: <lb/> Behold a Grott in Delphic Grove <lb/> The Graces &amp; the Muses love,
						<lb/> A Temple from Vain-Glory free; <lb/> Whose Goddess is Philosophy; <lb/> Whose Sides such licensed Idols crown,<lb/> As Superstition would pull down: <lb/> The only Pilgrimage I know, <lb/> That Men of Sense
						would chuse to go. <lb/> Wch sweet Abode, her wisest Choice, <lb/> Urania cheers with heavenly Voice: <lb/> While all the Virtues
						gather round <lb/> To see her consecrate the Ground. <lb/> If Thou, the God with winged Feet, <lb/> In Council talk of this
						Retreat; <lb/> And jealous Gods Resentment shew <lb/> At Altars raised to Men below: <lb/> Tell those proud Lords of Heaven, 'tis
						fit <lb/> Their House our Heroes should admit. <lb/> While each exists (as Poets sing) <lb/> A lazy, lewd, immortal, Thing: <lb/> They
						must, or grow in Disrepute, <lb/> With Earth's first Commoners recruit. <lb/> Needless it is in Terms unskill'd <lb/> To praise,
						whatever Boyle shall build. <lb/> Needless it is the Busts to name <lb/> Of Men, Monopolists of Fame; <lb/> Four Chiefs adorn the
						modest Stone <lb/> For Virtue, as for Learning, known. <lb/> The thinking Sculpture helps to raise <lb/> Deep Thoughts, the Genii
						of the Place: <lb/> To the Mind's Ear, &amp; inward Sight, <lb/> There Silence speaks, &amp; Shade gives Light: <lb/> While Insects
						from the Threshold preach, <lb/> And Minds disposed to Musing teach; <lb/> Proud of strong Limbs &amp; painted Hues <lb/> They
						perish by the slightest Bruise <lb/> Or Maladies begun within <lb/> Destroy more slow Life's frail Machine: <lb/> From Maggot-Youth
						thro' Change of State <lb/> They feel like us the Turns of Fate; <lb/> Some born to creep have lived to fly, <lb/> And changed
						Earth's Cells for Dwellings high: <lb/> And some, that did their six Wings keep, <lb/> Before they died, been forced to creep.
						<lb/> They Politicks, like ours, profess: <lb/> The greater prey upon the less. <lb/> Some strain on Foot huge Loads to bring,
						<lb/> Some toil incessant on the Wing: <lb/> Nor from their vigorous Schemes desist <lb/> Till Death; &amp; then are never mist.
						<lb/> Some frolick, toil, marry, increase, <lb/> Are sick &amp; well, have War &amp; Peace, <lb/> And broke with Age in half a Day
						<lb/> Yield to Successors, &amp; away. </p>
            <p/>
         </q>
         <p>
					 Please to tell Mr Chute, that I never borrow'd any Life of Mahomet (if that be his Meaning) having
					read Boulainvillers long ago: but that I have Du Clos' Louis Onze,
					&amp; will send it him, if you will be so good as to send me Directions both to Mr Whithed; &amp; Mr Chute (per se) at his Lodgeings,
					wch I would be glad to know for more Reasons than this. I hear Lamb-Pye is dead, &amp; could have
					wished to be told the Consequences: but both You &amp; He, I doubt, will grow to regard me in the Light of a <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Writer.</hi>
         </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am<lb/>Yours ever </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P:S: If You chance to see a Letter of mine in any body's Hand, this is the History of it. Dr Whalley, who has hated me ever since that Affair of Mr Turner, thought fit to intimate to a large Table
						full of People, that I was a Kind of Atheist. I wrote to him partly to laugh at, &amp; partly to reprove him for his Malice; &amp; (as
						what he said was publick) I shew'd my Letter to several of those, who had heard him; &amp; threaten'd (not in earnest, you may
						imagine) to have it hawk'd about Streets. they took me literally, &amp; by Way of Anticipation my Letter has been consign'd to one
							Etoffe (a Fiend of a Parson, that you know) to shew about here, &amp; to carry to Town, if any one
						will read it. he makes Criticisms on it, &amp; has found out a false Spelling, I'm told. Adieu! </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
