<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (15 January 1763)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 365, vol. ii, 791-793
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=365</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXXIX, 296-301
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:296</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 251-255
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:251</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXLVII, vol. iii, 1-4
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:1</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0418">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7029839">Aston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1763-01-15"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Dugdale, Sir William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Drake, Francis</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">York Minster</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0418">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Aston Jan: 15th 1763 </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I send you with this a drawing of the Ruin you were so much pleasd with when you saw it at York. I
					take it certainly to have been the Chapell of St Sepulchre founded by Archbishop Roger of wch
						Dugdale has given us the original Charta Fundationis. But as this opinion seems to contradict the
					opinion of Torre, &amp; of Drake too, who follows him, It is
					necessary to produce authentic Authority in proof of my Assertion. These two learned Antiquarys suppose that the Chapell in quæstion
						<hi rend="italic">ioind</hi> to the Minster. Thus Torre: 'Roger  ABp having built <hi rend="italic">against</hi> the great Church a Chapell.' &amp; Drake: 'Roger was buried in the Cathedral <hi rend="italic">near the door of</hi> St.
					Sepulchres chapel wch he himself had founded.' Vide Drake's Ebor: P. 478. P. 421. From these accts we should be led to conclude that
					this Chapell was as much and as close an appendage to the Minster as the Chapterhouse is. But the original records on wch they found
					this opinion May I think be construed very differently.</p>
         <p> ABp Roger himself in his Charta Fundationis describes its situation thus. 'Capellam quam–<hi rend="italic">juxta</hi> majorem
					Ecclesiam extruximus.' Juxta is surely <hi rend="italic">near</hi> only, not <hi rend="italic">adjoining</hi> and this ruin is <hi rend="italic">near</hi> enough. In the Extract of this ABps life from an antient MS wch Dugdale also gives us we find these words
					'Condidit etiam Capellam Sancti Sepulchri <hi rend="italic">ad Januam ipsius Palatii</hi> ex parte boreali ejusd. Eccles S. Petri.' The
					Ruin in quæstion might very probably be connected with the Pallace gate by a Cloyster of wch on one side there are a string of Arches
					remaining, and on the outside of the Minster over the little gate next the Tomb there are also vestiges of the roof of a Cloyster wch I
					imagine went asside the Pallace gateway &amp; connected the three buildings. Vide plan. But between this little gate &amp; the Pallace
					gate (which still remains) it is very evident there was no room for any thing but a Cloyster, for I dont think they are twenty yards
					asunder.</p>
         <p>The last and only further acct I can find of the situation is from the same Life. Where it is said The Canons of St Peter graviter
					murmurabant super situ dictæ capellæ eo quod <hi rend="italic">nimis adhæsit</hi> Matrici Ecclesiæ. This I think need not be translated
					litterally. the word nimis leads one to a metaphorical sense. The Preists of St Sepulchre were too near neighbours to St Peters Canons
					&amp; were troublesome to them, accordingly we find the ABp to quiet matters orderd that the Sacrist of his Chappel should make them a
					recompence, which is in this extract Stated.</p>
         <p>To These Arguments I would add that ABp Rogers donation was very great, (as we find in Drake) to this Chapell. and from the Number of
					Persons maintaind in its Service I quæstion not but there was a large Convent built round it, of wch there are plainly the foundations
					still to be seen. and what puts the matter out of all doubt that this building was seperate &amp; entire (tho indeed near to the
					Minster) is the following fact viz that the Tythes of the Chapell &amp; Chapell itself were sold to one Webster Ann: 4 Q Eliz. 'Capella
					vocat: St Sepulcres Chapell <hi rend="italic">prope</hi> Eccles: Cath Eborum cum decimis ejusdem. W. Webster. Ap: 4, Anno 4 Eliz.
					Rolls: Chap: Thus you see the <hi rend="italic">juxta</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">prope</hi> are clearly on my side the <hi rend="italic">nimis adhæsit</hi> is equivocal. I conclude with a rude Draught of the Platform according to my Idea, but without any
					mensuration &amp; merely to explain what has been said. I am with the greatest respect &amp; defference to your Sagacity.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>yours &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c </salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P.S. I ought to mention to you, that in the transept (I think you call it) of the Church namely at B there is at the top over the
						large Pillars, a range of Stonework like the windows in the ruin, viz three pointed arches under a circular one, but of a clumsey
						proportion. This part I think you said was the oldest in the Minster. Johny Ludlam found this out.
						perhaps it contradicts all Ive been saying &amp; proves the Building much older than Bp Roger.</p>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="/texts/letters/letters.0418.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
