<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (18 April 1770)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 212-213</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">224 mm x 184 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 519, vol. iii, 1125-1127
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=519</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter v, section v, 379-380
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:379</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXIII, vol. iii, 279-281
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:279</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, letter XI, vol. ii, 552-554
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:552</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section V, letter XI, vol. iv, 182-184
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:182</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLV, vol. ii, 166-167
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:166</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter V, vol. i, 471-472
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:471</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0597">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1770-04-18"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0597">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Thomas Wharton Esq of</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Old Park near</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Darlington</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>18 April 1770. </dateline>
					       <salute>My dear Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have been sincerely anxious for Miss Wharton, whose illness must have been indeed severe, if she is only now recovering. let us
					hope everything from the spring, wch begins (tho' slowly) to give new life to all things, &amp; pray give my best respects to her,
					&amp; thanks for remembring me &amp; my dictionary at a time, when she well may be excused for thinking of nothing but herself. </p>
				     <p>I have utterly forgot, where my journal left off, but (I think) it was after the account of <hi rend="italic">Gordale</hi> near Settle. if so, there was little more worth your notice: the principal things were <hi rend="italic">Wharldale</hi> in the way from Skipton to Ottley, &amp; <hi rend="italic">Kirstall-Abbey</hi> 3 mile from Leedes. the first is the
					valley form'd by the River Wharf, well-cultivated, well-inhabited, well-wooded, but with high rocky crags at distance, that border the
					green country on either hand: thro' the midst of it runs the river in long windings deep, clear, &amp; full to the brink, and of no
					inconsiderable breadth. how it comes to be so fine &amp; copious a stream here, &amp; at Tadcaster (so much lower) should have nothing
					but a wide stony channel with little or no water, I cannot tell you. <hi rend="italic">Kirstall</hi>
					 is a noble ruin in the Semi-Saxon style of building, as old as K: Stephen toward the end of his
					reign, 1152. the whole Church is still standing (the roof excepted) seated in a delicious quiet valley on the banks of the river <hi rend="italic">Are,</hi>
					 &amp; preserved with religious reverence by the Duke of Montagu.
					adjoining to the church between that &amp; the river are variety of chappels &amp; remnants of the abbey, shatter'd by the
					encroachments of the ivy, &amp; surmounted by many a sturdy tree, whose twisted roots break thro' the fret of the vaulting, &amp; hang
					streaming from the roofs. the gloom of these ancient cells, the shade &amp; verdure of the landscape, the glittering &amp; murmur of
					the stream, the lofty towers &amp; long perspectives of the Church, in the midst of a clear bright day, detain'd me for many hours
					&amp; were the truest subjects for my glass I have yet met with any where. as I lay at that smoky
					ugly busy town of Leedes, I drop'd all farther thoughts of my journal, &amp; after passing two days at Mason's (tho' he was
						absent) pursued my way by Nottingham, Leicester, Harborough, Kettering, Thrapston, &amp; Huntington
					to Cambridge, where I arrived, 22 Oct:, having met with no rain to signify, till this last day of my journey. there's luck for you!</p>
				     <p>I do think of seeing Wales this summer, having never found my spirits lower than at present, &amp;
					feeling that motion &amp; change of the scene is absolutely necessary to me. I will make Aston in my way to Chester, &amp; shall
					rejoice to meet you there the <hi rend="italic">last week in May;</hi>
					 Mason writes me word, that he wishes it, &amp; tho' his old house is down &amp; his new one not up,
					proposes to receive us like Princes in grain.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, my dear Sr &amp; believe me most faithfully yours,</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>My best compliments to Mrs Wharton &amp; the family. our weather till Christmas continued mild &amp; open. 28 Dec: some snow fell
						but did not lie. the 4th of Jan: was stormy &amp; snowy, wch was often repeated during that month, yet the latter half of it was warm
						&amp; gentle. 18 Feb: was snow again, the rest of it mostly fine. snow again on 15th March, from 23 to 30 March was cold &amp; dry, Wd
						E: or N:E:. on ye 31st rain. from thence till within a week past, Wd N:W: or N:E: with much hail &amp; sleet; &amp; on 4 Apr: a
						thunder-storm. it is now fine springweather.<lb/>
						         <lb/>
					       </p>
					       <table rend="frame">
						         <row>
							           <cell>1 March. </cell>
							           <cell>first violet appear'd. frogs abroad.  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>4 — </cell>
							           <cell>Almond blow'd, &amp; Gooseberry spread its leaves.  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>9 — </cell>
							           <cell>Apricot blow'd.  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>1 April. </cell>
							           <cell>Violets in full bloom, &amp; double Daffodils.  </cell>
						         </row>
						         <row>
							           <cell>5 — </cell>
							           <cell>Wren singing. double Jonquils.  </cell>
						         </row>
					       </table>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
