<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (12 September 1763)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
		                <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 376, vol. ii, 815-817
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=376</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 222, vol. ii, 215-219
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:215</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 125-129
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=125</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0429">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1763-09-12"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0429">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Pemb: Hall. Sept: 12. 1763. </dateline>
					       <salute>Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>W: Herbert's Book I can learn nothing about.<lb/>
					       <hi rend="italic">Milium</hi> Solis (with a single <hi rend="italic">l</hi>) is the Plant we call <hi rend="italic">Gromwell,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gray-mill,</hi> in Italian <hi rend="italic">Miglio del sole.</hi>
            <lb/>
					       <hi rend="italic">Antidotaries</hi> usually make a part of the old Dispensatories: for when Poisons were in fashion, Antidotes were
					equally so.
					<lb/> Joseph: Quercetanus publish'd a <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopœia Dogmaticorum restituta,</hi>
					1607. 4to. Paris:<lb/> Bricius Bauderonus.
					<hi rend="italic">Pharmacopœia, &amp; Praxis Medica.</hi> 1620. Paris.<lb/> Joannes Renadæus.
					<hi rend="italic">Dispensatorium Medicum, &amp; Antidotarium.</hi> 1609. 4to. Paris.<lb/> Valerius Cordus.
					<hi rend="italic">Dispensatorium.</hi> Antw: 1568.<lb/> Joannes Fernelius (Physician to Henry 2d of
					France, I think) <hi rend="italic">Opera Medicinalia, &amp; Universa Medicina.</hi> 1564. 4to, &amp; 1577. Fol:<lb/> Ludov:
						Mercatus (Physician to Philip 2d &amp; 3d of Spain) <hi rend="italic">Opera Medica &amp;
						Chirurgica.</hi> Fol: Francof: 1620.<lb/> Daniel Sennertus.
					<hi rend="italic">Institutiones Medicinæ.</hi> 1620.<lb/> Joannes Heurnius. (same title) 1597.
					Lugduni.</p>
				     <p>The word wanting is <hi rend="italic">Disease</hi> (I imagine). least <hi rend="italic">it</hi> (the making the body proof to any one
					distemper) should be thought to have made <hi rend="italic">it</hi> (the body) <hi rend="italic">no less than a prison to the
						soul,</hi>
					 wch would thereby have one way the less to escape from its confinement. this, you will say, is
					nonsense: that is not our fault, but my Ld Herberts, who had learnt from the Platonists.</p>
				     <p>
					       <hi rend="italic">Galeteus</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Il Galateo,</hi> a famous little work of Monsignor Giov: della Casa on the rules of Good-manners, that is, Good-breeding &amp; Behaviour.</p>
				     <p>What <hi rend="italic">St Islée</hi>
					 should be, I know not; &amp; you do not tell, in what part of France it seems to lie. <hi rend="italic">Alet</hi>
					 belong'd (I believe) to the Montmorencies; but it runs in my head, that they had an estate at St
						Hilaire: perhaps you may find in Sully's Memoirs. after all I guess, it is <hi rend="italic">Chantilly,</hi> wch was theirs.</p>
				     <p>
					       <hi rend="italic">Rees</hi>
					 lies in the Dutchy of Cleve very near Emerick.</p>
				     <p>Do I know any more Spanish than you? <hi rend="italic">Nó ay</hi> is what I doubt about: the rest should be <hi rend="italic">fuerça
						por las Reynas.</hi>
					
				     </p>
				     <p>The other bit of Spanish seems right, for <hi rend="italic">cada uno</hi> (so written separate) is <hi rend="italic">chacun,
						haga</hi> is <hi rend="italic">fasse,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Amo</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Maitre.</hi>
					
				     </p>
				     <p>I can not find <hi rend="italic">Tieleners</hi>
					 or any name like it in the list of Grotius' Friends or
					Correspondents. if any where, you will find it in Burigny's Life of him not long since publish'd,
					&amp; wch I conclude, you have.</p>
				     <p>If you are well &amp; good-humour'd, you will tell me a little news. how comes Ld Sh: to resign? is
					the tragical speech, that concluded a late conference, any thing like truth? the present times are so
					little like any thing I remember, that you may excuse my curiosity: besides I really interest myself in these transactions, &amp; can
					not persuade myself, that Quæ supra nos, nihil ad nos. I shall be in Town the middle of October, I believe.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am<lb/> Yours ever</salute>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
