<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (21 August 1755)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 73-74</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">204 mm x 163 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 205, vol. i, 433-434
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=205</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxiii, section iv, 244
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:244</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 179-183
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:179</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXIII, vol. i, 271-275
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:271</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XLVIII, vol. ii, 258-263
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:258</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LVI, vol. iii, 134-139
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:134</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XCI, vol. ii, 10-11
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:10</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0236">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1755-08-21"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0236">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton M:D:</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Kings-Arms Yard Coleman</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>22 AV</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Aug: 21. 1755. Stoke. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Doctor</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Instead of going to Twickenham I was obliged to send my excuses, &amp; the same day Mr. W: sent a
					messenger to say he was confined in Town with a Fever &amp; a Rash. he has since wrote me word, that
					he is well again; but for me I continue much as I was, &amp; have been but once out of the house to walk, since I return'd from
					Hampshire. being much inclined to bleeding myself, I yet was fearful to venture, least it should bring on a regular fit of the Gout, so
					I sent for advice at last, &amp; expected Dr Hayes should tell me presently, whether it were Gout or
					Rheumatism. in his talk he treated it rather as the former, but his prescription appears to me to be meant for the latter. you will
					judge. he took away 10 or 11 <hi rend="italic">Oz</hi> of blood, &amp; order'd these draughts night &amp; morning:–<hi rend="italic">Sal: Absinth. Succ: Limon. finitâ effervescentiâ add: Aqu: Alexit. Simpl:, Menth: Piperit, Magnes. alb., Tinct: G.
						Guiac. Spirituos.</hi> the quantities I can't read; only I think there is a Dram of the Tincture, &amp; ½ a Dram of Magnesia in each
					draught. the Blood had no sign of inflammation, but of a bright red: the Serum of a dark yellow with little transparency, not viscid to
					the touch. the draughts (wch I took over night only) made me sweat almost immediately, &amp; open'd a little in the morning. the
					consequence is, that I have still many slight complaints. broken &amp; unrefreshing sleeps, as before. less feverish than I was, in a
					morning: instead of it a sensation of weariness and soreness in both feet, wch goes off in the day. a frequent dizziness &amp;
					lightness of head. easily fatigued with motion. sometimes a little pain in my breast, as I had in the winter. these symptoms are all
					too slight to make an illness; but they do not make perfect health. that is sure. </p>
         <p>Tho' I allow abundance for your kindness &amp; partiality to me, I am yet much pleased with the good opinion you seem to have of the
						<hi rend="italic">Bard.</hi> you may alter that <hi rend="italic">Robed in the Sable,</hi> &amp;c,
					almost in your own words, thus <q>
               <p>With fury pale, &amp; pale with woe, <lb/> Secure of fate, the Poet stood &amp;c:</p>
            </q> Tho' <hi rend="italic">haggard,</hi> wch conveys to you the Idea of a <hi rend="italic">Witch,</hi> is indeed only a metaphor
					taken from an unreclaim'd Hawk, wch is call'd a <hi rend="italic">Haggard,</hi> &amp; looks wild &amp; <hi rend="italic">farouche</hi>
					&amp; jealous of its liberty. I have sent now Stonher a bit more of the <hi rend="italic">prophecy,</hi>
					 &amp; desire him to shew it you immediately: it is very rough &amp; unpolish'd at present.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, dear Sr, I am ever<lb/> Truly Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
