<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (28 June 1763)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 371, vol. ii, 801-802
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=371</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXXXII, 308-311
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:308</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLI, vol. iii, 10-12
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:10</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0424">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011995">York, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1763-06-28"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0424">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>York June 28th 1763 </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mr Gray </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Stonehewer tells me that you are returnd to Cambridge therefore I trust you are at leisure to read &amp; to answer my letter &amp; to
					tell me what is to be done about the Count &amp; his Coserelles. One can't thank him for them I think
					till one has recd them, and for my part I can only thank him in plain English whenever I do it. Pray write me your mind as to this
					matter.</p>
				     <p>You can't think what a favrite I am of Mr Bedingfeilds. I might have had an agate &amp; gold snuff-box from him the other day, &amp;
					why think you? only because I gave him an Etching of Mr Gray: Lord Sr, says I, would you repay me
					with a thing of this value for a thing not worth three halfpence. What (says he) a portrait of Mr Gray done by Mr Mason of no value!
					&amp;c &amp;c In short he presst me to accept it, till there was hardly any such thing as refusing, however, I refusd to the last, wch
					you will own to be miraculous when you consider my Avarice, my fondness for trinketts, &amp; when I tell you the Box was wonderful
					handsome &amp; withall had a french hinge. This said Gentleman is shortly going to leave York entirely without having resolvd in what
					other place to reside. to say the truth I am not displeas'd at this. for of all the Admirers I have had in my time, I think he would
					tire me the most was I to have much of him. He goes from hence to Norfolk first with his family &amp;
					that some time this next month, &amp; intends you a visit in his way. Get your Arm chair new stufft
					– No, the old stuffing will have more inspiration in it. I send you on the other page a Sonnet intended to be prefixt to my
						just volume (Gray Willing) It has I assure you cost me much pains, &amp; yet it is not yet what it
					should be, however I will do no more at it, till you have seen it, &amp; send me your opinion of it.</p>
				     <p>I have got about 10 Subscribers to Smart &amp; dont know how to transmit him the money. Stonehewer
					advises me to keep it, as he hears he is in somebodys hands who may cheat him. I have seen his Song to David &amp; from thence conclude him as mad as ever But this I mention only that one should endeavor to assist
					him as affectually as possible wch one cannot do without the mediation of a third person. If you know any body now in London (for
					Stonehewer has left it) whom I can write to on this subject pray tell me. Tis said in the papers he is prosecuting the people who
					confined him. if so, assisting him at present is only throwing ones money to the Lawyers. Give my
					Love to Mr Brown &amp; service to the College.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Yours most sincerely </salute>
					       <signed>W MASON. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <q>
						         <p>SONNET.
							<lb/>
						         </p>
						         <p>D'Arcy, to thee, whate'er of happier vein <lb/> Smit with the love of Song my youth
							essayd,<lb/> This verse devotes from that sequesterd shade <lb/> Where letterd Ease, thy gift, endears the scene. <lb/> Here, as
							the light-wing'd moments glide serene, <lb/> I arch the bower, or, thro the tufted glade, <lb/> In careless flow the simple pathway
							lead, <lb/> And strew with many a rose the shaven green. <lb/> So, to deceive my solitary days, <lb/> Pleas'd may I toil till
							Lifes vain vision end, <lb/> Nor own a wish beyond yon woodbine sprays; <lb/> Inglorious, not obscure, if D'Arcy lend <lb/> His
							wonted smile to these selected Lays; <lb/> The Muses patron, but the Poets friend. </p>
					       </q>
				     </postscript>
				     <closer>
					       <signed>W. M. </signed>
					       <dateline>Aston May 1763. July </dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
