<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (1 August 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 242, vol. ii, 511-512
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=242</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXI, 91-93
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:91</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXLIV, vol. i, 342-343
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:342</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0275">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1757-08-01"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0275">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Monday. Aug. 1. Stoke.</dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>If I did not send you a political letter forthwith, it was because Ld H: came in again so soon, that it was the same thing, as if he
					had never gone out: excepting one little circumstance indeed, the anger of old <hi rend="italic">Priam</hi>; wch (I am told) is the reason, that he has not the blue ribband, tho' promised him
						before. I have been here this month or more, low-spirited, &amp; full of disagreeablenesses, &amp; to
					add to them, am at this present very ill, not with the Gout, nor Stone (thank God) nor with blotches, nor blains, nor with frogs, nor
					lice, but with a painful infirmity, that has to me the charms of novelty, but would not amuse you much in the description. </p>
				     <p>I hope you divert yourself much better, than I do. you may be sure, Dodsley had orders to send you some Odes, the instant they were off the spit. indeed I forgot Mr Fraser; so I fear,
					they will come to Sheffield in the shape of a small parcel by some coach or waggon: but if there is time, I will prevent it. they had
					been out three weeks ago, but Mr W:, having taken it into his head to set up a Press of his own at Twickenham, was so earnest to
					handsel it with this new pamphlet, that it was impossible to find a pretence for refusing such a trifle. you will dislike this, as much
					as I do, but there is no help. you understand, it is he, that prints them not for me, but for Dodsley.
					I charge you send me some Caractacus, before I die. it is impossible, this weather should not bring
					him to maturity.</p>
				     <p>If you knew, how bad I was, you would not wonder, I could write no more.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, Dear Mason, I am ever most truly <lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
