<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (26 August 1766)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 51</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 422, vol. iii, 926-929
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=422</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter x, section v, 391-392
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:391</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXIII, vol. iii, 109-112
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:109</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXIII, vol. ii, 460-461
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:460</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXXIV, vol. iv, 65-67
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:65</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter II, vol. v, 60-62
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:60</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXIX, vol. ii, 105-106
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:105</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter X, vol. i, 482-483
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:482</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0477">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1766-08-26"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010052">Ripon, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0477">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Norton Nicholls Esq at Charles Floyers Esq of Hollinclose near Rippon Yorkshire</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Aug: 26. 1766. Pemb: Hall. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>It is long since that I heard you were gone in hast into Yorkshire on account of your Mother's
					illness, &amp; the same letter inform'd me, that she was recover'd. otherwise I had then wrote to you only to beg you would take care
					of her, &amp; to inform you, that I had discover'd a thing very little known, wch is, that in one's whole life one never can have any
					more than a single Mother. you may think this is obvious, &amp; (what you call) a trite observation. you are a green Gossling! I was at
					the same age (very near) as wise as you, &amp; yet I never discover'd this (with full evidence &amp; conviction, I mean) till it was
					too late. it is 13 years ago, &amp; seems but yesterday, &amp; every day I live it sinks deeper into my
						heart. many a corollary could I draw from this axiom for your use (not for my own) but I will leave
					you the merit of doing it yourself. pray, tell me how your own health is. I conclude it perfect, as I hear you offer'd yourself for a
					guide to Mr Palgrave into the Sierra-Morena of Yorkshire. for me I pass'd the end of May &amp; all June in Kent not disagreeably. the
					country is all a garden, gay, rich, &amp; fruitfull, &amp; (from the rainy season) had preserved, till I left it, all that emerald
					verdure, wch commonly one only sees for the first fortnight of the spring. in the west part of it from every eminence the eye catches
					some long winding reach of the Thames or Medway with all their navigation. in the east the sea breaks in upon you, &amp; mixes its
					white transient sails &amp; glittering blew expanse with the deeper &amp; brighter greens of the woods &amp; corn. this last sentence
					is so fine I am quite ashamed. but no matter! you must translate it into prose. Palgrave, if he heard
					it, would cover his face with his pudding-sleeve. I went to Margate for a day: one would think, it was Bartholomew Fair that had <hi rend="italic">flown</hi> down: From Smithfield to Kent in the London machine like my Lady Stuffdamask (to be sure you have read the New Bath Guide, the most fashionable of books) so then I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> go to Kingsgate, because it belong'd to my Ld Holland: but to Ramsgate I did, &amp; so to Sandwich &amp; Deal &amp; Dover
					&amp; Folkstone &amp; Hithe all along the coast very delightful. I do not tell you of the great &amp; small beasts &amp; creeping
					things innumerable that I met with, because you do not suspect, that this world is inhabited by any thing but Men &amp; Women, &amp;
					Clergy, &amp; such two-legged cattle. now I am here again very disconsolate &amp; all alone: even Mr Brown is gone, &amp; the cares of
					this world are coming thick upon me, I do not mean Children. you I hope are better off, riding &amp; walking with Mr Aislaby, singing Duets with my Cousin Fanny, improving with Mr Weddell, conversing with Mr Harry Duncomb. I must not wish for you here: besides I
					am going to Town at Michaelmas, by no means for amusement. do you remember, how we are to go into Wales next year? well!–Adieu, I am</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Sincerely Yours, </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Pray how does poor Temple find himself in his new situation? is Ld
							L: as good as his letters were? what is come of the Father &amp;
							Brother? Have you seen Mason?</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
