<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (21 November 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 75, vol. i, 129-131
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=75</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xii, section ii, 68-70
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:68</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 106, vol. i, 261-263
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:261</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XXVIII, vol. i, 46-47
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:46</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XII, vol. ii, 62-63
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:62</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XII, vol. ii, 73-75
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:73</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXX, vol. i, 63-65
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:63</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XII, vol. i, 194-195
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:194</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0085">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008546">Genoa, Italy</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-11-21"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">[Horridos tractus]</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Waller, Edmund</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Genoa</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0085">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Genoa, Nov. 21, 1739. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <q>
            <p>Horridos tractus, Boreæqb linquens<lb/> Regna Taurini fera, molliorem <lb/> Advehor brumam, Genuæqb amantes<lb/> Littora soles.
					</p>
         </q>
         <p>At least if they do not, they have a very ill taste; for I never beheld any thing more amiable. Only figure to yourself a vast
					semicircular bason, full of fine blue sea, and vessels of all sorts and sizes, some sailing out, some coming in, and others at anchor;
					and all round it palaces and churches peeping over one another's heads, gardens and marble terrases full of orange and cypress trees,
					fountains, and trellis-works covered with vines, which altogether compose the grandest of theatres.
					This is the first coup d'oeil, and is almost all I am yet able to give you an account of, for we arrived late last night. To-day was,
					luckily, a great festival, and in the morning we resorted to the church of the Madonna delle Vigne, to put up our little orisons; (I
					believe I forgot to tell you, that we have been sometime converts to the holy Catholic church) we found our Lady richly dressed out,
					with a crown of diamonds on her own head, another upon the child's, and a constellation of wax lights burning before them: Shortly
					after came the Doge, in his robes of crimson damask, and a cap of the same, followed by the Senate in black. Upon his approach began a
					fine concert of music, and among the rest two eunuchs' voices, that were a perfect feast to ears that had heard nothing but French
					operas for a year. We listened to this, and breathed nothing but incense for two hours. The Doge is a very tall, lean, stately, old
					figure, called Costantino Balbi; and the Senate seem to have been made upon the same model. They said
					their prayers, and heard an absurd white friar preach, with equal devotion. After this we went to the Annonciata, a church built by the
					family Lomellini, and belonging to it; which is, indeed, a most stately structure, the inside wholly marble of various kinds, except
					where gold and painting take its place. From hence to the Palazzo Doria. I should make you sick of marble, if I told you how it was
					lavished here upon the porticoes, the balustrades, and terrases, the lowest of which extends quite to the sea. The inside is by no
					means answerable to the outward magnificence; the furniture seems to be as old as the founder of the family. There great imbossed silver tables tell you, in bas-relief, his victories at sea; how he entertained the
					Emperor Charles, and how he refused the sovereignty of the Commonwealth when it was offered him; the rest is old-fashioned velvet
					chairs, and gothic tapestry. The rest of the day has been spent, much to our hearts' content, in cursing French music and architecture,
					and in singing the praises of Italy. We find this place so very fine, that we are in fear of finding nothing finer. We are fallen in
					love with the Mediterranean sea, and hold your lakes and your rivers in vast contempt. This is</p>
         <q>
            <p>'The happy country where huge lemons grow,'</p>
         </q>
         <p>as Waller says; and I am sorry to think of leaving it in a week for Parma, although it be</p>
         <q>
            <p>The happy country where huge cheeses grow.</p>
         </q>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
