<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Bentham (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> March 1765)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
		                <institution key="CAMB">Cambridge University Library</institution>
		                <repository>Department of Manuscripts and University Archives</repository>
		                <collection>Additional Manuscripts</collection>
		                <idno>Add. MSS 4251(B)563</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 399*, vol. ii, 862-866
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=399*</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gentleman's Magazine</title>, Apr. 1784, vol. liv, 244
			</bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 276-280
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:276</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, appendix III, vol. iii, 341-344
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:341</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXV, vol. ii, 464-467
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:464</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXXVI, vol. iv, 70-74
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:70</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0452">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1765-03"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/42192962">Bentham, James, 1708-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0452">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					
					       <salute>To the Rev. Mr. Bentham, </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Mr. Gray returns the papers and prints to Mr. Bentham, with many thanks for the sight of them.
				</p>
				     <p>Concludes, he has laid aside his intention of publishing the first four Sections of his Introduction, that contain the settlement and progress of Christianity among the Saxons: as (however curious and instructive in themselves) they
					certainly have too slight a connection with the subject in hand to make a part of the present work.</p>
				     <p>Has received much entertainment and information from his remarks on the state of Architecture among the Saxons, and thinks he has
					proved his point against the authority of Stow and Somner. The
					words of Eddius, Richard of Hexham, &amp;c., must be every where
					cited in the original tongue, as the most accurate translation is in these cases not to be trusted; this Mr. B. has indeed commonly
					done in the MSS. but not every where.</p>
				     <p>P. 31. He says, the instances Sir C. Wren brings were, <hi rend="italic">some of them at least,</hi> undoubtedly erected after the
					Conquest. Sure they were all so without exception.</p>
				     <p>There is much probability in what he asserts with respect to the <hi rend="italic">New Norman mode</hi> of building; though this is
					not, nor perhaps can be, made out with so much precision as the former point.</p>
				     <p>P. 35. Here, where the Author is giving a compendious view of the peculiarities that distinguish the Saxon style, it might be
					mentioned, that they had no tabernacles (or niches and canopies), nor any statues to adorn their buildings on the outside, which are
					the principal grace of what is called the Gothic; the only exception that I can recollect, is a
					little figure of Bishop Herebert Losing over the north transept door at Norwich, which appears to be
					of that time: but this is rather a mezzorelievo than a statue, and it is well known, that they used reliefs sometimes with profusion,
					as in the Saxon gateway of the abbey at Bury, the gate of the Temple Church at London, and the two gates at Ely, &amp;c.</p>
				     <p>The want of pinnacles, and of tracery in the vaults, are afterwards mentioned, but may as well be placed here too (in short), among
					the other characteristicks. </p>
				     <p>Escutcheons of arms are hardly (if ever) seen in these fabricks, which are the most frequent of all decorations in after-times. </p>
				     <p>P. 34. Beside the Chevron work (or zig-zag moulding) so common, which is here mentioned, there was also, </p>
				     <p>The <hi rend="italic">Billeted-moulding,</hi> as if a cylinder should be cut into small pieces of equal length, and these stuck on
					alternately round the face of the arches, as in the choir at Peterborough, and at St. Cross, &amp;c. </p>
				     <p>The <hi rend="italic">Nail-head,</hi> resembling the heads of great nails driven in at regular distances, as in the nave of old St.
					Paul's, and the great tower of Hereford, &amp;c.</p>
				     <p>The <hi rend="italic">Nebule,</hi> a projection terminated by an undulating line as under the upper range of windows on the outside
					at Peterborough.</p>
				     <p>Then to adorn their vast massive columns there was the <hi rend="italic">Spiral-Groove</hi> winding round the shafts, and the <hi rend="italic">Net,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lozenge-work,</hi> overspreading them; both of which appear at Durham, and the first in
					the undercroft at Canterbury.</p>
				     <p>These few things are mentioned only, because Mr. Bentham's work is so nearly compleat in this part, that one would wish it were quite
					so. His own observation may doubtless suggest to him many more peculiarities, which, however minute in appearance, are not
					contemptible, because they directly belong to his subject, and contribute to ascertain the age of an edifice at first sight. The great
					deficiency is from Henry VIth's time to the Reformation, when the art was indeed at its height. </p>
				     <p>P. 36. At York, under the choir, remains much of the old work, built by Archbishop Roger, of
					Bishop's-bridge, in Henry IId's reign; the arches are but just pointed, and rise on short round pillars, whose capitals are adorned
					with animals and foliage.</p>
				     <p>P. 37. Possibly the pointed arch might take its rise from those arcades we see in the early Norman (or Saxon) buildings on walls,
					where the wide semicircular arches cross and intersect each other, and form thereby at their intersection exactly a narrow and
					sharp-pointed arch. In the wall south of the choir at St. Cross, is a facing of such wide, round, interlaced arches by way of ornament
					to a flat vacant space; only so much of it as lies between the legs of the two neighbouring arches, where they cross each other, is
					pierced through the fabrick, and forms a little range of long pointed windows. It is of King Stephen's time. </p>
				     <p>P. 43. As Mr. B. has thought it proper to make a compliment to the <hi rend="italic">present set of Governors</hi> in their
					respective churches; it were to be wished he would insert a little reflection on the rage of repairing, beautifying, whitewashing,
					painting, and gilding, and (above all) the mixture of Greek (or Roman) ornaments in Gothic edifices. This well-meant fury has been and
					will be little less fatal to our ancient magnificent edifices, than the reformation and the civil wars. </p>
				     <p>Mr. G. would wish to be told (at Mr. Bentham's leisure), whether over the great pointed arches, on which the Western Tower at Ely
					rises, any thing like a semicircular curve appears in the stone work? and whether the screen (or rood-loft) with some part of the
					South-Cross, may not possibly be a part of the more ancient church built by Abbot Simeon and
						Fitz-Gilbert?
				</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
