<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mary Antrobus (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> December 1765)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="ROBA">Rosenbach Museum &amp; Library</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 418*, vol. ii, 908-909
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=418*</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0473">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1765-12"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29394522">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0473">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <salute> Dear Molly </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I am almost afraid of advising you for fear I should hurt, where I mean to serve you.</p>
				     <p> I think M<hi rend="super">r</hi> M: &amp; your Friends in Town mean exceedingly well, &amp; deserve your acknowledgements: but when
					they propose this method of proceeding, they are ignorant of what has passed.</p>
				     <p> I entirely approve of your answer in every respect, as it is. what if you added to it, (as in confidence to M<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					M:,) that a Friend of yours had found means to recommend you not long since to the two Lords at the head of that Board, &amp; had
					received a very favourable answer in case of your Mamma's death. that you have reason to believe, there was nobody before you on their
					list, &amp; that they would not easily give ear to any applications made to your prejudice.</p>
				     <p> That nevertheless you were conscious, many accidents might arise to disappoint these hopes; &amp; fully sensible of how much
					consequence the kind foresight &amp; assistance of the M<hi rend="super">r</hi> P:<hi rend="super">s</hi> may be to you in all senses;
					&amp; that you therefore did desire M<hi rend="super">r</hi> M: would communicate your letter (if he thinks it proper) to them, &amp;
					entreat the continuance of their favourable intentions to you &amp; to your Sister.</p>
				     <p> This you will put into your own style (w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is always best) but before you do so, consider whether it agree
					with your own sentiments, &amp; whether you foresee any ill, that may arise from it, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> does not occur to me:
					for my notion is, that generally People judge best upon due reflection in their own affairs.</p>
				     <p> I will see you after dinner.</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
