<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (13 January 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 262, vol. ii, 550-552
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=262</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XXX, 125-130
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:125</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 197-200
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:197</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CLX, vol. ii, 12-15
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:12</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0301">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1758-01-13"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0301">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Jan: 13. 1758. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mason </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Why you make no more of writing an Ode, &amp; throwing it into the fire, than of buckling and unbuckling your shoe. I have never read
						Keysler's book, nor you neither I believe: if you had taken that pains, I am persuaded you would have
					seen that his Celtic &amp; his Septentrional antiquities are two things entirely distinct. there are indeed some learned Persons, who
					have taken pains to confound, what Cæsar &amp; Tacitus have taken pains to separate, the old druidical or Celtic belief, &amp; that of
					the old Germans. but nobody has been so <hi rend="italic">learned</hi> as to mix the Celtic religion with that of the Goths. why, Woden
					himself is supposed not to have been older than Julius Cæsar; but let him have lived, when he pleases, it is certain that neither he,
					nor his <hi rend="italic">Valhalla,</hi> were heard of, till many ages after. this is the doctrine of the <hi rend="italic">Scalds,</hi> not of the Bards. these are the songs of Hengist &amp; Horsa, a modern new-fangled belief in comparison of that, wch you
					ought to profess. after all I shall be sorry to have so many good verses &amp; good chimæras thrown away. might we not be permitted (in
					that scarcity of Celtic Ideas we labour under) to adopt some of these foreign whimsies, dropping however all mention of Woden, &amp;
					his Valkhyrian Virgins, &amp;c: to settle this scruple of conscience I must refer you to Dr Warburton. if this should be his opinion,
					(wch I doubt) then I go on to tell you, (first premising that a <hi rend="italic">dirge</hi> is always a funeral service sung over
					persons already dead) that I would have something striking &amp; uncommon in the measures, the rhythm, &amp; the expression of this
					chorus. the two former are not remarkable here, &amp; the third is so little antiquated, that <hi rend="italic">murky &amp; dank</hi>
					look like two oldmaids of honour got into a circle of fleering girls &amp; boys. now for particulars; I like the first Stanza, the
					Image of Death in arms is very fine, &amp; gallant, but I banish <hi rend="italic">fre-born</hi> train, &amp; <hi rend="italic">glory
						&amp; luxury</hi> here (not the ideas, but the words) &amp; <hi rend="italic">Liberty, &amp; Freedom's</hi> cause, &amp; several <hi rend="italic">small</hi> epithets throughout. I do not see how one Person can <hi rend="italic">lift</hi> the voice of another Person.
					the imagery of the second Stanza too is excellent. a Dragon <hi rend="italic">pecks,</hi> why a Cock-Sparrow might do as much! in short
					I am pleased with the Gothic Elysium; don't think I am ignorant about either that or the <hi rend="italic">Hell</hi> before, or the <hi rend="italic">twilight.</hi> I have been there &amp; have seen it all in <hi rend="italic">Mallet's Introduction to the history of
						Denmark</hi> (it is in French) &amp; many other places. <hi rend="italic">Now they charge</hi>
					&amp;c: looks, as if the <hi rend="italic">Coursers</hi> rode upon the Men. a <hi rend="italic">Ghost</hi> does not <hi rend="italic">fall.</hi> these are all my little objections, but I have a greater. extreme conciseness of expression, yet pure, perspicuous, &amp;
					musical, is one of the grand beauties of lyric poetry. this I have always aim'd at, &amp; never could attain. the necessity of rhyming
					is one great obstacle to it: another &amp; perhaps a stronger is that way you have chosen of casting down your first Ideas carelessly
					&amp; at large, and then clipping them here &amp; there and forming them at leisure. this method after all possible pains will leave
					behind it in some places a <hi rend="italic">laxity,</hi> a diffuseness. the frame of a thought (otherwise well invented, well-turned,
					&amp; well-placed) is often weaken'd by it. do I talk nonsense? or do you understand me? I am persuaded, what I say, is true <hi rend="italic">in my head,</hi> whatever it may be in <hi rend="italic">prose,</hi> for I do not pretend to write prose.</p>
         <p>I am extremely pleased with your fashionable Ode, &amp; have nothing to find fault with there (only
					you must say <hi rend="italic">portray' st</hi>
					 in the first Stanza; &amp; It <hi rend="italic">looks</hi> at best but skin, in the 4th, is not right) I have observed your orders, but I want to shew it every body. pray, tell me, when
					I may have the credit of doing so. I have never seen a prettier <hi rend="italic">modernism:</hi> let it be seen, while it is
						warm. you are in the road to fame, but don't tell your name at first, whatever you may venture to do
					afterwards.</p>
         <p>Fobus is a treat: desire Ld —sse to kiss him on both ears for me. I forgive Ld B. for taking the <hi rend="italic">Tudors</hi> for the Restauration. Adieu, dear M:n &amp; remember me.
					remember too, that I have neither company, nor pleasure, nor spirits here, &amp; that a letter from you stands in the place of all
					these.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!</salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>So you have christen'd Mr. Dayrolle's Child, &amp; my Lady
							Y:, they say. oh brave Dupp: how comes he to be the Ch: of the
						Ex:r? what is going to be now? </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
