<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (10 December 1760)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 327, vol. ii, 713-717
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=327</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXI, 232-240
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:232</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 241-244
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:241</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXIV, vol. ii, 178-186
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:178</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0377">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1760-12-10"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0377">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>It is not good to give copies of a thing, before you have given it the last hand. if you would send
					it to Ld H:, you might have spared that to Lady M: C:; they have
					both shew'd it to particular friends, &amp; so it is half-publish'd before it is finish'd. I begin again from the beginning</p>
				     <p>Ah mark) is rather languid. I would read <hi rend="italic">Heard ye?</hi>
				     </p>
				     <p>V: 3.) I read: and now <hi rend="italic">with</hi> rising knell. to avoid two <hi rend="italic">the</hi>'s.</p>
				     <p>V: 10.) I read, – since now <hi rend="italic">that</hi> bloom &amp;c:</p>
				     <p>V: 11, 12.) Are alter'd for the better, &amp; so are the following, but for <hi rend="italic">Liquid Light'ning,</hi> Ld J: C: says, there is a Dram, wch goes by that name; &amp; T: G: adds, that the words are stolen from a Sonnet of
					the late Prince of Wales's. what if we read liquid <hi rend="italic">radiance,</hi> &amp; change the
					word <hi rend="italic">radiant</hi> soon after?</p>
				     <p>V: 18. Read, <hi rend="italic">That</hi> o'er her form &amp;c:</p>
				     <p>V: 23. Cease, <hi rend="italic">cease, Luxuriant Muse;</hi> tho' mended, it is still weakly. I do not much care for any Muse at all
					here.</p>
				     <p>V: 26. <hi rend="italic">Mould'ring</hi> is better than <hi rend="italic">clay-cold.</hi> somewhat else might be better perhaps than
					either.</p>
				     <p>V: 35. <hi rend="italic">Whirl you in her wild career.</hi> this image does not come in so well here between two real happinesses.
					the word <hi rend="italic">lead</hi> before it, as there is no epithet left to <hi rend="italic">purple,</hi> is a little faint.</p>
				     <p>Of her <hi rend="italic">choicest</hi> stores an <hi rend="italic">ampler</hi> share, seems to me prosaick.</p>
				     <p>
					       <hi rend="italic">Zenith-height</hi> is harsh to the ear, &amp; too scientific.</p>
				     <p>I take it the interrogation-point comes after <hi rend="italic">fresh delight,</hi> &amp; there the sense ends. if so, the Question
					is too long in asking, &amp; leaves a sort of obscurity.</p>
				     <p>V: 46. I understand, but can not read this line. does <hi rend="italic">tho' soon</hi> belong to <hi rend="italic">lead her
						hence,</hi> or to, <hi rend="italic">the Steps were slow</hi>? I take it, to the latter; &amp; if so, it is hardly Grammar. if to the
					former, the end of the line appears very naked without it.</p>
				     <p>V: 55. <hi rend="italic">Rouse</hi> then – <hi rend="italic">his voice pursue.</hi> I do not like this broken line.</p>
				     <p>V: 74. <hi rend="italic">Firm as</hi> the Sons – that is, <hi rend="italic">as firmly as.</hi> the adjective used for the
					adverb here gives it some obscurity, &amp; has the appearance of a contradiction.</p>
				     <p>V: 76. A less metaphorical line would become this place better. </p>
				     <p>V: 80. This, tho' a good line, would be better too, if it were more simple, for the same figure is amplified in the following Stanza,
					&amp; there is no occasion for anticipating it here. </p>
				     <p>V: 85. <hi rend="italic">And why</hi> – I do not understand. you mean, I imagine, that the Warrior must not expect to
					establish his fame, as a Heroe, while he is yet alive. but how does <hi rend="italic">living Fame</hi> signify this? the construction
					too is not good, if you mean, <hi rend="italic">with regard to Fame, while he yet lives, Fate denies him that.</hi> the next line is a
					bold expression of Shakespear. the 3d, <hi rend="italic">E'er from her trump–heav'n breath'd</hi>–is not good.</p>
				     <p>V: 89. <hi rend="italic">Is it the grasp</hi> – You will call me a Coxcomb, if I remind you, that this stanza in the turn of
					it is too like a stanza of <hi rend="italic">another body's.</hi>
					
				     </p>
				     <p>V: 98. <hi rend="italic">Truth ne'er can sanctify</hi> – is an indifferent line. both Mr Brown &amp; I have some doubt about
					the justness of this sentiment. a Kingdom is purchased (we think) too dear with the life of any Man; &amp; this no less, if there <hi rend="italic">be a life hereafter,</hi> than if there be none.</p>
				     <p>V: 102. We say, the juice of the grape <hi rend="italic">mantles,</hi> but not the grape.</p>
				     <p>V: 107. By earth's poor pittance–will not do. the end is very well, but the whole is rather too long, &amp; I would wish it
					reduced a little in the latter part. <lb/>
         </p>
				     <p>I am sorry you went so soon out of Town, because you lost your share in his Majesty's reproof to his Chaplains. 'I desire, <hi rend="italic">those Gentlemen</hi> may be told, that I come here to praise God, &amp; not to hear my own praises.' Kitt Wilson was (I think) the Person, that had been preaching. this, &amp; another thing I have been told, give me
					great hopes of the young Man. Fobus was asking him, what Sum it was his pleasure should be laid out on the next Election? Nothing, my
					Lord (the Duke stared, &amp; said, Sr!) Nothing, I say, my Ld: I desire to be tried by my Country.
				</p>
				     <p>There has been as great confusion this week, as if the French were landed. you see, the Heads of the Tories are invited into the
						bed-chamber, &amp; Mr P: avows it to be his advice, not as to the
					particular Men, but the measure. Fobus knew nothing of it, till it was done, &amp; has talked loudly for two days of resigning; Ld H:k &amp; his People say, they will support the whig-interest, as if
					all was going to ruin, &amp; they hoped to raise a party. what will come of it, is doubtful; but I fancy, they will acquiesce, &amp;
					stay in as long as they can. great confusion in the army too about Ld Fitzmaurice, who is put over
					the head of Ld G: Lenox, Mr Fitzroy, &amp; also of almost all the
					American Officers.
				</p>
				     <p>I have seen Mr Southwell, &amp; approve him much. he has got many new tastes &amp; knowledges,
					&amp; is no more a cockscomb than when he went from hence. I am glad to hear you bode so well of Ponsonby &amp; his Tutor. here is a delightful new Woman in the Burlettas, the rest is all
					Bartholomew &amp; his Fair. Elisi has been ill eversince he came, &amp; has not sung yet.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, I am truly<lb/> Yours. </salute>
					       <dateline>London, at Mr Jauncy's,
						<hi rend="italic">not Jenours.</hi>
               <lb/> Dec: 10. 1760. </dateline>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
