<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (30 July 1756)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 220, vol. ii, 470-473
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=220</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XV, 53-56
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:53</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXXII, vol. i, 303-305
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:303</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0251">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1756-07-30"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0251">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>The Revd William Mason</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>at the Right Hon<hi rend="super">ble</hi> the Earl of Holderness's</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>in Arlington Street</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>London</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>31 IY</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>July 30. Friday. 1756. <lb/> Stoke </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I received your Letters both at once yesterday which was Thursday, such is the irregularity of our
					Post. the affair of Southwell at this time is exceedingly unlucky. if it is committed to you, by all
					means defer it. it is even worth while to stop Mrs Southwell, who will enter into the reason of it.
					another thing is, you have very honestly &amp; generously renounced your own interest (I mention it not as a compliment, but <hi rend="italic">pour la rareté du fait</hi>) to serve Mr B:; but what if you might serve him still better by seemingly making interest
					for yourself. Addison must certainly be a Competitor. he will have
					the old (new) Ld Walpole of Wolterton, his Patron, to back him, the Bp of Chester, the Heads, who know him for a staunch Man, &amp;
					consequently the D: of N:. if you can divide or carry this interest, &amp; by it gain the dirty part of the College, so as to throw it
					into Mr B:s scale at pleasure, perhaps it may produce an unanimous election. this struck me last night as a practicable thing. but I
					see some danger in it. for you may disoblige your own friends, &amp; Ld H: must, I doubt, be acquainted with your true design, who very
					likely will not come into it. T: also &amp; Mr B: himself should be acquainted with it immediately.
					consider therefore well, whether this or the plain open way (wch, I own, is commonly the best) be most likely to succeed. the former,
					if it be found impracticable for Mr B: at last, may make it sure for yourself, wch is to be wish'd in the next place. it is odd to talk
					thus to a Man about himself, but I think, I know to whom I am talking. I have puzzled my head about a list of the College, &amp; can
					make out only these. pray, supply it for me. </p>
				     <list>
					       <item>– Brown May</item>
					       <item>– Bedford</item>
					       <item>– Tuthill</item>
					       <item>Forester</item>
					       <item>– Delaval</item>
					       <item>– Gaskarth</item>
					       <item>– Cardale</item>
					       <item>– Milbourne</item>
					       <item>– Spencer</item>
					       <item>Mapletoft</item>
					       <item>– Axton</item>
				     </list>
				     <p>I don't know, if Spencer's Fell:p be vacant or not. nor whether a majority only of the whole, or two thirds, be required to chuse a
						master.
				</p>
				     <p>I should hope 9 of these, &amp; perhaps Mapletoft too, if Gaskarth pleases, might be got for Mr B:,
					but I can answer only for T: Bedford has always profess'd a friendship for Mr B:, but he is a queer man. his Patron is a Mr Buller of
						Cornwall a Tory. Delaval, Gask:th, Milbourne &amp; Axton you may soon enquire into yourself. Spencer
					(if he is one) has promised Dr. Wharton.</p>
				     <p>I write to Mr. W: (your Neighbour over the way) to desire him to speak to Mr. F: or the D: of B:d, if it may be of use; &amp; add, that if he will let you
					know, he is at home, you will come, &amp; give him any information necessary. whether this will signify I can't say, but I do not see
					any hurt it can do.</p>
				     <p>I wish, like you, I were at Camb:; but to hurry down on this occasion would be worse, than useless, according to my conception. I am
					glad you think of going, if they approve it. Dr L:, if he is not
					dead, will recover. mind, if he don't.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I leave my answer to your first Letter to another opportunity, &amp; am always<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
