<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (23 September 1766)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 53</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 425, vol. iii, 935-936
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=425</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter i, section v, 343-345
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:343</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXVI, vol. iii, 119-120
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:119</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, letter II, vol. ii, 511-512
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:511</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section V, letter II, vol. iv, 130-132
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:130</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter III, vol. v, 63-64
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:63</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLI, vol. ii, 129-131
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:129</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section V, letter I, vol. i, 441-443
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:441</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0480">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1766-09-23"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010052">Ripon, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0480">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Norton Nicholls Esq at Hollin-close Hall near Rippon Yorkshire</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>SAFFRON WALDEN 24 SE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>My dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I was absent in Suffolk, &amp; did not receive your melancholy letter till my return hither
					yesterday: so you must not attribute this delay to me, but to accident. to sympathize with you in such a loss is an easy task for me: but to comfort you not so easy. can I wish to see you unaffected with the sad scene
					now before your eyes, or with the loss of a person, that thro' a great part of your life has proved himself so kind a Friend to you? he
					who best knows our nature (for he made us, what we are) by such afflictions recalls us from our wandering thoughts &amp; idle
					merriment, from the insolence of youth &amp; prosperity, to serious reflection, to our duty &amp; to himself: nor need we hasten to get
					rid of these impressions; Time (by appointment of the same Power) will cure the smart, &amp; in some hearts soon blot out all the
					traces of sorrow: but such as preserve them longest (for it is left partly in our own power) do perhaps best acquiesce in the will of
					the Chastiser. </p>
         <p>For the consequences of this sudden loss I see them well, &amp; (I think) in a like situation could
					fortify my mind so as to support them with chearfulness &amp; good hopes, tho' not naturally inclined to see things in their best
					aspect. your Cousins seem naturally kind &amp; well-disposed worthy young People: your Mother &amp;
					they will assist one another. you too (when you have time to turn you round) must think seriously of your profession. you know I would have wish'd to see you wear the livery of it long ago. but I will not dwell on this subject
					at present. to be obliged to those we love &amp; esteem is a pleasure: but to serve &amp; to oblige them is a still greater, &amp; this
					with independence (no vulgar blessings) are what a Profession at your age may reasonably promise. without it they are hardly
					attainable. remember, I speak from experience!</p>
         <p>Poor Mr. W: is struck with a paralytick disorder. I know it only from the papers, but think it very
					likely. he may live in this state, incapable of assisting himself, in the hands of servants or relations, that only gape after his
					spoils, perhaps for years to come. think, how many things may befall a man far worse than death.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I sincerely wish your happiness, &amp; am<lb/> Faithfully Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
            <dateline>Pemb: C: Sept: 23. 1766. </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P:S: I must go soon to London: but if you direct to me here, I shall have your letters. let me know soon, how you go on. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
