<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Richard West to Thomas Gray (5 May 1742)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 106, vol. i, 200-201
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=106</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter vii, section iii, 146-148
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:146</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 148, vol. ii, 37-39
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:37</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section II, letter no. 39, 164-166
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:164</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section III, letter VII, vol. ii, 134-135
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:134</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section III, letter VII, vol. ii, 160-162
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:160</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LV, vol. i, 123-125
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:123</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section III, letter VII, vol. i, 264-266
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:264</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0122">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown">Pope's, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1742-05-05"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0122">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Popes, May 5, 1742 </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>Without any preface I come to your verses, which I read over and over with excessive pleasure, and
					which are at least as good as Propertius. I am only sorry you follow the blunders of Broukhusius, all
					whose insertions are nonsense. I have some objections to your antiquated words, and am also an enemy to Alexandrines; at least I do not
					like them in Elegy. I like your Elegy extremely, so extremely, that I long to shew you some little errors you are fallen into by
					following Broukhusius: for example, your thirty first lines are most intelligibly soft and pretty: but pray what sense do you affix to
					your six Broukhusian lines, that begin at happy youth and end at – let me die? [...] Were I
					with you now, and Propertius with your verses lay upon the table between us, I could discuss this point in a moment; but there is
					nothing so tiresome as spinning out a criticism in a letter; doubts arise, and explanations follow, till there swells out at least a
					volume of undigested observations: and all because you are not with him whom you want to convince. Read only the letters between Pope
					and Cromwell in proof of this; they dispute without end. Are you aware now that I have an interest all
					this while in banishing Criticism from our correspondence? Indeed I have; for I am going to write down a little Ode (if it deserves the
					name) for your perusal, which I am afraid will hardly stand that test. Nevertheless I leave you at your full liberty; so here it
					follows.</p>
         <q>
            <p>ODE.</p>
            <p>Dear Gray, that always in my heart <lb/> Possessest far the better part, <lb/> What mean these sudden blasts that rise <lb/> And
						drive the Zephyrs from the skies? <lb/> O join with mine thy tuneful lay, <lb/> And invocate the tardy May. </p>
            <p>Come, fairest Nymph, resume thy reign! <lb/> Bring all the Graces in thy train! <lb/> With balmy breath, and flowery tread, <lb/>
						Rise from thy soft ambrosial bed; <lb/> Where, in elysian slumber bound, <lb/> Embow'ring myrtles veil thee round. </p>
            <p>Awake, in all thy glories drest, <lb/> Recall the Zephyrs from the west; <lb/> Restore the sun, revive the skies, <lb/> At mine,
						and Nature's call, arise! <lb/> Great Nature's self upbraids thy stay, <lb/> And misses her accustom'd May. </p>
            <p>See! all her works demand thy aid; <lb/> The labours of Pomona fade: <lb/> A plaint is heard from ev'ry tree; <lb/> Each budding
						flow'ret calls for thee; <lb/> The Birds forget to love and sing; <lb/> With storms alone the forests ring. </p>
            <p>Come then, with Pleasure at thy side, <lb/> Diffuse thy vernal spirit wide; <lb/> Create, where'er thou turn'st thy eye, <lb/>
						Peace, Plenty, Love, and Harmony; <lb/> Till ev'ry being share its part, <lb/> And Heav'n and Earth be glad at heart.</p>
         </q>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
