<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (2 September 1760)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>tipped into a copy of Bentley's <hi rend="it">Designs</hi>; a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 320, vol. ii, 696-703
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=320</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 239-241
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:239</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 215, vol. ii, 186-206
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:186</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, appendix II, vol. iii, 325-341
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:325</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, vol. v, 199-216
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:199</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 107-116
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=107</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0369">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1760-09-02"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0369">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Cambr: Sept: 2. 1760. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>My Enquiries, &amp; the Information I am able to give you in consequence of them, are as follows: if they amount to but little, thank
					yourself for applying to a sucking Antiquary. </p>
         <p>Mr. Vertue's Mss (as I do not doubt, you have experienced) will often put you on a false scent. be
					assured, that Occleve's portrait of Chaucer is not, nor ever was in St John's Library: they have a
					Mss of the Troilus &amp; Cressida without illuminations, &amp; no other part of his works. in the University Library indeed there is a
					large volume with most of his works on vellum, &amp; by way of frontispiece is (pasted in) a pretty old print taken (as it says) by Mr Speed from Occleve's original painting in the <hi rend="italic">book De Regimine
						Principum.</hi>
					 in the middle is Chaucer, a whole length; the same countenance, attitude, &amp; dress, that Vertue
					gives you in the two heads, wch he has engraved of him. the border is composed of escutcheons of arms, all the alliances of the Chaucer
					Family, &amp; at bottom the tomb of Thomas Chaucer &amp; Maud Burghersh at Ewelm. the print &amp; all
					the arms are neatly colour'd. I only describe this, because I never took notice of such a print any where else, tho' perhaps you may
					know it; for I suppose it was done for some of Speed's Works. about the painting I have a great
					puzzle in my head between Vertue, Mr. D'urry, &amp; Bishop Tanner.
					Vertue (you know) has twice engraved Chaucer's head, once for D'urry's edition of his works, &amp; a second time in the Set of Poet's
					Heads. both are done from Occleve's painting: but he never tells us, where he found the painting, as he generally uses to do. D'urry
					says, there is a portrait of Chaucer (doubtless a whole length, for he describes his <hi rend="italic">port &amp; stature</hi> from
					it), in possession of <hi rend="italic">George Greenwood, Esq.</hi> of Chastleton in Gloucestershire. a little after he too mentions
					the picture by Occleve, but whether the same, or not, does not appear. Tanner in his Bibliotheca,
					(Artic: Chaucer, see the notes) speaks of Occleve's painting too, but names another work of his (not the De Regim. Principum) &amp; adds, that it is in <hi rend="italic">the King's Library at Westminster</hi>: if so, you will
					certainly find it in the Museum, &amp; Casley's Catalogue will direct you to the place.</p>
         <p>Of the Profile of Dr Keys there is only a Copy in his College: but there is a Portrait of him (not
					in profile) a good picture, &amp; undoubtedly original, a half-figure upon board, dated Anno 1563, æt. suæ 53. There are 14 Latin
					verses inscribed on it, containing a character of him, as a Scholar &amp; excellent Physician, &amp; thus much more</p>
         <q>
            <p>Qui Cantabrigiæ Gonvilli incæpta minuta <lb/> auxit, &amp; e parvo nobile fecit opus; <lb/> Et qui Mausoleum Linacro donavit in
						æde, <lb/> quæ nunc de Pauli nomine nomen habet, &amp;c: <lb/> Talis erat Caius, qualem sub imaginis umbrâ <lb/> Pæne hic viventem
						picta tabella refert. </p>
         </q>
         <p>At the corners is written Vivit Virtus, &amp; Virtus Vivit, <hi rend="italic">but no Painter's name.</hi> in the same room hangs an
					old picture (very bad at first, &amp; now almost effaced by cleaning) of a Man in a slash'd doublet, dark curl'd hair &amp; beard,
					looking like a Foreigner, holding a pair of Compasses, &amp; by his side a Polyedron, made up of twelve pentagons. no name, or date.
					you will see presently, why I mention it.</p>
         <p>The Vice-Chancellor (Burroughs, Master of Keys) tells me he very well knew Vertue. that in a book
					belonging to the board of Works he had discover'd John of Padua to be the architect of
					Somerset-house, &amp; had found that he likewise built Long-leat for Sr John Thynne. that it was from
					the similitude of style in those buildings, &amp; in the <hi rend="italic">four Gates</hi> of Keys-College, he had imagined the latter
					to be also the work of John of Padua, &amp; this was <hi rend="italic">all the proof</hi> he had of it. upon looking at these gates I
					plainly see, that they might very well be the work of one Man. from the College-books I find, that
					the East-side, in wch are the <hi rend="italic">Portæ Virtutis &amp; Sapientiæ</hi>, was built in 1566, &amp; 1567. these are joined by
					two long walls to the <hi rend="italic">Porta Humilitatis,</hi> opening to the Street; &amp; in the two walls are two little Dorick
					frontis-pieces, leading into gardens. all these are (I dare say) of one time, &amp; shew the Roman Architecture reviving amongst us
					with little Columns &amp; Pilasters, well enough proportion'd in themselves, &amp; neatly executed, but in no proportion to the
					building they are meant to adorn. in the year 1575 are these words, <hi rend="italic">Porta</hi> (<hi rend="italic">quæ Honoris
						dicitur</hi>) <hi rend="italic">&amp; ad Scholas Publicas aperit</hi>) <hi rend="italic">a lapide quadrato duroqb </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">extruebatur, ad eam scilicet formam &amp; effigiem, quam Doctor Caius</hi> (<hi rend="italic">dum viveret</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Architecto præscripserat, elaborata.</hi> this is the Gate (more ornamented than the rest, but in the same style) wch
					you remember: it cost 128£. 9s. 5d. N:B: Dr Caius died July 29, 1573.</p>
         <p>In the same year, 1575, are these words: <hi rend="italic">Positum est Joh: Caio ex alabastro monumentum summi decoris &amp;
						artificii eodem in sacelli loco, quo corpus ejus antea sepeliebatur: cui præter insculpta illius insignia &amp; annotatum ætatis
						obitusqb </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">diem &amp; annum</hi> (<hi rend="italic">uti vivus executoribus ipse præceperat</hi>) <hi rend="italic">duas
						tantummodo sententias has inscripsimus, Vivit post funera Virtus – Fui Caius.</hi> this Monument (made to stand upon the
					ground, but now raised a great deal above the eye on a heavy ugly base projecting from the wall) is a Sarcophagus with rib'd work &amp;
					mouldings (somewhat antique) placed on a basement, supporting pretty large Corinthian columns of fine Alabaster, wch bear up an
					intablature, &amp; form a sort of canopy over it. the Capitals are gilt, &amp; the upper part both gilt &amp; painted with ugly scrolls
					&amp; compartments, <hi rend="italic">à l'Elisabet</hi>; the rest is simple and well enough.</p>
         <p>Charge of the Founder's Tomb finish'd in 1575. </p>
         <table rend="frame">
            <row>
               <cell>For Alabaster &amp; Carriage </cell>
               <cell>10£. 10s. 0<hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>To <hi rend="italic">Theodore,</hi> &amp; others, for carving </cell>
               <cell>33 .. 16 .. 5  </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>To Labourers </cell>
               <cell>0 .. 18 .. 1  </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Charges extraordinary </cell>
               <cell>2 .. 0 .. 2  </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>Then in Anno 1576 are these words. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">In Atrio Doctoris Caii Columna erecta est, eiqb </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">miro artificio elaboratus, atqb </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">in se</hi> 60 <hi rend="italic">Horologia complexus imponitur, quem Theodorus Haveus Cleviensis Artifex egregius
						&amp; insignis Architecturæ Professor fecit &amp; insigniis</hi> (read, <hi rend="italic">insignibus</hi>) <hi rend="italic">eorum
						Generosorum qui tum in</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Collegio morabantur depinxit, et velut monumentum suæ erga collegium benevolentiæ eidem dedicavit. hujus in summitate
						lapidis constituitur ventilabrum ad formam Pegasi formatum.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This column is now destroy'd, with all its sun-dials. but when Loggan did his views of the
					colleges, the Pillar (tho' not the Dials) was still standing.</p>
         <p>From all this I draw, that Theodore Haveus of Cleves, the Architect, Sculptor, Painter, &amp; Diallist, did probably build the Porta
					Honoris (if not all the others) &amp; having work'd many years for Dr Caius &amp; the College, in
					gratitude left behind him his <hi rend="italic">own picture.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the Gallery at Emanuel are several pictures worth remarking, but not one name of a Painter to be
					found.</p>
         <p>1. Archb:p Cranmer, head &amp; hands (on board) in his tippet of martens, &amp; seal-ring of his arms, æt: 57. </p>
         <p>2. Sr Walter Mildmay (the Founder) whole length, black cap &amp; long gown, book of statutes in his
					hand, pale &amp; old. 1588. tolerably well done.</p>
         <p>3. Sir Antony Mildmay, (his Son) 1596. whole length, doublet of gold tissue, black cloak, many
					jewels, high-crown'd hat hanging on a chair, armour lying on the floor, &amp; a fine damask'd long pistol. letters on a table directed
					to hir Majestie's Ambassador. a carpet mightily finish'd.</p>
         <p>4. Mrs Joyce Franklin, (a Benefactress) jolly woman above 40 with an enamel'd watch open in her
					hand. no date, dress of about Q: Mary's time. a head &amp; hands. </p>
         <p>5. Dr Hall, Bishop of Exeter, the great gold medal (representing the Synod of Dort) hanging in a
					chain about his neck. a head miserably done.</p>
         <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Effig: Rodulphi Simons,</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Architecti suâ ætate peritisimi, qui</hi> (<hi rend="italic">præter plurima ædificia ab eo præclare facta</hi>) <hi rend="italic">duo Collegia, Emanuelis hoc, Sidneii illud, extruxit integre: magnam etiam partem Trinitatis reconcinnavit
						amplissime.</hi> head, &amp; hands with a great pair of compasses.</p>
         <p>In St John's Library is what I take for the original of Lady Margaret, kneeling at her oratory
					under a state. it is hung at a great height, &amp; spoil'd by damp &amp; neglect, while the Master keeps very choicely in his Lodge a
					miserable copy of it. in the same Library is a very good whole length of Bp Williams, (while Lord
					Keeper) standing, &amp; <hi rend="italic">a carpet</hi> in it finish'd with great care; perhaps therefore by the same hand with that of
					Sr Ant: Mildmay. in the lodge is a very good old Picture, that used to be call'd Bp Fisher, but Dr
						Taylor has told them, it is <hi rend="italic">Sr</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Antony Brown.</hi>
					 what his reasons are, I can not tell, as he is not here: 'tis surely of Henry 8ths time, &amp; a
					Layman; on a board split from top to bottom.</p>
         <p>I sympathise with your Gout: it would be strange if I did not, with so many internal monitors as I carry about me, that hourly bid me
					expect it myself this autumn. yet it frights me to hear of <hi rend="italic">both feet.</hi> what did you do, &amp; in the night too,
					wch one foot only can make of equal duration with a night in Greenland?</p>
         <p>I thank you for your anecdote about Sr W:r Raleigh, wch is very extraordinary.</p>
         <p>What do you think of the Erse-Poems, now they are come out? I suppose your suspicions are augmented: yet (upon some farther enquiries
					I have made) Mr D:d Hume (the Historian) writes word, that 'their authenticity is beyond all
					question; that Adam Smith, the celebrated Professor at Glasgow, has assured him (who doubted too) that he had heard the <hi rend="italic">Piper of the Argyleshire militia</hi> repeat all these &amp; many more of equal beauty. that Major Mackay, the Laird
					&amp; Lady of Macleod, &amp; the Laird of Macfarline, the greatest Antiquarian in all their country, &amp; others, who live in the
					Highlands very remote from each other, remember them perfectly well, &amp; could not be acquainted with them, if they were not spread
					into every one's mouth there, &amp; become in a manner national works.' this is certainly the only proof, that works preserved merely
					by tradition, &amp; not in Manuscript, will admitt of.</p>
         <p>Adieu, I have done at last. oh no! my defence of Sr T: Wyat is much at your service, but as it was
					the first thing I transcribed (when I was little versed in old hands) there probably may be mistakes, wch I could correct by comparing
					it with the Mss, were I in Town. I have also four long letters of his to the King (while he was Embassador) but, I doubt, you will scarce think them worth printing, as they contain no very remarkable facts, yet they
					help to shew the spirit, vigilance, &amp; activity of the Man.</p>
         <p>Look in Casley's Catalogue of the King's Library at 17. D. 4to. VI. 1. &amp; you will find the Mss
					of Occleve &amp; Painting of Chaucer.
				</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
