<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (December 1760)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 328, vol. ii, 717
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=328</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 399
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 217, vol. ii, 207-208
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/207</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXV, vol. ii, 187-188
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/187</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXI, vol. ii, 285
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/285</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXIX, vol. iii, 164
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/164</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XCVI, vol. ii, 18
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/1819/2/18</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 118
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=118</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, appendix, letter XII, vol. i, 554
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MaW_1814i/1/554</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0378">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1760-12"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Rousseau, Jean Jacques</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0378">
      <body>
         <p>I have been very ill this week with a great cold and a fever, and though now in a way to be well, am like to be confined some days
					longer: whatever you will send me that is new, or old, and <hi rend="italic">long,</hi> will be received as a charity. Rousseau's
						people do not interest me; there is but one character and one style in them all, I do not know their
					faces asunder. I have no esteem for their persons or conduct, am not touched with their passions; and as to their story, I do not
					believe a word of it – not because it is improbable, but because it is absurd. If I had any little propensity, it was to Julie;
					but now she has gone and (so hand over head) married that monsieur de Wolmar, I take her for a <hi rend="italic">vraie Suissesse,</hi>
					and do not doubt but she had taken a cup too much, like her lover. All this does not imply that I
					will not read it out, when you can spare the rest of it.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
