<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (24 December 1767)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>Class No. LC II, 90</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 458, vol. iii, 984-986
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=458</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 237, vol. ii, 262-264
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:262</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 159-161
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=159</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0514">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1767-12-24"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0514">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Honble Horace Walpole in Arlington Street London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>SAFFRON WALDEN 25 DE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Surely as the letter is address'd to a <hi rend="italic">Lady,</hi> &amp; subscribed, Your most humble <hi rend="italic">Son,</hi> it
					can be to nobody but his Mother. I do not remember, that there is any superscription to it, for the
						<hi rend="italic">original</hi> is not the letter itself, but a transcript of it set down in a great register-book belonging to the
					Privy-seal Office, in wch this stands very near to the beginning. I have mark'd the number of the Mss, &amp; of the article, if you
					chuse to consult the Musæum about it. I told you false, when I said the letter was dated: but the reason I concluded so was, that the
					articles, as I remember, go on regularly in the book in order of time &amp; many come after it, that belong to the first year of his
					reign.</p>
         <p>In the page, that contains his letter about Jane Shore, at a little distance below it are some abbreviated words in a cramp hand
						thus –ffin by [ ] Thom Drury date A° IX° Henrici sept [ ] per Copiam [ ] [ ] wch seem to say
					something about the 9th year of Henry 7th, but I think they relate not to this letter (wch is directed to the <hi rend="italic">Bp of
						Lincoln, his Chaunc:r;</hi>; now Russel Bp of Lincoln was his Chancellor, &amp; not so to H: 7th.)
					&amp; the few succeeding articles are really of H: 7th &amp; H: 8th's time, so I suppose the words to relate to them only.</p>
         <p>Mr Anstey's satyr seems to aim chiefly at this University, the patrons that protect it, the clients
					that make their court to them, their dedications, &amp; clumsy flattery, their method of education, &amp; style of politicks, &amp;c:
					he has not indeed refused any thing else ridiculous, that came across him. I like it but little: the only things, that made me laugh,
					were <q>
               <p>Sent venison, wch was kindly taken <lb/> And Woodcocks, wch they boild with bacon.</p>
            </q> and the High-Sheriffs frizzled Lady, when she meets her Husband, after he is knighted, at a ball.</p>
         <p> I have been confined to my room, eversince I came hither, but not very ill.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am <lb/> Ever Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
            <dateline>24 Dec: 1767. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
