<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Charles Victor de Bonstetten and Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (6 January 1770)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
		                <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
		                <repository>College Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.">
			                  <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 512, vol. iii, 1110-1112
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=512</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLVI, vol. iii, 266-267
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:266</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXIV, vol. v, 101-103
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:101</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0574">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76366659">Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832</persName>
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1770-01-06"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0574">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk by Yarmouth</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <div type="part">
					       <opener>
						
						
						         <dateline>Cambridge the 6. Jan. 1770. </dateline>
					       </opener>
					       <p>
						         <hi rend="italic">Hence vain deluding Joys</hi>
						 is our motto hier, written on every feature, and ourly spoken by every solitary Chapel bel; So that
						decently you cant expect no other but a very grave letter. I realy beg you pardon to wrap up my thoughts in so smart a dress as an in
						quarto sheet. I know they should apear in a folio leave, but the Ideas themselves shall look so solemn as to belie their
						dress.–Tho' I wear not yet the black gown, and am only an inferior Priest in the temple of Meditation, yet my countenance is
						already consecrated. I never walk but with even steps and musing gate, and looks comercing with the skyes; and unfold my wrinkles only
						when I see mr. Gray, or think of you. Then nothwithstanding all your learnings and knowledge, I feel in such occasions that I have a
						heart, which you know is as some others a quite prophane thing to carry under a black gown. </p>
					       <p>I am in a hurry from morning till evening. At 8 o Clock I am roused by a young square Cap, with
						whom I follow Satan through Chaos and night. He explaind me in Greek and latin, the <hi rend="italic">sweet reluctant amorous
							Delays</hi> of our Grandmother Eve. We finish our travels in a copious breakfeast of muffins and tea. Then apears Shakespair and old
							Lineus strugling together as two ghost would do for a damned Soul. Sometimes the one get the better
						sometimes the other. Mr Gray, whose acquaintance is my greatest debt to you, is so good as to shew me Macbeth, and all witches
						Beldams, Ghost and Spirits, whose language I never could have understood without his Interpretation. I am now endeavouring to dress
						all those people in a french dress, which is a very hard labour. </p>
					       <p>I am afraid to take a room, which Mr. Gray shall keep still much better. So I stop hier my everrambling pen. My respectful
						Compliments to Md. Nichole. Only remember that you have no where a better or more grateful friend than your de Bonstetten. –I
						loosd Mr. Wheeler letter and his direction.</p>
				     </div>
				     <div type="part">
					       <p>
						 I never saw such a boy: our breed is not made on this model. he is busy from morn[ing] to night,
						has no other amusement, than tha[t] of changing one study for another, like[s] nobody, that he sees here, &amp; yet wishes to stay
						longer, tho' he has pass'd a whole fortnight with us already. his letter has had no correction whatever, &amp; is prettier by half
						than English.</p>
					       <p>Would not you hazard your journal: I want to see, what you have done this summer tho' it would be safer &amp; better to bring it
						yourself, methinks! </p>
					       <p>Complimens respectueux à Mad: Nichole, &amp; à notre aimable Cousine, la <hi rend="italic">Sposa.</hi>
						
					       </p>
				     </div>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
