<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (24 February 1771)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 105</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 543, vol. iii, 1166-1168
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=543</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXXVIII, vol. iii, 303-304
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:303</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXXVI, vol. v, 127-129
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:127</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0623">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1771-02-24"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="high">Blundeston, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Ste.-Palaye, Jean Baptiste la Curne</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Monstrelet, Enguerrand de</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0623">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls at Blundeston near Leostoff Suffolk by Norwich</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Your Friend <hi rend="italic">Jean Froissart,</hi> Son of Thomas by profession a Herald-painter, was born at Valenciennes in Haynault
					about the year 1337. was by nature fond of every <hi rend="italic">noble</hi> diversion, as hunting, hawking, dress, good-cheer, wine,
					&amp; women (this latter passion commenced at 12 years old) and was in his own time no less distinguish'd by his gallant poesies (still
					preserved in Mss) than by his historical writings, wch he begun at the desire of <hi rend="italic">Robert de Namur,</hi> Seigneur de
					Beaufort, when he was barely 20 years of age. at 24 he made his first voyage into England, &amp; presented the first part of his
					history to Edw: the 3d's Queen, Philippa of Haynault, who appointed him <hi rend="italic">Clerk of her chamber,</hi> that is,
					Secretary, by wch he became one of the Houshold in that Court. after the death of this Queen in 1369 he had the Living of <hi rend="italic">Lessines</hi> in his own country given him, &amp; must then consequently be a Priest. he attach'd himself to Wenceslaus
					of Luxemburg, Duke of Brabant, who dying in 1384, he became Clerk of the Chappel to Guy Comte de Blois, who probably gave him a canonry
					in the collegiate Church of <hi rend="italic">Chimay</hi> near Marienbourg in the county of Haynault.
					he also had obtain'd of the Pope a reversion of another canonry in the Church of Lisle; but of this he never could get possession.
					after 27 years absence from England he made a third voyage thither in 1395, &amp; stay'd in it only 3 months. his Patron Guy de Blois
					died in 1397, &amp; Froissart survived him certainly 4 years, but how much more is uncertain. these &amp; many more particulars are
					taken from the account of his life &amp; writings collected by Mons: <hi rend="italic">de la Curne</hi> de St Palaye, in 10 Tome of the <hi rend="italic">Mem: de l'Acad: des Inscript:ns</hi> &amp;c: where you may see much
					more about him. the same Author defends him strongly against the suspicions, that have been entertain'd, of his partiality to the
					English Nation.</p>
         <p>A Man at arms was a complicated machine, consisting of about seven Men, i:e: the Knight or Gentleman himself compleatly &amp; heavily
					arm'd &amp; mounted on his great war-horse caparison'd &amp; arm'd as strongly as the Rider: the rest were his Esquires rather meant to
					assist him &amp; watch his motions in the combat, than to engage in action themselves. all of them were (as I apprehend) on horseback,
					&amp; thus taken together, made the principal strength &amp; principal expence of armies in those days. <hi rend="italic">Ecuyers</hi>
					were the sons of Gentleman, train'd up in quality of <hi rend="italic">Pages</hi> till 12 years old
					(commonly not in their Father's Castle, but in that of some famous Knight, his Friend) after wch age they assumed the title of <hi rend="italic">Esquires,</hi> were exercised daily in feats of arms &amp; curtesy, attended the person of their Lord at home &amp;
					abroad, and at 21 were qualified to receive themselves the order of knighthood. read the same St Palaye's <hi rend="italic">Mem: de
						l'ancienne Chevalerie,</hi> 2 v: 8vo. 1759, Paris. if you would have me say any thing to T: you must
					remind me, what period of time he enquired about, for my memory fails me.</p>
         <p>You may be sure of a month's notice from me, if I undertake the voyage, wch seems to me next to
					impossible. I received a letter from B:n last night, wch mentions you kindly, &amp; seems very desirous, we should come this summer.
					what you m[entio]n of herrings I know not: I have never seen or
					heard of them!</p>
         <p>Monstrelet reaches from A:D: 1400 to 1467, &amp; there are
					additions at the end of him, that come down to 1516. it is a splendid &amp; very substantial Folio, publ:d in 1572.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! my respects to Mrs. Nicholls.</salute>
            <dateline>24 Feb: 1771</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
