<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs. (Dorothy) Gray (21 August 1740)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 93, vol. i, 173-175
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=93</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxvi, section ii, 103-104
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:103</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XLIV, vol. i, 79-81
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:79</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter XXIX, vol. ii, 109-110
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:109</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter XXIX, vol. ii, 131-133
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:131</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XLIV, vol. i, 98-100
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:98</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter XXVI, vol. i, 225-227
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:225</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0105">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000457">Florence, Italy</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1740-08-21"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Gray, Mrs. (Dorothy), 1685-1753</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0105">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Florence, Aug. 21, N.S. 1740. </dateline>
				     </opener>
				     <p>It is some time since I have had the pleasure of writing to you, having been upon a little excursion cross the mountains to Bologna.
					We set out from hence at sunset, passed the Apennines by moon-light, travelling incessantly till we came to Bologna at four in the
					afternoon next day. There we spent a week agreeably enough, and returned as we came. The day before yesterday arrived the news of a
					Pope; and I have the mortification of being within four days journey of Rome, and not seeing his coronation, the heats being violent,
					and the infectious air now at its height. We had an instance, the other day, that it is not only fancy. Two country fellows, strong
					men, and used to the country about Rome, having occasion to come from thence hither, and travelling on foot, as common with them, one
					died suddenly on the road; the other got hither, but extremely weak, and in a manner stupid; he was carried to the hospital, but died
					in two days. So, between fear and laziness, we remain here, and must be satisfied with the accounts other people give us of the matter.
					The new Pope is called Benedict XIV. being created Cardinal by Benedict XIII. the last Pope but one.
					His name is Lambertini, a noble Bolognese, and Archbishop of that city. When I was first there, I
					remember to have seen him two or three times; he is a short, fat man, about sixty-five years of age, of a hearty, merry countenance,
					and likely to live some years. He bears a good character for generosity, affability, and other virtues; and, they say, wants neither
					knowledge nor capacity. The worst side of him is, that he has a nephew or two; besides a certain young favourite, called Melara, who is
					said to have had, for some time, the arbitrary disposal of his purse and family. He is reported to have made a little speech to the
					Cardinals in the Conclave, while they were undetermined about an election, as follows: 'Most eminent Lords, here are three Bolognese of
					different characters, but all equally proper for the Popedom. If it be your pleasures, to pitch upon a Saint, there is Cardinal
						Gotti; if upon a Politician, there is Aldrovandi; if upon a Booby,
					here am I.' The Italian is much more expressive, and, indeed, not to be translated; wherefore, if you meet with any body that
					understands it, you may show them what he said in the language he spoke it. 'Eminssimi. Sigri. Ci siamo tré, diversi sì, mà tutti
					idonei al Papato. Si vi piace un Santo, c' è l'Gotti; se volete una testa scaltra, e Politica, c' è
						l'Aldrovandé; se un Coglione, eccomi!' Cardinal Coscia (the late
					Pope's nephew) as he has had no hand in this election, it is hoped, will be called to account for all his villanous practices. The
					Pretender, they say, has resigned all his pretensions to his eldest boy, and will accept of the Grand Chancellorship, which is thirty
					thousand crowns a-year; the pension he has at present is only twenty thousand. I do not affirm the truth of this last article; because,
					if he does, it is necessary he should take the ecclesiastical habit, and it will sound mighty odd to be called his Majesty the
					Chancellor. — So ends my Gazette.</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
