<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (20 March 1738)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/37</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 51, vol. i, 82-83
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=51</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 78, vol. i, 182-184
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915i/1/182</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. i, 154-155
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=13&amp;page=154</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0055">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1738-03-20"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
               <p>Julian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Bentley, Richard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0055">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Honble Horatio Walpole, Esq</addrLine>
               <addrLine>at the Treasury St James's</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>CAMBRIDGE 20 MR</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>[           ]</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Thank God, I had a very good night's rest, and am sufficiently awake to answer your letter, tho' likely to be more dull, than you
					that write in your sleep: and indeed I do not believe, that you ever are so much asleep, but you can write to a relation, play a sober
					game at Picquet, keep up a tete á tete conversation, sell a bargain, or perform any of the little offices of life with tolerable
					spirit; certain I am, there are many people in the world, who in their top spirits are no better eveillés, than you are at four in the
					morning, reclined upon your pillow. 
					 I believe, I partly guess [what is] your hopeful branch; I fancy you may find the first letters of
					both somewhere between H &amp; T inclusive; if I interpret your hieroglyphs aright. as to my journey
					to London, which you are so good as to press, alas! what can I do? if I come, it is for good &amp; all, &amp; I don't know how it is, I have a sort of reluctance to leave this place, unamiable as it may seem; 'tis true Cambridge is
					very ugly, she is very dirty, &amp; very dull; but I'm like a cabbage, where I'm stuck, I love to grow; you should pull me up sooner,
					than any one, but I shall be ne'er the better for transplanting: poor Mr Cornwallis is here, sadly
					alter'd, so that one can very hardly know him; Towers still stands out, &amp; refuses to admit him; so
					that they have called in their visitours, that is the Vice-chancellour, Dr Bently, &amp; Dr Ashton; but nothing is yet determined: the
					Assizes are just over, I was there; but I a'nt to be transported: Adieu,</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>yours sincerely</salute>
            <signed>T: GRAY </signed>
            <dateline>Cam: March: 20 
					</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
