<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (25 July 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Fort Worth, TX</settlement>
		                <institution key="TXCU">Texas Christian University Library</institution>
		                <repository>Mary Couts Burnett Library</repository>
		                <collection>W. L. Lewis Collection</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <surrogates>
			                  <bibl>
				                    <title>Digital facsimile [JPEG] and transcription from original letter</title>
			                  </bibl>
		                </surrogates>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 241, vol. ii, 508-511
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=241</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XX, 89-91
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:89</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXLIII, vol. i, 340-342
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:340</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0274">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-07-25"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0274">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					       <dateline>July. 25. 1757. Stoke.</dateline>
					       <salute> Dear S<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I thank you for the second little letter, for your Cambridge-Anecdotes, &amp; (suffer me to say too) for the trouble you have had on
					my account. I am going to add to it by sending you my poetical Cargo to distribute, tho' whatever the Advertisement says, it will not be this fortnight yet. for you must know (what you will
					like no more, than I do; yet it was not in my power any how to avoid it) M<hi rend="super">r</hi> W:,
					who has set up a printing-press in his own house at Twickenham, earnestly desired, that he might print it for Dodsley, &amp; as there
					is but one hand employ'd, you must think it will take up some time to dispatch 2000 Copies, as soon as
					may be, you will have a parcel sent you. w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> you will dispose of, as follows. M<hi rend="super">rs</hi>
						Bonfoy,M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Bonfoy, D<hi rend="super">r</hi>
						Long, Gaskarth, &amp; all the Fellows resident, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Montagu, &amp; Southwell (if they happen to be there) Master
					of S<hi rend="super">t</hi> Johns, (I know, he is at Rochester, but it suffices to send it to his
					lodge) Master of Bennet, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Hurd, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Balguy, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Talbot, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Nourse, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Neville (of Jesus) M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Bickham, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Hadley, M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Newcome. if you think, I forget any body, pray send it them in my name,
					what remain upon your hands, you will hide in a corner.</p>
				     <pb/>
				     <p>I am sorry to say I know no more of Mason, than you do. it is my own fault, I am afraid, for I have not yet answer'd that
						letter.</p>
				     <p>His Prussian Majesty wrote a letter to the K: owning himself in a bad situation, from w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> (he said) nothing but
					a <hi rend="underline">Coup de Maitre</hi> could extricate him. we have a secret expedition going forward: all I know is that L<hi rend="super">d</hi> Ancram, S<hi rend="super">r</hi> John Mordaunt, &amp; Gen:<hi rend="super">l</hi> Conway are to bear a part in it. the Duke has been very ill with his leg;
						Ranby was sent for, but countermanded; the Mar:<hi rend="super">l</hi> d'Etrées having sent him his own Surgeons. I would wish to be like M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Bonfoy, &amp; think that every thing turns out the best in the world, but it won't do. I am stupid &amp;
					low-spirited, but ever </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> Yours </salute>
					       <signed> TG: </signed>
				     </closer>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
