<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (23 July 1756)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 218, vol. ii, 466-467
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=218</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XIV, 48-53
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:48</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xxiv, section iv, 245-247
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:245</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXXI, vol. i, 300-303
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:300</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LIII, vol. ii, 273-275
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:273</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXI, vol. iii, 151-153
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:151</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XCII, vol. ii, 12-14
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:12</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XXIV, vol. i, 354-355
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:354</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0249">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1756-07-23"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0249">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Revd Mr Mason</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Mason</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I feel a contrition for my long silence; &amp; yet perhaps it is the last thing you trouble your head about. nevertheless I will be
					as sorry, as if you took it ill. I am sorry too to see you so punctilious, as to stand upon answers, &amp; never to come near me, till
					I have regularly left my name at your door, like a Mercer's Wife, that imitates People, who go a-visiting. I would forgive you this, if
					you could possibly suspect I were doing any thing, that I liked better. for then your formality might look like being piqued at my
					negligence; wch has somewhat in it like kindness: but you know I am at Stoke, hearing, seeing, doing, absolutely nothing. not such a
					nothing, as you do at Tunbridge, chequer'd &amp; diversified with a succession of fleeting colours; but heavy, lifeless, without form,
					&amp; void; sometimes almost as black, as the <hi rend="italic">Moral</hi> of Voltaire's Lisbon, wch
					angers you so. I have had no more pores &amp; muscular inflations, &amp; am only troubled with this depression of mind. you will not
					expect therefore I should give you any account of my <hi rend="italic">Verve,</hi> wch is at best (you know) of so delicate a
					constitution, &amp; has such weak nerves, as not to stir out of its chamber above three days in a year. but I shall enquire after
					yours, &amp; why it is off again? it has certainly worse nerves than mine, if your Reviewers have frighted it. sure I (not to mention a
					score of your Uncles and Aunts) am something a better Judge, than all the Man-Midwives &amp;
					Presbyterian Parsons, that ever were born. pray give me leave to ask you. do you find yourself tickled
					with the commendations of such People? (for you have your share of these too) I dare say not. Your Vanity has certainly a better taste.
					and can then the censure of such Criticks move you? I own, it is an impertinence in these Gentry to talk of one at all either in good
					or in bad, but this we must all swallow, I mean not only we, that write, but all the <hi rend="italic">we's</hi> that ever did any
					thing to be talk'd of. I canot pretend to be learned without books, nor to know the Druids from the Pelasgi at this distance from Cambridge, I can only tell you not to go &amp; take the Mona for the Isle of Man. it is Anglesey, a tract of plain country, very fertile, but picturesque only from the
					view it has of Caernarvonshire, from wch it is separated by the Menai, a narrow arm of the Sea. forgive me for supposing in you such a
					want of erudition.</p>
         <p>I congratulate you on our glorious successes in the Mediterranean. shall we go in time, &amp; hire a house together in
						Switzerland? it is a fine poetical country to look at, &amp; no body there will understand a word we
					say or write. pray, let me know what you are about, what new acquaintances you have made at Tunbridge, how you do in body &amp; in
					mind?</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>believe me ever sincerely<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
            <dateline>Stoke – July, 23. 1756 </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Have you read Mad: Maintenon's Letters. When I saw Ld John in Town,
						he said if his Brother went to Ireland, you were to go <hi rend="italic">second</hi> Chaplain. but it
						seem'd to me not at all certain, that the Duke would return thither. you probably know by this time.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
