<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (9 August 1750)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 39-40</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">185 mm x 148 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 154, vol. i, 327-330
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=154</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xiii, section iv, 209-210
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:209</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 161-163
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:161</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XCI, vol. i, 205-208
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:205</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXIII, vol. ii, 205-207
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:205</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XXX, vol. iii, 72-75
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:72</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter LXXIV, vol. i, 158-160
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:158</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XIII, vol. i, 320-322
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:320</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0174">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1750-08-09"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
			         <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0174">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Stoke–Aug: 9 1750 </dateline>
					       <salute>My dear Wharton</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> Aristotle says (one may write Greek to you without Scandal) that <hi rend="italic">Οἱ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">τόποι</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">οὐ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">διαλύουσι</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">τὴν</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">φιλίαν</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">ἁπλῶς</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ἀλλὰ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">τὴν</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">ἐνέργειαν</hi>· <hi rend="italic">ἐὰν</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">δὲ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">χρόνιος</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">ἡ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">ἀπουσία</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">γένηται</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">καὶ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">τῆς</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">φιλίας</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">δοκεῖ</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">λήθην</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">ποιεῖν</hi>· <hi rend="italic">ὅθεν</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">εἴρηται</hi>
					       <q>
						         <p>
							           <hi rend="italic">Πολλὰς</hi>
							           <hi rend="italic">δὴ</hi>
							           <hi rend="italic">φιλίας</hi>
							           <hi rend="italic">ἀπροσηγορία</hi>
							           <hi rend="italic">διέλυσεν</hi>.
						</p>
					       </q> but Aristotle may say whatever he pleases. I do not find myself at all the worse for it. I could indeed wish to refresh my <hi rend="italic">Ενέργεια</hi> a little at Durham by a Sight of you, but when is there a Probability of my being so happy? it concerned
					me greatly when I heard the other Day, that your Asthma continued at Times to afflict you, &amp; that you were often obliged to go into
					the Country to breath. you cannot oblige me more than by giving me an Account of the State both of your Body &amp; Mind; I hope the
					latter is able to keep you chearful &amp; easy in spite of the Frailties of its Companion. as to my own it can do neither one, nor the
					other; &amp; I have the Mortification to find my spiritual Part the most infirm Thing about me. You have doubtless heard of the Loss I
					have had in Dr. Middleton, whose House was the only easy Place one could find to converse in at
					Cambridge. for my Part I find a Friend so uncommon a Thing, that I can not help regretting even an old Acquaintance, wch is an
					indifferent Likeness of it, &amp; tho' I don't approve the Spirit of his Books, methinks 'tis pity the World should lose so rare a
					Thing as a good Writer. my Studies can not furnish a Recommendation of many new Books to you. there
					is a Defense de l'Esprit des Loix by Montesquieu himself. it has some lively Things in it, but is
					very short, &amp; his Adversary appears to be so mean a Bigot, that he deserved no Answer. there are
					3 V: in 4to of, Histoire du Cabinet du Roi, by Mess: Buffons, &amp;
						D'Aubenton. the first is a Man of Character, but (I am told) has hurt it by this Work. it is all a
					Sort of Introduction to Natural History. the weak Part of it is a Love of System, wch runs thro' it,
					the most contrary Thing in the World to a Science, entirely grounded upon Experiments, &amp; that has nothing to do with Vivacity of
					Imagination. there are some microscopical Observations, that seem'd curious to me, on those Animalcula to wch we are supposed to owe
					our Origin; &amp; wch he has discover'd of like Figure in Females not pregnant, &amp; in almost every Thing we use for Nourishment,
					even Vegetables, particularly in their Fruits &amp; Seeds. not that he allows them to be animated Bodies, but <hi rend="italic">Molecules organisées.</hi> if you ask what that is, I can not tell; no more than I can understand a new System of Generation wch he
					builds upon it. but what I was going to commend is a general View he gives of the Face of the Earth, follow'd by a particular one of
					all known Nations, their peculiar Figure &amp; Manners, wch is the best Epitome of Geography I ever met with, &amp; wrote with Sense,
					&amp; Elegance: in short these Books are well worth turning over. the Memoires of the Abbé de Mongon
					in 5 V: are highly commended, but I have not seen them. he was engaged in several Embassies to Germany, England, &amp;c: during the
					Course of the late War. The Presid: Henault's Abregé Chronol:ique de l'Hist: de France I believe I
					have before mention'd to you, as a very good Book of its Kind.</p>
				     <p>You advised me in your last to be acquainted with [Keene] &amp; we are accordingly on very good
					&amp; civil Terms: but to make us love one another (I reckon) you hardly proposed. I always placed the Service he did me [about
						Tuthill] to your Account. this latter has done him some Service, about his Regulations. if you will give me the Pleasure of a Letter, while I continue here, it will be a great Satisfaction to me.
					I shall stay a Month longer. my best Wishes to Mrs Wharton &amp; your Family. I am</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Ever Yours </salute>
					       <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Do not imagine I have forgot my Debts, I hope to repay them this Year. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
