<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (4 December 1762)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 156-157</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>4 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">200 mm x 162 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 363, vol. ii, 784-788
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=363</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter xliii, section iv, 292-293
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:292</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXLV, vol. ii, 263-269
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:263</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CIV, vol. ii, 399-402
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:399</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXIV, vol. iii, 297-302
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:297</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXV, vol. ii, 63-65
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:63</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter XLIII, vol. i, 395-396
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:395</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0416">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1762-12-04"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0416">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Wharton M:D: at</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Old-Park near</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>YORK</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I feel very ungrateful every day, that I continue silent, &amp; yet I do not write to you: but now the pen is in my hand, and I am in
					for it. when I left you, in spite of the rain I went out of my way to Richmond, &amp; made a shift to
					see the Castle, &amp; look down upon the valley, thro' wch the Swale winds: that was all the weather would permitt. at Rippon I visited
					the Church, which we had neglected before, with some pleasure, &amp; saw the Ure full to its brink
					&amp; very inclinable to overflow. some faint gleams of sunshine gave me an opportunity of walking over Studley, &amp; descending into
					the ruins of Fountain's Abbey, wch I examined with attention. I pass'd over the ugly moor of
					Harrowgate, made a bow to the Queen's-Head, &amp; got late at night to Leedes: here the rain was so
					perverse I could scarce see the Town, much less go to Kirkstall-Abbey, wch was my intention; so I
					proceeded to Wakefield, &amp; Wentworth Castle. here the Sun again
					indulged me, &amp; open'd as beautiful a scene of rich &amp; cultivated country, as (I am told) Yorkshire affords. the water is all
					artificial, but with an air of nature; much wood; a very good house in the Q: Anne style, wch is now new-fronting in a far better taste
					by the present Earl; many pictures not worth a farthing, &amp; a
					castle built only for a play-thing on the top of the hill as a point of view, &amp; to command a noble prospect. I went on to
						Sheffield, liked the situation in a valley by a pretty river's side, surrounded with charming hills:
					saw the handsome parish-church with the chappel &amp; monuments of the Talbots. then I enter'd the Peak, a countrey beyond comparison uglier than any
					other I have seen in England, black, tedious, barren, &amp; not mountainous enough to please one with its horrors. this is mitigated,
					since you were there, by a road like a bowling-green, wch soon brought me to Chatsworth. the house
					has the air of a Palace, the hills rising on three of its sides shut out the view of its dreary neighbourhood, &amp; are cover'd with
					wood to their tops: the front opens to the Derwent winding thro' the valley, wch by the art of Mr Brown is now always visible &amp; full to its brim. for heretofore it could not well be seen (but in rainy seasons) from the windows. a
					handsome bridge is lately thrown over it, &amp; the stables taken away, wch stood full in view between the house &amp; the river. the
					prospect opens here to a wider tract of country terminated by more distant hills: this scene is yet in its infancy, the objects are
					thinly scatter'd, &amp; the clumps and plantations lately made: but it promises well in time. within
					doors the furniture corresponds to the stateliness of the appartments, fine tapestry, marble
					doorcases with fruit, flowers, &amp; foliage, excellently done by Old Cibber's Father, windows of
					plate-glass in gilded frames, &amp; such a profusion of Gibbons' best carving in wood, viz.
					Dead-Game, fish, shells, flowers, &amp;c: as I never saw anywhere. the cielings &amp; staircases all painted by Verrio or Laguerre, in their usual sprawling way, &amp; no other pictures, but in one room 8 or 10 portraits, some of them very good, of James &amp; Charles the first's time. the
					gardens are small, &amp; in the French style with water-works, particularly a grand Cascade of steps &amp; a <hi rend="italic">Temple
						d'eaux</hi> at the head of it. from thence I went to Hardwick. one would think Mary, Queen of
						Scots, was but just walk'd down into the Park with her Guard for half-an-hour. her Gallery, her room
					of audience, her antichamber, with the very canopies, chair of state, footstool, Lit-de-repos, Oratory, carpets, &amp; hangings, just
					as she left them. a little tatter'd indeed, but the more venerable; &amp; all preserved with religious care, &amp; paper'd up in
					winter. the park &amp; country are just like Hertfordshire. I went by Chesterfield &amp; Mansfield to revisit my old friend the Trent
					at Nottingham, where I passed 2 or 3 days, &amp; from thence took stage-coach to London.</p>
         <p>When I arrived there, I found Professor Turner had been dead above a fortnight, &amp; being
					cocker'd and spirited up by some Friends (tho' it was rather of the latest) I got my name suggested to Ld B:. you may easily imagine, who undertook it; &amp; indeed he did it with zeal. I received my answer very soon, wch was what you may easily imagine, but join'd with great professions of <hi rend="italic">his
						desire to serve me</hi> on any future occasion, &amp; many more fine words, that I pass over, not out of modesty, but for another
					reason. so you see I have made my fortune, like Sr Fr: Wronghead. this <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>
					is a profound secret, and no one here suspects it even now: today I hear, that Delaval has got it, but we are not yet certain: next to
					myself I wish'd for him.</p>
         <p>You see we have made a peace. I shall be silent about it, because if I say anything
					antiministerial, you will tell me, you know the reason; &amp; if I approve it, you will tell me, I have expectations still. all I know
					is, that the D: of Newcastle &amp; Ld Hardwick both say, it is an excellent Peace; &amp; only Mr Pitt calls it inglorious &amp;
					insidious.</p>
         <p>I had a little Gout twice, while I was in Town, wch confined me some time: yet I bespoke your chairs. they are what is call'd <hi rend="italic">Rout-Chairs,</hi> but as they are to be a little better in shape &amp; materials than ordinary, will come to about 6s 9d
					a chair. I desired your Brother to judge, how he perform'd, &amp; the first, that was made, was to be sent him to see.</p>
         <p>My best respects attend Mrs Wharton, who I suppose, receives them in bed. how does she doe? My compliments to Miss.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am ever truly<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <dateline>Cambridge. Dec: 4. 1762. </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Mason is in Yorkshire now, but I miss'd of him. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
