<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Henrietta Jane Speed to Thomas Gray (25 August 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="MOLI">Morgan Library &amp; Museum</institution>
                  <repository>Department of Literary and Historical Manuscripts (LHMS)</repository>
                  <idno>PML 16518 (extra-illustrated copy of Gray's Odes), 16</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>
                     <cit>
                        <quote>"Thanking him for his friendship, giving news of Lady Cobham, urging him to go to the country rather than withstanding the heat of London, and commenting on news of the "K. of P." and others. [With notes (a list) on the verso, perhaps in Gray's hand.]"</quote>
                        <bibl>Nelson, Christine, "extra-illustrated copy of Gray's Odes". E-mail to the editor, 14 November 2006</bibl>
                     </cit>
                  </p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat each is in MS. Toynbee d.32 and c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 300, vol. ii, 636-638
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=300</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section V, 198-200
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:198</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0347">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high">Speed, Henrietta Jane, 1728-1783</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1759-08-25"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0347">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>25th August 59 </dateline>
            <salute>My dear Sir, </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I wonder whether you think me capable of all the gratitude I really feel for the late marks you have given me of your friendship, I
					will venture to say if you knew my heart you wou'd be content with it, but knowing my exterior so well as you do You can easily
					conceive me Vain of the Partiallity you show me; in return for puting me in good humour with myself I will give you pleasure by
					assuring you Lady Cobham is surprizingly well &amp; most extremely oblig'd to you for the Anxiety you
					express'd on her account.–we now take the Air ev'ry day and are returnd to our old way of living and hope we shall go on in the
					same way many Years. </p>
         <p>we are both scandaliz'd at your being in Town at this time of year, not because (as you may think) that it is unfashionable, but
					because we think it very unwholsome from the heat of the Season – now I know you are insensible to heat or cold, not but that
					your Body suffers by either extreme, but you have not attention enough to your self to seek a remedy, we beg now to point out one
					against the Excessive heat of London, by desiring you wou'd come down to Stoke where you will find
					Ev'ry thing cool but the reception we shall give you–there is always a Bed Air'd for you &amp; one for your Servt; indeed I can
					make use of the Strongest argument to tempt you which is that at this time it will be a deed of Charity as we are absolutely alone. Mrs
					Clavering and Mr Crane the Apothecary left us Yesterday, I dont know whether you are acquainted with the latter but I have such a
					partiallity from his attendance on Lady Cobham that I almost wish for a Slight fit of illness that I may have something to do with him
					– if you are at present an invalide let that prompt you to come, for from the <hi rend="italic">affected creature</hi> you knew
					me, I am nothing now but a comfortable nurse –</p>
         <p>You sent me dreadfull News in regard to the K. of P. I now begin to fear for him, it was vastly
					good of you to Give us a detail of what passes in the World for few People will be at that trouble, indeed a certain Countess with whom
					I correspond does not Spare pains, but such news as she sends is not always to be depended on – I have kept her last Letter for
					your Entertainment;</p>
         <p>I am au desespoire about my friend L. G. S. and am sorry from different hands to hear that his
					narative is about as much in his favor as you seem to think his Letter to Co:l Fitzroy – I
					hope to talk all these matters over with you soon therefore shall add no more at present but that I am with great truth</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Dear Mr Greys <lb/> faithfull Servt </salute>
            <signed>HENRIETTA JANE SPEED </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>never make Excuses about franks for I never shall grudge the Expence you put me to by your Letters. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
