<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Dodsley (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 1 February 1768)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Add. MSS 38511</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>9 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">320 mm x 200 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 465, vol. iii, 999-1001
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=465</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Athenæum</title>, 18 Mar. 1899, printed by Arnold Glover, 388
			</bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0521">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1768-02-01"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314332">Dodsley, James, 1724-1797</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0521">
			   <body>
				
				
				
				     <p> Let the Title be only <hi>Poems by M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Gray</hi> without any mention of notes or additions. you will judge,
					whether what few notes there are should stand at bottom of each page, or be thrown to the end. all I
					desire is, that the text be accurately printed, &amp; therefore whoever corrects the press, should have some acquaintance with the
					Greek, Latin, &amp; Italian, as well as the English, tongues. let the order stand thus, unless you have begun to print already: if so,
					it is indifferent to me.</p>
				     <list>
					       <item>1. Ode. (Lo, where the rosy-bosom'd &amp;c:)</item>
					       <item>2. Ode, on the death of a favourite Cat.</item>
					       <item>3. Ode, on a distant prospect of Eton-College.</item>
					       <item>4. Ode, to Adversity.</item>
					       <item>5. The progress of Poësy, a Pindaric Ode.</item>
					       <item>6. The Bard, a Pindaric Ode.</item>
					       <item>7. The Fatal Sisters.</item>
					       <item>8. The Descent of Odin.</item>
					       <item>9. The Triumphs of Owen, a fragment.</item>
					       <item>10. Elegy, written in a country church-yard.</item>
				     </list>
				     <p> You will print the four first &amp; the last from your own large edition (first publish'd with M<hi rend="super">r</hi> B:<hi rend="super">s</hi> plates) in the 5<hi rend="super">th</hi> &amp; 6<hi rend="super">th</hi> you will
					do well to follow the edition printed at St:<hi rend="super">y</hi>-hill: I mention this, because
					there are several little faults of the press in your Miscellanies. remember, the <hi>Long Story</hi>
					must be quite omitted. now for the notes.</p>
				     <p> [...]<lb/> [...]<lb/> [...]<lb/>
				     </p>
				     <p> I hope, you have not begun to reprint: but if you have, you must throw the notes, &amp;c: to the end, or where you please, omitting
					the mottoes, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> do not much signify. When you have done, I shall desire you to present in my name a copy to M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Walpole in Arlington-street, another to M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Daines Barrington (he is one of the Welch Judges) in the Inner-Temple; &amp; a third to M<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					       <hi>J: Butler at Andover:</hi> whether this latter Gentleman be living or not, or in that
					neighbourhood, I am ignorant: but you will oblige me in making the enquiry. if you have no better means of knowing, a line directed to
					the Post-mistress at Andover will bring you information. after this you may (if you please) bestow another copy or two on me.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> I am<lb/> Your obed<hi rend="super">t</hi> humble Servant </salute>
					       <signed> T. Gray. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p> P:S: It is M<hi rend="super">r</hi>
						         <hi>Foulis of Glasgow</hi>, that prints them in Scotland: he has been told, that you are doing the same. I have desired, he would not
						print a great number, &amp; could wish the same of you.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
