<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (27 June 1755)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 197, vol. i, 422-425
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=197</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter IX, 29-34
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:29</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXIX, vol. i, 263-267
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:263</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0228">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7013260">Hanover, Germany</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1755-06-27"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="poem">Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Young, Dr. Edward</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Whitehead, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Italy</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hanover</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hamburg</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Germany</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0228">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Amongst the variety of rational entertainments that Travel affords to a thinking mind, I have always rankd with the principal that
					fund wch it presents of new Ideas, peculiarly proper to be thrown upon paper in order to form that wch we call a free Epistolary
						correspondence. An easy Communication of Sentiments neither obscurd by a cloud of reserve, wch is
					always dissagreable to an amicable reader nor embarrassd by a Burthen of terms recherchés wch is always full as unpleasing to a
					negligent writer, is the very thing wch I should always labor to attain in my productions of this kind, tho perhaps my aim is totally
					chimerical as the stile I speak of may be calld with the Poet </p>
         <q>
            <p>A faultless Monster wch the world neer saw.</p>
         </q>
         <p>Therefore without further apology I shall trust to the sincerity of your friendship for a plenary Absolution in this case And proceed
					in all the simplicity of Narration.</p>
         <p>Germany is a country–But why should I tell my Friend who has seen France who has seen Italy
					what kind of a country is Germany. And yet perhaps he will not dispise me for it. For tho France is remarkable for its savoir-vivre and
					Italy for its Virtù. Yet Germany is the reservoir of solid Litterature &amp; therefore not unworthy of the attention of a Person who
					unites all these qualifications in his own particular and may be calld without flattery a Microcosm of the talents both of his own
					Island &amp; the continent. But Hard very hard is my fate that I cannot give him any satisfactory account of the state of Germanic
					Learning Having only as yet had a single Interview with MynHerr Shite the Royal Librarian of this place. MynnHerr Shite is of a
					roundish squab figure and of a face corresponding, that is as his Body is cylindrical, his face is rather circular than Oval, He
					apparells himself generally in a decent grass-green Suit. With a fair full Peruke not too full to break upon the spherical form of his
					cheeks &amp; yet full enough to add a graceful squarness on each side of them. The Altitude of his square-toedshoe heels the breadth of
					his Milk and waterd Rollups and the size of his amber-headed Cane are all truly symbolical not only
					of his own Genius but of that of all his Compatriots. When I say that Mynheer Shite is the only erudite person whom I have yet seen, I
					must be understood to mean in this place, for when I lately made a tour to Hamburg, I met with another tho of a different Sex, her name
					Madam Belcht. Her person I will not attempt to describe But will endeavor to give you a morceau of Her Conversation, for I was honord
					with it, She askd me who was the famous Poet that writ the Nitt toats. I replyd Doctr Yonge. She begd
					leave to drink his Health in a Glass of sweet wine adding that he was her favrite English Author. We toasted the Doctor. Upon wch
					having a mind to give my Parnassian Toast, I askd Madame Belch if she had ever read La Petite Elegie dans La Cœmeterie Rustique, C'est
					Beaucoup Jolie je vous Assure! (for I had said fort jolie very often before). Oui Monsr (replyd Madame Belch) Je lu, &amp; elle est
					bien Jolie &amp; Melancholique mais elle ne touche point La Cœur comme mes tres cheres Nitt toats.</p>
         <p>The Prudence you recommended to me at parting &amp; wch you yourself are so remarkable for I shall strictly observe &amp; therefore
					will say nothing of the Place I am in. Indeed I have nothing to say if I was not prudent, only that it is the noisiest Place I ever was
					in, &amp; that I want to get out of it, wch I hope is no treason. I have sent Lord John Cavendish a
					list of the Noises &amp; their times of beginning wch will give you some Idea if he shews you the Letter.</p>
         <p>Oh Mr Gray! I bought at Hamburg such a piano Forte, and so cheap, it is a Harpsichord too of 2
					Unisons &amp; the Jacks serve as mutes (when the Piano Forte stop is playd) by the cleverest mechanism imaginable. Wont you buy my Kirkman?
				</p>
         <p>Pray Mr Gray write soon (how strangly is my stile changd since the beginning!) and tell me about Rousseau or any thing. It's great
					Charity, I do assure you; I would have writ to you before but Hamburg &amp; Reviews prevented me. Whitehead head is here with his two
						lordlings. You would delight in Lord Newnam, he's so peevish &amp;
					hates things so much &amp; has so much sense. Lord Villiers is Plumer exceedingly polishd. Whitehead talks rather too much of Princesses of the Blood in a way between jest &amp; earnest that most
					people must mistake &amp; take for Admiration. The rest of the English are Earl of Peterhouse,
						Sutton, &amp; just now Bagnal of Trinity, With Grooms, Dogs,
					Tutors &amp; all. Whitworth is also soon expected so that I think we shall soon have a pretty Partie
					enough. O the Duce take that confounded Drum &amp; fife it plagues me past endurance.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I cannot write a word more adieu &amp; beleive me Yours<lb/> with the greatest Sincerity </salute>
            <signed>W. MASON. </signed>
            <dateline>Hanover June 27th 55 </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
