<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (6 August 1755)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 71-72</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">202 mm x 163 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 199, vol. i, 427-428
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=199</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXX, vol. i, 267-268
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/267</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XLVII, vol. ii, 256-258
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/256</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LIV, vol. iii, 131-133
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/131</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0230">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1755-08-06"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="poem">The Bard. A Pindaric Ode</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Windsor</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Winchester</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Twickenham</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Titchfield</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Strawberry-Hill</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Southampton</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Portsmouth</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Portsdown</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Porchester Castle</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Newmarket</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Netley Abbey</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Isle of Wight</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hampshire</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Gosport</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Fareham</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Calshot Castle</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Berkshire</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0230">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton, M:D:</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Kings-Arms Yard, Coleman</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>7 AV</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Aug: 6. 1755. Stoke. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Doctor</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I was just returned from my Hampshire expedition, &amp; going to enquire after your little family,
					&amp; how they had got over the measles, when I found a Letter from Stonhewer, in wch he says nothing on that head; whence I conclude
					they are out of danger, &amp; you free from anxiety about them. but he tells me, you expect me in
					town, for wch I am at a loss to account, having said nothing to that purpose, at least I am sure, nothing with that meaning. I said, I
					was to go to Twickenham, &amp; am now expecting a letter from Mr. W: to inform me, when he shall be
					there. my stay will be at farthest a week with him, &amp; at my return I shall let you know, &amp; if the season be better than it now
					is, enquire, if you continue inclined to visit Windsor &amp; its Environs. I wished for you often on the Southern Coast, where I have
						been, &amp; made much the same Tour, that Stonhewer did before me. take notice, that the Oaks grow
					quite down to the Beach, &amp; that the Sea forms a number of Bays little &amp; great, that appear glittering in the midst of thick
					Groves of them. add to this the Fleet (for I was at Portsmouth two days before it sail'd) &amp; the
					number of Vessels always passing along, or sailing up Southampton-River (wch is the largest of these Bays I mention) and enters about
					10 mile into the Land, &amp; you will have a faint Idea of the <hi rend="italic">South.</hi> from Fareham to Southampton, where you are
					upon a level with the coast, you have a thousand such Peeps &amp; delightful Openings, but would you see the whole at once, you must
					get upon Ports-Down 5 Mile on this side Portsmouth. it is the top of a ridge, that forms a natural Terrass 3 Mile long, literally not
					three times broader than Windsor-Terrass with a gradual fall on both sides &amp; cover'd with a turf like New-Market. to the North
					opens Hampshire &amp; Berkshire cover'd with woods, &amp; interspersed with numerous Gentlemen's Houses &amp; Villages. to the South,
					Portsmouth, Gosport, &amp;c: just at your foot in appearance, the Fleet, the Sea winding, &amp; breaking in bays into the land, the
					deep shade of tall Oaks in the enclosures, wch become blue, as they go off to distance, Portchester-Castle, Carshot-Castle, &amp; all the Isle of Wight, in wch you plainly distinguish the fields, hedge-rows, &amp; woods next the
					shore, &amp; a back-ground of hills behind them. I have not seen a more magnificent or more varied Prospect. I have been also at
					Tichfield, at Netly-Abbey, (a most beautiful Ruin in as beautiful a situation) at Southampton, at
						Bevis-Mount, at Winchester, &amp;c: my Gout is gone, but I am not absolutely well yet. I hear Mason
					was expected on Monday last, but was not to speak of it, therefore you will say nothing till you see him. I do not understand this, nor
					what he means by coming. It seems wrong to me. what did you think of the <hi rend="italic">Morceau</hi>
					 I sent you, pray, speak your mind.</p>
         <p>My best Compliments to Mrs. Wharton.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, I am <lb/> Ever Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
