<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Horace Walpole to Thomas Gray (26 February 1768)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 472, vol. iii, 1021-1023
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=472</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Horatio Walpole, Earl of Orford</title>, 5 vols. London: G. G. and J. Robinson and J. Edwards, 1798, vol. v, 376-378
			</bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 241, vol. ii, 281-285
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/TyP_1915ii/1/281</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 175-178
				<ref type="url">https://libsvcs-1.its.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=175</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0528">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1768-02-26"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Dodsley, James, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Stow, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Lyttelton, George Lyttelton, 1st Lord</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hume, David</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Guthrie, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Cornwallis, Sir William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Commynes, Philip de</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Catalogue of the MSS. of the King's Library</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Kimbolton Castle</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0528">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Arlington-street, Friday night, February 26.</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>I plague you to death, but I must reply a few more words. I shall be very glad to see in print, and to have those that are worthy see
					your ancient odes; but I was in hopes there were some pieces too that I had not seen. I am sorry there are not. </p>
         <p>I troubled you about Perkin's proclamation, because Mr. Hume lays great stress upon it, and insists, that if Perkin affirmed his
					brother was killed, it must have been true, if he was true duke of York. Mr. Hume would have persuaded me that the proclamation is in
					Stowe, but I can find no such thing there; nor, what is more, in Casley's catalogue, which I have twice looked over carefully. I wrote
					to sir David Dalrymple in Scotland, to enquire after it, because I would produce it if I could, though
					it should make against me: but he, I believe, thinking I enquired with the contrary view, replied very drily, that it was published at
					York, and was not to be found in Scotland. Whether he is displeased that I have plucked a hair from the tresses of their great
						historian; or whether, as I suspect, he is offended for king William; this reply was all the notice he took of my letter and book. I only smiled, as I must do when I find one party is angry with me on
					king William's, and the other on lord Clarendon's account.</p>
         <p>The answer advertised is Guthrie's, who is furious that I have taken no notice of <hi rend="italic">his</hi> History. I shall take as little of his pamphlet; but his end will be answered, if he sells that and one or two copies of his
					History. Mr. Hume, I am told, has drawn up an answer too, which I shall see, and, if I can, will get him to publish; for, if I should ever choose to say any thing more on this subject, I had rather reply to him than to
					hackney-writers: –to the latter, indeed, I never will reply. A few notes I have to add that
					will be very material; and I wish to get some account of a book that was once sold at Osborn's, that
					exists perhaps at Cambridge, and of which I found a memorandum t'other day in my note-book. It is called A paradox, or apology for
					Richard III. by sir William Cornwallis. If you could discover it, I should be much obliged to you.</p>
         <p>Lord Sandwich, with whom I have not exchanged a syllable since the general warrants, very obligingly
					sent me an account of the roll at Kimbolton; and has since, at my desire, borrowed it for me and sent
					it to town. It is as long as my lord Lyttelton's History; but by what
					I can read of it (for it is both ill-written and much decayed), it is not a roll of kings, but of all that have been possessed of, or
					been earls of Warwick: or have not–for one of the first earls is Æneas. How, or wherefore, I do not know, but amongst the first
					is Richard III. in whose reign it was finished, and with whom it concludes. He is there again with his wife and son, and Edward IV. and
						Clarence and his wife, and Edward their son (who unluckily is a little old man), and Margaret
					countess of Salisbury, their daughter–But why do I say with these? There is every body else too–and what is most
					meritorious, the habits of all the times are admirably well observed from the most savage ages. Each figure is tricked with a pen, well
					drawn, but neither coloured nor shaded. Richard is straight, but thinner than my print; his hair short, and exactly curled in the same
					manner; not so handsome as mine, but what one might really believe intended for the same countenance, as drawn by a different painter,
					especially when so small; for the figures in general are not so long as one's finger. His queen is ugly, and with just such a square
					forehead as in my print, but I cannot say like it. Nor, indeed, where forty-five figures out of fifty (I have not counted the number)
					must have been imaginary, can one lay great stress on the five. I shall, however, have these figures copied, especially as I know of no
					other image of the son. Mr. Astle is to come to me to-morrow morning to explain the writing.</p>
         <p>I wish you had told me in what age your Franciscan friars lived; and what the passage in Comines is.
					I am very ready to make amende honorable.</p>
         <p>Thank you for the notes on the Noble Authors. They shall be inserted when I make a new edition, for the sake of the trouble the
					person has taken, though they are of little consequence. Dodsley has asked me for a new edition; but I
					have had little heart to undertake such work, no more than to mend my old linen. It is pity one cannot be born an ancient, and have
					commentators to do such jobs for one!</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!<lb/> Yours ever, </salute>
            <signed>HOR. WALPOLE. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Saturday morning. </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>On reading over your letter again this morning, I do find the age in which the friars lived–I read and write in such a hurry,
						that I think I neither know what I read or say. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
