<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>J. Butler to Thomas Gray (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 23 January 1758)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 265*, vol. ii, 558-559
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=265*</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, imitations, variations, and additional notes, 88, 90-91
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:2:88</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0306">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high">Butler, J., Mr</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011400">Andover, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1758-01-23"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0306">
			   <body>
				
				
				     <p>[           ]</p>
				     <p>A poet is perhaps never more conciliating than when he praises favourite predecessors in his art. Milton is not more the pride than
					Shakespear the love of their country: It is therefore equally judicious to diffuse a tenderness and a grace through the praise of
					Shakespear, as to extol in a strain more elevated and sonorous the boundless soarings of Milton's epic imagination.
				</p>
				     <p>[           ]</p>
				     <p>I quit this Ode with the strongest conviction of its abundant merit; though I took it up, (for this
					last attentive perusal) persuaded that it was not a little inferior to the other. They are not the treasures of imagination only that
					have so copiously enriched it: It speaks, but surely less feelingly than the Bard, (still my favourite) to the heart. Can we in truth
					be equally interested, for the fabulous exploded Gods of other nations (celebrated in the first half of this Ode) as by the story of
					our own Edwards and Henrys, or allusions to it? Can a description, the most perfect language ever attained to, of tyranny expelling the
					muses from Parnassus, seize the mind equally with the horrors of Berkley Castle, with the apostrophe
					to the tower? <q>
						         <p>And spare the meek Usurper's holy head!
						</p>
					       </q> I do not mean, however, wholly to decry fabulous subjects or allusions, nor more than to suggest the preference due to historical
					ones, where happily the Poet's fertile imagination supplies him with a plentiful choice of both kinds, and he finds himself capable of
					treating both, according to their respective natures, with equal advantage. </p>
				     <p>[           ]</p>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
