<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (3 January 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 197-199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>5 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">228 mm x 180 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 511, vol. iii, 1094-1098
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=511</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iv, section v, 360-364
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:360</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, journal 4, vol. iii, 244-264
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:244</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section V, letter VIII/IX, vol. ii, 531-549
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:531</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section V, letter IX, vol. iv, 154-178
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:154</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXLIV, vol. ii, 146-165
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:146</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0573">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-01-03"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0573">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Thos. Wharton Esq. of Old Park near Darlington Durham</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="journal">
            <p rendition="#center">Journal continued. </p>
            <p>3 Jan: 1770. Pemb: C: </p>
            <p>Oct: 5. Wd N:E: Clouds &amp; sunshine. Walk'd thro' the meadows &amp; corn-fields to the Derwent &amp; crossing it went up <hi rend="italic">How-hill.</hi> it looks along Bassinthwaite -water &amp; sees at the same time the
						course of the river &amp; a part of the Upper-Lake with a full view of Skiddaw. then I took my way through Portingskall village to the <hi rend="italic">Park,</hi> a hill so call'd cover'd entirely with wood: it is all a mass
						of crumbling slate. pass'd round its foot between the trees &amp; the edge of the water, &amp; came to a Peninsula that juts out into
						the lake &amp; looks along it both ways. in front rises Walla-crag, &amp; Castle-hill, the Town, the road to Penrith, Skiddaw &amp;
						Saddleback. returning met a brisk and cold N: Eastern blast, that ruffled all the surface of ye lake and made it rise in little waves
						that broke at the foot of the wood. After dinner walked up the Penrith-road 2 miles or more &amp; turning into a corn-field to the
						right, call'd Castle-Rigg, saw a Druid-Circle of large stones 108 feet in diameter, the biggest not 8 feet high, but most of them
						still erect: they are 50 in number. the valley of St John's appear'd in sight, &amp; the summits of
							<hi rend="italic">Catchidecam</hi> (called by Camden, <hi rend="italic">Casticand</hi>) &amp; <hi rend="italic">Helvellyn,</hi> said
						to be as high as <hi rend="italic">Skiddaw,</hi> &amp; to rise from a much higher base. a shower came on, &amp; I return'd.</p>
            <p>Oct: 6. Wd E: Clouds &amp; sun. went in a chaise 8 miles along the east-side of Bassingth: Water
						to <hi rend="italic">Ouse-Bridge</hi> (pronounce <hi rend="italic">Ews-bridge</hi>) the road in some part made &amp; very good, the
						rest slippery &amp; dangerous cart-road, or narrow rugged lanes but no precipices: it runs directly along the foot of Skiddaw.
						opposite to <hi rend="italic">Widhope-Brows</hi>
						 (cloth'd to the top with wood) a very beautiful view opens down the Lake, wch is narrower &amp;
						longer than that of Keswick, less broken into bays &amp; without islands. at the foot of it a few paces from the brink gently sloping
						upward stands <hi rend="italic">Armathwate</hi> in a thick grove of Scotch firs, commanding a noble
						view directly up the lake. at a small distance behind the house is a large extent of wood, &amp; still behind this a ridge of
						cultivated hills, on wch (according to the Keswick-proverb) <hi rend="italic">the Sun always shines.</hi> the inhabitants here on the
						contrary call the vale of Derwent-water <hi rend="italic">the Devil's Chamber-pot,</hi> &amp; pronounce the name of <hi rend="italic">Skiddaw-fell</hi> (wch terminates here) with a sort of terror &amp; aversion. <hi rend="italic">Armathwate-House</hi> is a modern
						fabrick, not large, &amp; built of dark-red stone, belonging to Mr <hi rend="italic">Spedding,</hi> whose Gr:father was Steward to old
						Sr <hi rend="italic">Ja: Lowther,</hi>
						 &amp; bought this estate of the <hi rend="italic">Himers.</hi> so you must look for Mr Michell in
						some other country. the sky was overcast &amp; the wind cool, so after dining at a publick house, wch stands here near the bridge
						(that crosses the Derwent just where it issues from the lake) &amp; sauntering a little by the water-side I came home again. the
						turnpike is finish'd from Cockermouth hither (5 miles) &amp; is carrying on to Penrith. several little showers to-day. A Man came in,
						who said there was snow on <hi rend="italic">Cross-fell</hi> this morning.</p>
            <p>Oct: 7. Market-day here. Wd N:E: Clouds &amp; Sunshine. little showers at intervals all day. yet walk'd in the morning to Crow-park,
						&amp; in the evening up Penrith-road. the clouds came rolling up the mountains all round very [unpromising]; yet the moon shone at intervals. it was too damp to go towards the lake. tomorrow mean to bid farewell to
						Keswick.</p>
            <p>Botany might be studied here to great advantage at another season because of the great variety of soils &amp; elevations all lieing
						within a small compass. I observed nothing but several curious Lichens, &amp; plenty of gale or Dutch myrtle perfuming the borders of
						ye lake. this year the Wadd mine had been open'd (which is done once in 5 years) it is taken out in
						lumps sometimes as big as a man's fist, &amp; will undergo no preparation by fire, not being fusible. when it is pure soft, black,
						&amp; close-grain'd, it is worth sometimes 30 shillings a pound. there are no Charr ever taken in
						these lakes, but plenty in Butter-mere-water, which lies a little way N: of Borrodale, about Martlemas, wch are potted here. they sow chiefly oats &amp; bigg here, wch are now cutting, &amp; still on
						the ground. the rains have done much hurt; yet observe, the soil is so thin &amp; light, that no day
						has pass'd, in wch I could not walk out with ease, &amp; you know, I am no lover of dirt.
						Fell-mutton is now in season for about six weeks; it grows fat on ye mountains, &amp; nearly resembles venison: excellent Pike &amp;
						Perch (here called <hi rend="italic">Bass</hi>) trout is out of season. partridge in great plenty.
						Rec:t to dress Perch (for Mrs Wharton) </p>
            <p>Wash, but neither scale, nor gut them. broil till enough; then pull out the fins, &amp; open them along ye back, take out the bone
						&amp; all the inwards without breaking them. put in a large lump of butter &amp; salt, clap the sides together, till it melts, &amp;
						serve very hot. it it excellent. the skin must not be eaten.
					</p>
            <p>Oct: 8. Left Keswick &amp; took the Ambleside-road in a gloomy morning. Wd E: &amp; afterwds N:E:. about 2 m: from the Town mounted
						an eminence call'd <hi rend="italic">Castle-rigg,</hi> &amp; the sun breaking out discover'd the most enchanting view I have yet seen
						of the whole valley behind me, the two lakes, the river, the mountains all in their glory! had almost a mind to have gone back again.
						the road in some few parts is not compleated, but good country-road thro' sound, but narrow &amp; stony lanes, very safe in broad
						day-light. this is the case about <hi rend="italic">Causeway-foot</hi> &amp; among Naddle-Fells to <hi rend="italic">Lanewaite.</hi>
						the vale you go in has little breadth, the mountains are vast &amp; rocky, the fields little &amp; poor, &amp; the inhabitants are now
						making hay, &amp; see not the sun by two hours in a day so long as at Keswick. came to the foot of Helvellyn along wch runs an
						excellent road, looking down from a little height on <hi rend="italic">Lee's-water</hi>
						 (call'd also Thirl-meer, or Wiborn -water) &amp; soon descending
						on its margin. the lake from its depth looks black (tho' really clear as glass) &amp; from the gloom of the vast crags, that scowl
						over it: it is narrow &amp; about 3 miles long, resembling a river in its course. little shining torrents hurry down the rocks to join
						it, with not a bush to overshadow them, or cover their march. all is rock &amp; loose stones up to the very brow, wch lies so near
						your way, that not half the height of Helvellyn can be seen.. (to be continued, but now we have got franks)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>Happy new year &amp; many to you all. Hepatica &amp; Mezereon now in flower! I saw Mrs
							Jonathan, who is much fallen away, &amp; was all in tears for the loss of her Brother's child: she
						&amp; Miss Wilson desired their compliments. your nephew is here
						&amp; very well. so is Mr Brown, who presents his best wishes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <p>Past by the little Chappel of Wiborn, out of wch the Sunday-congregation were then issuing.</p>
            <p>Past a beck near <hi rend="italic">Dunmail-raise,</hi> &amp; enter'd <hi rend="italic">Westmoreland</hi> a second time. now begin to
						see <hi rend="italic">Helm-Crag</hi> distinguish'd from its rugged neighbours not so much by its height, as by the strange broken
						outline of its top, like some gigantic building demolish'd, &amp; the stones that composed it, flung cross each other in wild
						confusion. just beyond it opens one of the sweetest landscapes, that art ever attempted to imitate. (the bosom of ye mountains
						spreading here into a broad bason) discovers in the midst Grasmere-water. its margin is hollow'd into small bays with bold eminences
						some of rock, some of soft turf, that half conceal, and vary the figure of the little lake they command, from the shore a low
						promontory pushes itself far into the water, &amp; on it stands a white village with the parish-church rising in the midst of it,
						hanging enclosures, corn-fields, &amp; meadows green as an emerald with their trees &amp; hedges &amp; cattle fill up the whole space
						from the edge of the water &amp; just opposite to you is a large farm-house at the bottom of a steep smooth lawn embosom'd in old
						woods, wch climb half way up the mountain's side, &amp; discover above them a broken line of crags, that crown the scene. not a single
						red tile, no flaring Gentleman's house, or garden-walls, break in upon the repose of this little unsuspected paradise, but all is
						peace, rusticity, &amp; happy poverty in its neatest most becoming attire. </p>
            <p>The road winds here over <hi rend="italic">Grasmere</hi>-hill, whose rocks soon conceal the water from your sight, yet it is
						continued along behind them, &amp; contracting itself to a river communicates with Ridale-water, another small lake, but of inferior
						size &amp; beauty. it seems shallow too, for large patches of reeds appear pretty far within it. into this vale the road descends. on
						the opposite banks large &amp; ancient woods mount up the hills, &amp; just to the left of our way stands <hi rend="italic">Rydale</hi>-hall, the family-seat of Sr Mic: Fleming, but now a farm-house, a large old-fashion'd
						fabrick surrounded with wood &amp; not much too good for its present destination. Sr Michael is now on his travels, &amp; all this
						timber far &amp; wide belongs to him. I tremble for it, when he returns. near the house rises a huge crag call'd <hi rend="italic">Rydale-head,</hi> wch is said to command a full view of Wynander-mere, &amp; I doubt it not, for within a mile that great Lake is
						visible even from the road. as to going up the crag one might as well go up Skiddaw.</p>
            <p>Came to Ambleside, 18 m: from Keswick meaning to lie there, but on looking into the best bed-chamber dark &amp; damp as a cellar
						grew delicate, gave up Winandermere in despair &amp; resolved I would go on to <hi rend="italic">Kendal</hi> directly, 14 m: farther.
						the road in general fine turnpike, but some parts (about 3 m: in all) not made, yet without danger.</p>
            <p>Unexpectedly was well-rewarded for my determination. the afternoon was fine, &amp; the road for full 5 m: runs along the side of
						Winder-mere with delicious views across it &amp; almost from one end to the other. it is ten miles in length, &amp; at most a mile
						over, resembling the course of some vast &amp; magnificent river, but no flat marshy grounds, no osier-beds, or patches of scrubby
						plantation on its banks. at the head two vallies open among the mountains, one that by wch we came down, the other <hi rend="italic">Langsledale,</hi>
						 in wch <hi rend="italic">Wreenose</hi>
						 &amp; <hi rend="italic">Hard-Knot,</hi> two great mountains, rise above the rest. from thence the
						fells visibly sink &amp; soften along its sides, sometimes they run into it (but with a gentle declivity) in their own dark &amp;
						natural complexion, oftener they are green &amp; cultivated with farms interspersed &amp; round eminences on the border cover'd with
						trees: towards the South it seem'd to break into larger bays with several islands &amp; a wider extent of cultivation. the way rises
						continually till at a place call'd <hi rend="italic">Orrest-head</hi> it turns to S:E: losing sight of the water.</p>
            <p>Pass'd by <hi rend="italic">Ings-Chappel, &amp; Staveley,</hi> but I can say no farther, for the dusk of evening coming on I enter'd
							<hi rend="italic">Kendal</hi> almost in the dark, &amp; could distinguish only a shadow of the Castle on a hill, &amp;
							tenter-grounds spread far &amp; wide round the Town, wch I mistook for houses. my inn promised
						sadly having two wooden galleries (like Scotland) in front of it. it was indeed an old ill-contrived house, but kept by civil sensible
						people, so I stay'd two nights with them &amp; fared &amp; slept very comfortably.</p>
            <p>Oct: 9. Wd N:W: clouds &amp; sun. air mild as summer. all corn off the ground, sky-larks singing aloud (by the way I saw not one at
						Keswick, perhaps because the place abounds in birds of prey). went up the Castle-hill. the Town consists chiefly of three nearly
						parallel streets almost a mile long. except these all the other houses seem as if they had been dancing a country-dance &amp; were
						out: there they stand back to back, corner to corner, some up hill, some down without intent or meaning. along by their side runs a
						fine brisk stream, over which are 3 stone-bridges. the buildings (a few comfortable houses excepted) are mean, of stone &amp; cover'd
						with a bad rough-cast. near the end of the Town stands a handsome house of Col: Wilson's, &amp; adjoining to it the Church, a very
						large Gothick fabrick with a square Tower. it has no particular ornaments but double isles, &amp; at the east-end 4 chappels, or
						choirs. one of the <hi rend="italic">Pars,</hi> another of the <hi rend="italic">Stricklands,</hi> the 3d is the proper choir of ye
						church, &amp; the 4th of ye <hi rend="italic">Bellingcams,</hi> a family now extinct.  is an
						altar-tomb of one of them dated 1577 with a flat brass, arms &amp; quarterings. &amp; in the window their arms alone, Arg: a
						hunting-horn, sab: strung Gules. in the <hi rend="italic">Strickland's</hi> chappel several modern monuments, &amp; another old
						altar-tomb, not belonging to the family: on the side of it, a Fess dancetty between 10 Billets (Deincourt?) in the <hi rend="italic">Parr</hi>-chappel is a third altar-tomb in the corner, no fig: or inscription,
						but on the side cut in stone an escutcheon of <hi rend="italic">Roos</hi> of Kendal (3 Water-Budgets) quartering <hi rend="italic">Parr</hi> (2 bars in a bordure engrail'd). 2dly an escutcheon, Vaire, a Fess (for Marmion). 3dly. an escutcheon. three Chevronels
						braced &amp; a Chief (wch I take for Fitzhugh) at the foot is an escutcheon surrounded with the Garter, bearing <hi rend="italic">Roos</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Parr</hi> quarterly, quartering the other two beforemention'd. I have no books to look in,
						therefore can not say, whether this is the Ld <hi rend="italic">Parr of Kendal</hi> (Queen Catharine's Father) or her Brother, the
						Marquis of <hi rend="italic">Northampton.</hi> it is a Cenotaph for the latter, who was buried at Warwick in 1571. the remains of the Castle are seated on a fine hill on the side of the river opposite to the Town. almost
						the whole enclosure of walls remains with 4 towers, 2 square &amp; 2 or 3 round, but their upper part &amp; embattlements are
						demolished. it is of rough stone &amp; cement, without any ornament or arms, round enclosing a court of like form &amp; surrounded by
						a mote, nor ever could have been larger than it is, for there are no traces of outworks. there is a good view of the town &amp; river
						with a fertile open valley, thro wch it winds. </p>
            <p>After dinner went along the Milthrop -turnpike 4 m: to see the falls (or force) of the river <hi rend="italic">Kent.</hi> came to <hi rend="italic">Siserge</hi> (pronounce Siser) &amp; turn'd down a lane to the left. Siser, the
						seat of the <hi rend="italic">Stricklands</hi>
						 an old Catholick family, is an ancient Hall-house, with a very large tower embattled: the rest of
						the buildings added to this are of later date, but all is white &amp; seen to advantage on a back ground of old trees: there is a
						small park also well-wooded. opposite to this turn'd to the left &amp; soon came to the river. it works its way in a narrow &amp; deep
						rocky channel o'erhung with trees. the calmness &amp; brightness of ye evening, the roar of the waters, &amp; the thumping of huge
						hammers at an iron-forge not far distant made it a singular walk, but as to the falls (for there are two) they are not 4 feet high. I
						went on down to the forge &amp; saw the Dæmons at work by the light of their own fires: the iron is brought in pigs to Milthrop by sea
						from Scotland &amp;c. &amp; is here beat into bars &amp; plates. two miles farther at <hi rend="italic">Levens</hi> is the seat of Ld
							Suffolk, where he sometimes passes the summer. it was a favourite place of his late Countess: but
						this I did not see.</p>
            <p>Oct: 10. went by <hi rend="italic">Burton</hi> to Lancaster. Wd N:W: clouds &amp; sun. 22 m: very good country well enclosed &amp;
						wooded with some common interspersed. pass'd at the foot of <hi rend="italic">Farlton-Knot,</hi> a high fell. 4 m: N: of Lancaster on
						a rising ground call'd <hi rend="italic">Bolton</hi> (pron: <hi rend="italic">Bouton</hi>)-<hi rend="italic">Wait</hi> had a full view
						of <hi rend="italic">Cartmell-sands</hi> with here and there a Passenger riding over them (it being low water) the points of Furness
						shooting far into the sea, &amp; lofty mountains partly cover'd with clouds extending North of them. Lancaster also appear'd very
						conspicuous &amp; fine, for its most distinguish'd features the Castle &amp; Church, mounted on a green eminence, were all, that could
						be seen. woe is me! when I got thither, it was the second day of their fair. the Inn (in the principal street) was a great old gloomy
						house full of people, but I found tolerable quarters, &amp; even slept two nights in peace.</p>
            <p>Ascended the Castle-hill in a fine afternoon. it takes up the higher top of the eminence on wch it stands, &amp; is irregularly
						round, encompassed with a deep mote. in front towards the Town is a magnificent Gothick Gateway, lofty &amp; huge, the overhanging
						battlements are supported by a triple range of corbels, the intervals pierced thro' &amp; shewing the day from above. on its top rise
						light watchtowers of small height. it opens below with a grand pointed arch: over this is a wrought tabernacle, doubtless once
						containing the Founders figure, on one side a shield of France semy quarter'd with England, on the other the same with a label ermine
						for John of Gant D: of Lancaster. this opens to a court within, wch I did not much care to enter, being the County Gaol &amp; full of
						Prisoners, both Criminals &amp; Debtors. from this gateway the walls continue &amp; join it to a vast square tower of great height,
						the lower part at least of remote antiquity, for it has small round-headed lights with plain short pillars on each side of them, there
						is a third tower also square &amp; of less dimensions. this is all the castle, near it &amp; but little lower stands the Church, a
						large &amp; plain Gothic fabrick, the high square Tower at the West-end has been rebuilt of late years, but nearly in the same style.
						there are no ornaments of arms, &amp;c: any where to be seen. within it is lightsome &amp; spacious, but not one monument of
						antiquity, or piece of painted glass is left. from the Church-yard there is an extensive sea-view (for now the tide had almost cover'd
						the sands, &amp; fill'd the river) &amp; besides greatest part of Furness I could distinguish <hi rend="italic">Peel</hi>-Castle on
						the isle of Fowdrey, wch lies off its southern extremity. the Town is built on the slope &amp; at
						the feet of the Castle-hill more than twice the bigness of Aukland with many neat buildings of white stone, but a little disorderly in
						their position ad libitum like Kendal. many also extend below on the keys by the river-side, where a number of ships were moor'd, some
						of them three-mast vessels deck'd out with their colours in honor of the Fair. here is a good bridge of 4 arches over the <hi rend="italic">Lune,</hi> wch runs (when the tide is out) in two streams divided by a bed of gravel, wch is not cover'd but in
						spring-tides. below the town it widens to near the breadth of ye Thames at London, &amp; meets the sea at 5 or 6 m: distance to
						S:W:</p>
            <p>Oct: 11. Wd S:W: clouds &amp; sun. warm &amp; a fine dappled sky. cross'd the river &amp; walk'd over a peninsula 3 miles to the
						village of <hi rend="italic">Pooton</hi> wch stands on the beach. an old Fisherman mending his nets (while I enquired about the danger
						of passing those sands) told me in his dialect a moving story, how a brother of the trade, a <hi rend="italic">Cockler</hi> (as he
						styled him) driving a little cart with two daughters (women grown) in it, &amp; his Wife on horseback following, set out one day to
						pass the 7 mile sands, as they had frequently been used to do, for nobody in the village knew them better than the old Man did. when
						they were about half way over, a thick fog rose, &amp; as they advanced, they found the water much deeper than they expected. the old
						man was puzzled, he stop'd, &amp; said he would go a little way to find some mark he was acquainted with. they staid a little while
						for him, but in vain. they call'd aloud, but no reply. at last the young women press'd their mother to think, where they were, &amp;
						go on. she would not leave the place, she wander'd about forlorn &amp; amazed, she would not quit her horse, &amp; get into the cart
						with them. they determined after much time wasted to turn back, &amp; give themselves up to the guidance of their horses. the old
						Woman was soon wash'd off and perish'd. the poor Girls clung close to their cart, &amp; the horse sometimes wading &amp; sometimes
						swimming brought them back to land alive, but senseless with terror &amp; distress &amp; unable for many days to give any account of
						themselves. the bodies of their parents were found soon after; that of the Father a very few paces
						distant from the spot, where he had left them.
					</p>
            <p>In the afternoon wander'd about the town &amp; by the key till it grew dark. a little rain fell. </p>
            <p>Oct: 11 [12] Wd N:E: sky gloomy, then gleams of sunshine. set out for <hi rend="italic">Settle</hi> by a fine turnpike road, 29 miles.</p>
            <p>Rich &amp; beautiful enclosed country diversified with frequent villages &amp; churches, very unequal ground, &amp; on the left the
						river Lune winding in a deep valley, its hanging banks clothed with fine woods, thro' wch you catch long reaches of the water, as the
						road winds about at a considerable height above it. pass'd the <hi rend="italic">Park</hi> (Hon: Mr Clifford's, a catholick) in the
						most picturesque part of the way. the grounds between him &amp; the river are indeed charming: the house is ordinary, &amp; the park
						nothing but a rocky fell scatter'd over with ancient hawthorns. came to <hi rend="italic">Hornby</hi> a little Town on the river
						Wanning, over wch a handsome bridge is now in building. the Castle in a lordly situation attracted me, so I walkd up the hill to it.
						first presents itself a large but ordinary white Gentleman's house sash'd. behind it rises the ancient Keep built by Edward Stanley,
						Lord Mounteagle (inscribed Helas et quand?) he died about 1524 in Henry the 8th's time. it is now a
						shell only, tho' rafters are laid within it as for flooring. I went up a winding stone-staircase in one corner to the leads, &amp; at
						the angle is a single hexagon watch-tower rising some feet higher, fitted up in the tast of a modern <hi rend="italic">Toot</hi>
						 with sash-windows in gilt frames, &amp; a stucco cupola, &amp; on the top a vast gilt eagle by Mr
							<hi rend="italic">Charteris,</hi>
						 the present Possessor. but he has not lived here since the year 1745, when the people of Lancaster
						insulted him, threw stones into his coach, &amp; almost made his Wife (Lady Katherine Gordon) miscarry. since that he has built a
						great ugly house of red stone (thank God it is not in England) near Haddington, wch I remember to have pass'd by. he is the 2d Son of the Earl of Wemyss, &amp; brother to the Ld Elcho, Grandson to Col: Charteris, whose name he bears.</p>
            <p>From the leads of the Tower there is a fine view of the country round, &amp; much wood near the castle. Ingleborough, wch I had seen
						before distinctly at Lancaster to N:E: was now compleatly wrap'd in clouds all but its summit, wch might have been easily mistaken for
						a long black cloud too, fraught with an approaching storm. now our road begun gradually to mount towards the <hi rend="italic">Apennine,</hi> the trees growing less, and thinner of leaves, till we came to Ingleton 18 m: it is a pretty village situated very
						high &amp; yet in a valley at the foot of that huge creature of God <hi rend="italic">Ingleborough.</hi> two torrents cross it with
						great stones roll'd along their bed instead of water: over them are two handsome arches flung. here at a little ale-house were Sr
						Bellingcam Graham &amp; Mr Parker, Ld of ye Manour (one of them 6 feet ½ high, &amp; the other as
						much in breadth) come to dine.</p>
            <p>The nipping air (tho' the afternoon was growing very bright) now taught us, we were in Craven. the road was all up &amp; down (tho'
						no where very steep). to the left were mountain-tops (Weryside), to the right a wide valley (all
						inclosed ground) &amp; beyond it high hills again. in approaching Settle the crags on the left drew nearer to our way, till we
						ascended <hi rend="italic">Brunton-brow,</hi> into a chearful valley (tho' thin of trees) to <hi rend="italic">Giggleswick</hi> a
						village with a small piece of water by its side cover'd over with coots. near it a Church, wch belongs also to <hi rend="italic">Settle</hi> &amp; half a mile farther having passed the <hi rend="italic">Ribble</hi> over a bridge arrived at <hi rend="italic">Settle.</hi> it is a small market-town standing directly under a rocky fell. there are not a dozen good-looking houses, the rest are
						old &amp; low with little wooden portico's in front. my inn pleased me much (tho' small) for the neatness &amp; civility of the good
						Woman that kept it, so I lay there two nights, &amp; went</p>
            <p>Oct: 12 [13] to visit <hi rend="italic">Gordale-Scar.</hi> Wd N:E: day gloomy &amp; cold. it lay
						but 6 m: from Settle, but that way was directly over a Fell, &amp; it might rain, so I went round in a chaise the only way one could
						get near it in a carriage, wch made it full 13 m: &amp; half of it such a road! but I got safe over it, so there's an end, &amp; came
						to <hi rend="italic">Malham</hi> (pronounce <hi rend="italic">Maum</hi>) a village in the bosom of the mountains seated in a wild
						&amp; dreary valley. from thence I was to walk a mile over very rough ground, a torrent rattling along on the left hand. on the cliffs
						above hung a few goats: one of them danced &amp; scratched an ear with its hind-foot in a place where I would not have stood
						stock-still <q>
                  <p>for all beneath the moon.</p>
               </q> as I advanced the crags seem'd to close in, but discover'd a narrow entrance turning to the left between them. I followed my
						guide a few paces, &amp; lo, the hills open'd again into no large space, &amp; then all farther way is bar'd by a stream, that at the
						height of about 50 feet gushes from a hole in the rock, &amp; spreading in large sheets over its broken front dashes from steep to
						steep, &amp; then rattles away in a torrent down the valley. the rock on the left rises perpendicular with stubbed yew-trees &amp;
						shrubs, staring from its side to the height of at least 300 feet. but these are not the thing! it is that to the right, under wch you
						stand to see the fall, that forms the principal horror of the place. from its very base it begins to slope forwards over you in one
						black &amp; solid mass without any crevice in its surface, &amp; overshadows half the area below with its dreadful canopy. when I
						stood at (I believe) full 4 yards distance from its foot, the drops wch perpetually distill from its brow, fell on my head, &amp; in
						one part of the top more exposed to the weather there are loose stones that hang in air, &amp; threaten visibly some idle Spectator
						with instant destruction. it is safer to shelter yourself close to its bottom, &amp; trust the mercy of that enormous mass, wch
						nothing but an earthquake can stir. the gloomy uncomfortable day well suited the savage aspect of the place, &amp; made it still more
						formidable. I stay'd there (not without shuddering) a quarter of an hour, &amp; thought my trouble richly paid, for the impression
						will last for life. at the alehouse where I dined, in Malham, Vivares, the landscape-painter, had
						lodged for a week or more. Smith &amp; Bellers had also been
						there, &amp; two prints of Gordale have been engraved by them. return'd to my comfortable inn. night fine, but windy &amp; frosty.</p>
            <p>Oct: 13 [14]. Went to Skipton, 16 miles. Wd N:E: gloomy, at one o'clock a little sleet falls. from
						several parts of the road, &amp; in many places about Settle I saw at once the three famous hills of this country, Ingleborough,
						Penigent, &amp; Pendle, the first is esteem'd the highest. their features are hard to describe, but I could trace their outline with a
							pencil.</p>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="/texts/letters/letters.0573.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Craven</hi> after all is an unpleasing country, when seen from a height. its valleys are chiefly wide &amp; either
						marshy, or enclosed pasture with a few trees. numbers of black Cattle are fatted here, both of the Scotch breed, &amp; a larger sort
						of oxen with great horns. there is little cultivated ground, except a few oats.</p>
            <p>[Oct: 14. Wd N:E: gloomy. at noon a few grains of sleet fell, then bright &amp; clear. Went thro' Long-Preston &amp; Gargrave
							to]
						<hi rend="italic">Skipton</hi> [16 miles. it] is a pretty large Market-Town in a valley with one
						very broad street gently sloping downwards from the Castle, wch stands at the head of it. this is one of our good Countesse's buildings, but on old foundations: it is not very large, but of a handsome antique appearance with round
						towers, a grand Gateway, bridge &amp; mote, &amp; many old trees about it, in good repair, &amp; kept up, as a habitation of the Earl
						of Thanet, tho' he rarely comes thither. what with the sleet &amp; a foolish dispute about chaises,
						that delay'd me, I did not see the inside of it, but went on 15 miles to <hi rend="italic">Ottley.</hi> first up <hi rend="italic">Shode-bank,</hi> the steepest hill I ever saw a road carried over in England, for it mounts in a strait line (without any other
						repose for the horses, than by placing stones every now &amp; then behind the wheels) for a full mile. then the road goes on a level
						along the brow of this high hill over Rumbald-moor, till it gently descends into <hi rend="italic">Wharldale:</hi> so they call the
						Vale of the Wharf, &amp; a beautiful vale it is, well-wooded, well-cultivated, well-inhabited, but with high crags at distance, that
						border the green country on either hand. thro' the midst of it deep, clear, full to the brink, &amp; of no inconsiderable breadth runs
						in long windings the river. how it comes to pass that it should be so fine &amp; copious a stream here, &amp; at Tadcaster (so much
						lower) should have nothing but a wide stony channel without water, I can not tell you. I pass'd through <hi rend="italic">Long-Addingham, Ilkeley</hi> (pronounce <hi rend="italic">Eecla</hi>) distinguish'd by a lofty brow of loose rocks to the right, <hi rend="italic">Burley,</hi> a neat &amp; pretty village among trees. on the opposite side of the river lay <hi rend="italic">Middleton</hi>-Lodge, belonging to a Catholick Gentleman of that name; <hi rend="italic">Weston,</hi> a venerable stone-fabrick with
						large offices, of Mr Vavasor, the meadows in front gently descending to the water, &amp; behind a great &amp; shady wood. Farnley (Mr
							Fawke's) a place like the last, but larger, &amp; rising higher on the side of the hill. <hi rend="italic">Ottley</hi> is a large airy Town, with clean but low rustick buildings, &amp; a bridge over the Wharf. I went into its
						spatious Gothic Church, wch has been new-roof'd with a flat stucco ceiling. in a corner of it is the monument of Tho: Ld
							Fairfax, &amp; Helen Aske, his Lady, descended from the Cliffords &amp; Latimers, as her epitaph
						says. the figures not ill-cut particularly his in armour, but bare-headed, lie on the tomb. I take them for the Grand Parents of the famous Sr Tho: Fairfax.
					</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
