<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (24 December 1767)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
		                <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
		                <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
		                <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
		                <idno>AU MS 30/24/6/4</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 457, vol. iii, 982-984
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=457</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter lvi, section iv, 327-329
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:327</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 284
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:284</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCXIV, vol. iii, 161-163
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:161</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXXI, vol. ii, 481-483
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:481</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLII, vol. iv, 90-92
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:90</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXII, vol. ii, 110-112
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:110</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LVI, vol. i, 426-428
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:426</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0513">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1767-12-24"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7009782">Aberdeen, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0513">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To Mr Professor Beattie in the University of Aberdeen by Caxton-Bay</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Dec: 24. 1767. Pembroke Hall <lb/> Cambridge. </dateline>
					       <salute>Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>Since I had the pleasure of receiving your last letter, wch did not reach me, till I had left the
					North, &amp; was come to London, I have been confined to my room with a fit of the gout: now I am recover'd &amp; in quiet at
					Cambridge, I take up my pen to thank you for your very friendly offers, wch have so much the air of frankness &amp; real good-meaning,
					that were my body as tractable &amp; easy of conveyance as my mind, you would see me tomorrow in the chamber you have so hospitably
					laid out for me at Aberdeen. but, alas! I am a summer-bird, &amp; can only sit drooping, till the sun returns: even then too my wings
					may chance to be clipp'd, &amp; little in plight for so distant an excursion.</p>
				     <p>The proposal you make me about printing, what little I have ever written, at Glasgow does me honour. I leave my reputation in that
					part of the kingdom to your care, &amp; only desire you would not let your partiality to me &amp; mine mislead you. if you persist in
					your design, Mr Foulis certainly ought to be acquainted of what I am now going to tell you. when I was
					in London the last spring, Dodsley the Bookseller ask'd my leave to reprint, in a smaller form all I have ever publish'd, to wch I
					consented; &amp; added, that I would send him a few explanatory notes, &amp; if he would omitt entirely the <hi rend="italic">Long
						Story</hi> (wch was never meant for the publick, &amp; only suffer'd to appear in that pompous edition because of Mr Bentley's
					designs, wch were not intelligible without it) I promised to send him some thing else to print instead of it, least the bulk of so
					small a volume should be reduced to nothing at all. now it is very certain, that I had rather see them printed at Glasgow (especially
					as you will condescend to revise the press) than at London, but I know not how to retract my promise to Dodsley. by the way you perhaps
					may imagine, that I have some kind of interest in this publication: but the truth is, I have none whatever. the expence is his &amp; so
					is the profit, if there be any. I therefore told him the other day in general terms, that I heard,
					there would be an edition put out in Scotland by a friend of mine, whom I could not refuse, &amp; that if so, I would send thither a
					copy of the same notes &amp; additions, that I had promised to send to him. this did not seem at all to cool his courage; Mr Foulis
					therefore must judge for himself, whether he thinks it worth while to print, what is going to be printed also at London. if he does I
					will send him (in a packet to you) the same things I shall send to Dodsley. they are imitations of two pieces of old Norwegian poetry, in wch there was a wild spirit, that struck me:
					but for my paraphrases I can not say much. you will judge. the rest are nothing but a few parallel passages; &amp; small notes just to
					explain, what People said at the time was wrap'd in total darkness. you will please to tell me, as soon as you can conveniently, what
					Mr F:s says on this head, that (if he drops the design) I may save myself &amp; you the trouble of
					this packet. I ask your pardon for talking so long about it: a little more &amp; my letter would be as big as all <hi rend="italic">my
						works.</hi>
				     </p>
				     <p>I have read with much pleasure an Ode of yours (in wch you have done me the honour to adopt a
					measure, that I have used) on Ld Hay's birth-day. tho' I do not love <hi rend="italic">panegyrick,</hi> I can not but applaud this, for there is nothing mean in it. the diction is easy &amp; noble. the texture of the
					thoughts lyrick, &amp; the versification harmonious. the fourth Stanza is particularly my favourite
						(<hi rend="italic">the Muse with joy</hi> &amp;c:) for the contrast of images; &amp; the three follo[wing]
					 are excellent: not so the last. it is rather sp[un out] &amp; the
					thoughts repeated. I object a little too to (in St: 2d) <hi rend="italic">All energy of mind.</hi> the word <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
					weakens the verse; &amp; again in St: 6, <hi rend="italic">O yet e'er Luxury.</hi>
					 that word can not be contracted to a dissyllable without harshness, tho' <hi rend="italic">Mem'ry</hi> may. these indeed are Minutiæ, but they weigh for something, as half a grain makes a difference in the value of a
					diamond.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! Dear Sr, &amp; believe me <lb/> Your Friend &amp; faithful Servant </salute>
					       <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>I am forced to write without a frank, but I will do so no more. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
