<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (23 September 1753)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
		                <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
		                <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
		                <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 181, vol. i, 381-383
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=181</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter V, 18-21
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:18</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CVIII, vol. i, 237-239
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:237</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0210">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010370">Kingston-Upon-Hull, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1753-09-23"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0210">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Thomas Gray Esquire</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>at Dr Whartons in</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
			         </address>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <salute>Dear Mr. Gray,</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> You have been rightly informd that I have lost a most affectionate Father. I have felt for him, all that a heart not naturally hard,
					&amp; at the time already softend by preceeding anxiety could feel. But my Greiss rest not on him alone, only last tuesday my most
					intimate friend Dr Pricket followd him, a Man who I assure you had more good Qualities of the Heart,
					than the brightest of the Head could outballance either in mine or your estimation, we were brought up together from infancy &amp; ever
					livd in the sincerest affection; in my long illness at London he attended me with a Care and assiduity almost unparralelld. I endeavord
					to repay that Care in my turn but alas his Fate did not give me time to discharge half the debt, yet what I could, I did. </p>
				     <p>O Mr Gray how dreadful is it to sit besides a Dying Friend! to see as I did, reason withdraw herself gradually, often return by
					starts, to a Memory evry Minute less capable of furnishing her with Ideas, and a tongue less able to give them utterance. I talk
					nonsence I beleive, but let me do it, it gives me some relief, what makes his Loss to me more deplorable is, that I am afraid either
					the Physician who constantly attended him mistook his Case, or that the other who was calld in afterwards hastend his End, for a sudden
					change ensued the alteration of his medicines. But I will check myself till I see you and then you must bear with me, if I am even a
					Child or a Woman in my complainings. I must add however that in a Will he made five year ago his Friendship bequeathd to me two hundred
					pounds wch when my Debt is dischargd to his executor will be reducd to one, yet the sum will come at present as oportunly as any thing
					of the kind possibly could, as My Father by the Strangest disposition of his affairs that can be conceivd has left all my paternal
					estate to my Mother in Law for her life and entaild it so on my little sister, that I can take up no
					Money upon it, so that without this Legacy I should not have had a Shilling at present. I beleive I shall be obligd to take a journey
					to Mr. Huttons near Richmond and may perhaps be at York next sunday, but this is so exceedingly uncertain that I only just name it but would not have you alter your schemes upon it for the sake of a
					meeting. Because my Mother is at present in a fever with three blisters but I hope on the recovery, yet I cannot leave her till there
					appears a greater certainty. Tom has been also in a feavor and got out only to day, therefore I dont
					know whether he'll be in a condition to travel, and I cant easily relinquish the pomp of travelling with a Servt all on a sudden; and
					my Father's Servt, a Lad of the same age, died the week after his Master of a Fever also. from all this you may guess what a time I
					have gone thro lately. yet I am well myself at present except that my hands tremble, and my spiritts often, very often sink. yet have
					they supported me hitherto supprizingly. Pray tell Mr Brown when you see him that I fear I cannot be up at College by the tenth of
						October, yet I shall get there as soon as ever I can make any end of my perplext [affairs] here. I wish you had told me how long you would stay in Buckinghamshire I hope it will be short, and that
					we may meet again at Cambridge soon. adieu. My best complmts to Dr Wharton.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am Dr Sir<lb/> yours with sincerity and affection </salute>
					       <signed>W. MASON. </signed>
					       <dateline>Hull Sept. 23d–53 </dateline>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>Do write to me again very soon. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
