<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Ashton (25 August 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a MS transcript is at the British Library, Add. MSS 32562, ff. 148-150</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 66, vol. i, 115-116
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=66</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 97, vol. i, 237-239
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:237</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section I, letter no. 5, 47-48
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:47</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XXI, vol. i, 33-34
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:33</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0076">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011060">Reims, France</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1739-08-25"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227197">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Rheims</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0076">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Mr Ashton at Mrs Lewes's</addrLine>
               <addrLine>in Hanover Square London</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Franc a Paris.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>pour l'Angleterre</addrLine>
               <addrLine>franc jusqu'a Paris.</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Rheims. 25 Aug. N: S </dateline>
            <salute>My dear Ashton,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am not so ignorant of Pain myself as to be able to hear of anothers Sufferings, without any Sensibility to them, especially when
					they are those of One, I ought more particularly to feel for; tho' indeed the goodness of my own Constitution, is in some Sense a
					Misfortune to me, for as the health of everybody I love seems much more precarious than my own, it is but a melancholy prospect to
					consider myself as one, that may possibly in some years be left in the World, destitute of the advice or good Wishes of those few
					friends, that usd to care for me, and without a likelihood or even a desire of gaining any new ones. this letter will, I hope, find you
					perfectly recoverd, &amp; your own painful experience will, for the future, teach you not to give so much in to a sedentary Life, that
					has [I] fear been the Cause of your illness. Give my duty to your Mind, &amp; tell her she has taken more care of herself, than of my
					tother poor friend, your Body, &amp; bid her hereafter remember how nearly <hi rend="italic">her</hi> Welfare is connected with <hi rend="italic">his:</hi> tell her too, that she may pride herself in her great family, &amp; despise him for being a poor Mortal, as
					much as she pleases, but that he is her wedded husband, &amp; if he suffers, she must smart for it. my inferences you will say, don't
					follow very naturally, nor have any great relation to what has been said, but they are as follows.</p>
         <p>Messrs Selwin and Montague have been here these 3 weeks, are by this time pretty heartily tired of Rheims, &amp; return in about a
					week. The day they set out for England, we are to do the same for Burgundy, in our way only as it is said to Provence, but People
					better informd conceive that Dijon will be the end of our expedition. for me, I make everything that does not depend on me, so
					indifferent to me, that if it be to go to the Cape of good Hope I care not: if you are well enough, you will let me know a little of
					the history of West who does not remember there is such a Place as Champagne in the world. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Your's ever </salute>
            <signed>T. G. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
