<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (12 August 1767)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
                  <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
                  <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
                  <idno>AU MS 30/24/6/3</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 452, vol. iii, 974-975
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=452</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter lv, section iv, 325-327
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:325</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 282-283
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:282</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCX, vol. iii, 156-157
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:156</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXX, vol. ii, 479-481
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:479</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXLI, vol. iv, 87-89
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:87</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXXI, vol. ii, 108-110
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:108</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LV, vol. i, 424-426
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:424</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0508">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1767-08-12"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7009782">Aberdeen, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0508">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Mr Professor Beattie of the Marischal College Aberdeen</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>DUNDEE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Old-Park, near Darlington, Durham. <lb/> 12 Aug: 1767. </dateline>
            <salute>Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I received from Mr Williamson that very obliging mark you were pleased to give me of your
					remembrance. had I not entertain'd some slight hopes of revisiting Scotland this summer, &amp; consequently of seeing you at Aberdeen,
					I had sooner acknowledged by letter the favor you have done me. those hopes are now at an end: but I do not therefore despair of seeing
					again a country, that has given me so much pleasure; nor of telling you in person how much I esteem you, &amp; (as you chuse to call
					them) your <hi rend="italic">amusements.</hi> the specimen of them, wch you were so good to send me, I
					think excellent. the sentiments are such as a melancholy imagination naturally suggests in solitude &amp; silence, &amp; that (tho'
					light &amp; business may suspend or banish them at times) return with but so much the greater force upon a feeling heart. the diction
					is elegant &amp; unconstrain'd, not loaded with epithets &amp; figures, nor flagging into prose. the versification is easy &amp;
					harmonious. my only objection is to the first part of this line <q>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Perfumed with fresh fragrance</hi> &amp;c:</p>
            </q> where the consonants are harsh &amp; frequent, tho' the image is good &amp; the words in all other respects well chosen. a
						Friend of mine, to whom I shew'd these verses, rather blames the choice of your measure, as
					appropriated to comic, or at most to pastoral subjects: but I do not think his criticism of much weight. you see, Sr, I take the
					liberty you indulged me in, when I first saw you, &amp; therefore I make no excuses for it, but desire you would take your revenge on
					me in kind. </p>
         <p>I have read over (but too hastily) Mr Ferguson's book. there are uncommon strains of eloquence in
					it, &amp; I was surprised to find not one single idiom of his country (I think) in the whole work. he has not the fault you mention:
					his application to the heart is frequent, &amp; often successful. his love of Montesquiou &amp; Tacitus has led him into a manner of
					writing too short-winded &amp; sententious, wch those great Men had they lived in better times &amp; under a better government would
					have avoided.</p>
         <p>I know no pretence, that I have, to the honor Lord Gray is pleased to do me: but if his Ldp chuses
					to own me, it certainly is not my business to deny it. I say not this merely on account of his quality: but because he is a very worthy
					&amp; accomplish'd Person. I am truly sorry for the great loss he has had, since I left Scotland. if
					you should chance to see him, I will beg you to present my respectful humble service to his Lordship.</p>
         <p>I gave Mr Williamson all the information I was able in the short time he stay'd with me. he seem'd to answer well the character you
					gave me of him: but what I chiefly envied in him was his ability of walking all the way from Aberdeen to Cambridge, &amp; back again,
					wch if I possess'd, you would soon see </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Your obliged &amp; faithful humble Servant </salute>
            <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
