<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Richard West (12 April 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 60, vol. i, 101-104
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=60</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter ii, section ii, 44-47
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:44</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 122-124
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:122</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 87, vol. i, 201-206
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915i:201</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XV, vol. i, 18-23
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:18</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter II, vol. ii, 38-41
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:38</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter II, vol. ii, 42-46
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:42</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XX, vol. i, 37-41
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:37</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter II, vol. i, 171-174
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:171</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0067">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008038">Paris, France</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-04-12"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143039">West, Richard, 1716-1742</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Conway, Henry Seymour, 1721-1795</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Voltaire</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Prévost, L'Abbé</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Pandore</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Destouches, Philippe Néricault</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">St. Denis</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Paris</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Chantilly</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Amiens</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0067">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Paris, April 12, 1739. </dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>Enfin donc me voici à Paris. Mr. Walpole is gone out to supper at Lord Conway's, and here I remain alone, though invited too. Do not think I make a merit of writing to you preferably to a
					good supper; for these [eight] days we have been here, have actually given me an aversion to eating in
					general. If hunger be the best sauce to meat, the French are certainly the worst cooks in the world; for what tables we have seen have
					been so delicately served, and so profusely, that, after rising from one of them, one imagines it impossible ever to eat again. And
					now, if I tell you all I have in my head, you will believe me mad, mais n'importe, courage, allons! for if I wait till my head grow
					clear and settle a little, you may stay long enough for a letter. Six days have we been coming hither, which other people do in two;
					they have not been disagreeable ones; through a fine, open country, admirable roads, and in an easy conveyance; the inns not absolutely
					intolerable, and images quite unusual presenting themselves on all hands. At Amiens we saw the fine cathedral, and eat paté de perdrix;
					passed through the park of Chantilly by the Duke of Bourbon's palace, which we only beheld as we passed; broke down at Lusarche; stopt
					at St. Denis, saw all the beautiful monuments of the Kings of France, and the vast treasures of the abbey, rubies, and emeralds as big
					as small eggs, crucifixes, and vows, crowns and reliquaries, of inestimable value; but of all their curiosities the thing the most to
					our tastes, and which they indeed do the justice to esteem the glory of their collection, was a vase of an entire onyx, measuring at
					least five inches over, three deep, and of great thickness. It is at least two thousand years old, the beauty of the stone and
					sculpture upon it (representing the mysteries of Bacchus) beyond expression admirable; we have dreamed of it ever since. The jolly old
					Benedictine, that showed us the treasures, had in his youth been ten years a soldier; he laughed at all the reliques, was very full of
					stories, and mighty obliging. On Saturday evening we got to Paris, and were driving through the streets a long while before we knew
					where we were. The minute we came, voila Milors Holdernesse, Conway, and his brother; all stayed supper, and till two o'clock in the morning, for here nobody ever sleeps; it is not the way: Next
					day go to dine at my Lord Holdernesse's, there was the Abbé Prevôt, author of the Cleveland, and several other pieces much esteemed: The rest were English. At night we went to the Pandore; a spectácle
					literally, for it is nothing but a beautiful piece of machinery of three scenes. The first represents the chaos, and by degrees the
					separation of the elements. The second, the temple of Jupiter, and the giving of the box to Pandora. The third, the opening of the box,
					and all the mischiefs that ensued. An absurd design, but executed in the highest perfection, and that in one of the finest theatres in
					the world; it is the grande sale des machines in the Palais des Tuileries. Next day dined at Lord Waldegrave's; then to the opera.</p>
         <p>Imagine to yourself for the drama four acts entirely unconnected with each other, each founded on
					some little history, skilfully taken out of an ancient author, e.g. Ovid's Metamorphoses, &amp;c., and with great address converted
					into a French piece of gallantry. For instance, that which I saw, called the Ballet de la Paix, had its first act built upon the story
					of Nereus. Homer having said he was the handsomest man of his time,
					the poet, imagining such a one could not want a mistress, has given him one. These two come in and sing sentiment in lamentable
					strains, neither air nor recitative; only, to one's great joy, they are every now and then interrupted by a dance, or (to one's great
					sorrow) by a chorus that borders the stage from one end to the other, and screams, past all power of simile to represent. The second
					act was Baucis and Philemon. Baucis is a beautiful young shepherdess, and Philemon her swain. Jupiter
					falls in love with her, but nothing will prevail upon her; so it is all mighty well, and the chorus sing and dance the praises of
					Constancy. The two other acts were about Iphis and Ianthe, and the judgment of Paris. Imagine, I say,
					all this transacted by cracked voices, trilling divisions upon two notes and a half, accompanied by an orchestra of humstrums, and a
					whole house more attentive than if Farinelli sung, and you will almost have formed a just notion of
					the thing. Our astonishment at their absurdity you can never conceive; we had enough to do to express
					it by screaming an hour louder than the whole dramatis personæ. We have also seen twice the Comedie Françoise; first, the Mahomet
						Second, a tragedy that has had a great run of late; and the thing itself does not want its beauties,
					but the actors are beyond measure delightful. Mademoiselle Gaussin (Mr. Voltaire's Zara) has with a charming (though little) person the most pathetic tone of voice, the finest expression in her
					face, and most proper action imaginable. There is also a Dufrêne, who did the chief character, a
					handsome man and a prodigious fine actor. The second we saw was the Philosophe marié, and here they
					performed as well in comedy; there is a Mademoiselle Quinault, somewhat in Mrs. Clive's way, and a Monsieur Grandval, in the nature of Wilks, who is the genteelest thing in the world. There are several more would be much admired in England, and many
					(whom we have not seen) much celebrated here. Great part of our time is spent in seeing churches and palaces full of fine pictures,
					&amp;c., the quarter of which is not yet exhausted. For my part, I could entertain myself this month merely with the common streets and
					the people in them. [...]</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
