<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Horace Walpole (24 September 1766)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution key="PBCC">Pembroke College, Cambridge</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
                  <idno>GBR/1058/GRA/3/4/99</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Digital facsimile [greyscale GIF] from a print reproduction of the letter</title>
                     </bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 426, vol. iii, 937
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=426</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Gray, Walpole, West and Ashton (1734-1771)</title>, 2 vols. Chronologically arranged and edited with introduction, notes, and index by Paget Toynbee. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1915, letter no. 236, vol. ii, 260-261
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=TyP_1915ii:260</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence</title>. Ed. by W. S. Lewis. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP; London: Oxford UP, 1937-83, vols. 13/14: <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton</title> i, 1734-42, <title>Horace Walpole's Correspondence with Thomas Gray</title> ii, 1745-71, ed. by W. S. Lewis, George L. Lam and Charles H. Bennett, 1948, vol. ii, 158
				<ref type="url">http://images.library.yale.edu/hwcorrespondence/page.asp?vol=14&amp;page=158</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0481">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1766-09-24"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17231985">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Cole, William, 1714-1782</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Norfolk</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Houghton</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0481">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The Honble</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Horace Walpole in</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Arlington Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>London</addrLine>
            </address>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I happen'd to be in Norfolk on the way to Houghton, when I read an article in a news-paper relating to you, that shock'd me. I wrote
					to Dr Gisburne (who lives very near you) to beg he would inform himself of your health: but I fear he
					is out of Town, for I have received no answer. today by accident I received a letter from Cole, from
					whence I learn, thank God! that the worst part of that news was false: but that you have suffer'd much from a return of the gout, &amp;
					are prevented only by weakness from going to Bath. it would be a singular satisfaction to me, if I might see three lines in your own
					hand: but it is impossible for me to judge, whether this is a reasonable request. I flatter myself, if you can, you will indulge me in
					it, especially when you know, that of those who are most about you, there is no one I can well write to. in a fortnight or less I hope
					to be in Town. Heaven preserve you, &amp; restore you to health &amp; ease. I hope this severe lesson will warn you against that
					careless regimen, to wch you were so unreasonably attach'd.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T GRAY. </signed>
            <dateline>Sept: 24. 1766 Pemb: Hall. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
