<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (19 July 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 148-149</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">199 mm x 164 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 337, vol. ii, 742-743
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=337</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXIII, vol. ii, 218-219
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/218</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XCVIII, vol. ii, 389-390
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/389</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CVI, vol. iii, 285-286
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/285</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0388">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1761-07-19"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Old Park</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Eton</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0388">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>As you &amp; Mr R: Wharton seem determined for the foundation, I shall say no more on that subject: it is pity you could not resolve
					sooner, for I fear you are now too late, &amp; must defer your design till the next year, as the Election at Eton begins this day
					se'nnight, &amp; your Nephew ought to be there on the evening of the 27th at farthest, wch is scarce possible. you have never told me
					his age: but (I suppose) you know, that after 15 compleat Boys are excluded from the election, &amp; that a Certificate of their age,
					(that is, an extract from the Parish-Register, where they were baptised,) is always required, wch must be attested &amp; sign'd by the
					Minister &amp; Churchwardens of the said Parish. your Nephew (I imagine) is much younger than fifteen, &amp; therefore there will be no great inconvenience if he should be placed at Eton, whenever it suits Mr Wharton to carry him,
					&amp; there wait for the next election. this is commonly practised, &amp; Dr A: (I do not doubt) will
					be equally ready to serve him then, as now. he will probably be placed pretty high in the School, having had the same education, that
					is in use there, &amp; will have time to familiarise himself to the place, before he actually enters
					the College. I have waited to know your intentions, before I could answer Dr A:s letter; &amp; wish you would now write to me, what you
					finally determine. there is a Month's Breaking-up immediately after the Election (wch lasts a week) so it is probable Mr Wharton will
					hardly send his Son till those holidays are over.</p>
         <p>I do not mention the subject you hint at for the same reason you give me; it should be <hi rend="italic">offer'd,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">clear of all taxes,</hi> before I would go into it, in spite of the mines in America,
					on which I congratulate you.</p>
         <p>I shall hope to see Old-Park next summer, if I am not bedrid, but who can tell? Mr Brown presents his best services to the family
					with mine: he is older than I.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu, the Post waits! I am ever truly <lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
            <dateline>July 19 .. Pemb: Coll:</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
