<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (31 January 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 139-141</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>6 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">ff. 139-140: 205 mm x 160 mm f. 141: 330 mm x 202 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 331, vol. ii, 724-732
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=331</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, section iv, 288
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:288</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXVIII, vol. ii, 199-209
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:199</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XCV, vol. ii, 376-384
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:376</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CIII, vol. iii, 270-280
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:270</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0381">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-01-31"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Montagu, Lady Mary Wortley</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Theophrastus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Stillingfleet, Benjamin</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Linnæus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hill, Dr. John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Berger, Alexander Malachias</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Aristotle</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Upsala</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Stratton Strawless</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Old Park</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Attica</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0381">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>London. Jan: 31. 1761.</dateline>
            <salute>My dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You seem to forget me: if it were for any other reason, than that you are very busy, that is, very happy, I should not so easily pass
					it over.</p>
         <p>I send you a Swedish &amp; English Calendar. the first Column is by Berger, a Disciple of
						Linnæus; the 2d by Mr Stillingfleet, the 3d (very imperfect
					indeed) by me. you are to observe, as you tend your plantations &amp; take your walks, how the Spring advances in the North, &amp;
					whether Old-Park most resembles Upsal, or Stratton. this latter has on one side a barren black heath,
					on the other a light sandy loam; all the country about it is a dead flat. you see, it is necessary you should know the situation (I do
					not mean any reflection upon any body's place) &amp; this is Mr. Stillingfleet's description of his Friend Mr Marsham's Seat, to wch in summer he retires, &amp; botanizes. I have lately made an acquaintance with this
					Philosopher, who lives in a garret here in the winter, that he may support some near relations, who depend upon him. he is always
					employ'd, &amp; always chearful, &amp; seems to me a very worthy honest Man. his present scheme is to send some Persons properly
					qualified to reside a year or two in Attica to make themselves acquainted with the climate, productions, &amp; natural history of the
					country, that we may understand Aristotle &amp; Theophrastus, &amp;c: who have been heathen-Greek to
					us for so many ages. this he has got proposed to Ld Bute, who is no unlikely Person to put it in execution, being himself a Botanist,
					&amp; having now in the press a new System of Botany of his own writing in several volumes, the
					profits of wch he gives to Dr Hill (the Inspector) who has lately got the place of Master-Gardiner at
					Kensington, reckon'd worth near 2000£ a-year. there is an odd thing for you!</p>
         <p>One hears nothing of the K:,
					 but what gives one the best opinion of him imaginable: I hope, it may hold. the R: F: run loose about the world, &amp; people do not know how to treat them, nor they how to be treated. they
					visit &amp; are visited: some come to the Street-door to receive them, &amp; that, they say, is too much: others to the head of the
					stairs, &amp; that they think too little. no body sits down with them, not even in their own house, unless at a card-table, so the
					world are like to grow very weary of the honour. none but the D: of Y: enjoy themselves (you know, he
					always did) but the world seems weary of this honour too, for a different reason. I have just heard no bad story of him. when he was at
					Southampton in the summer, there was a Clergyman in the neighbourhood with two very handsome daughters. he had soon wind of them, &amp;
					drop'd in for some reason or other, came again &amp; again, &amp; grew familiar enough to eat a bone of their mutton. at last he said
					to the Father, Miss — lead a mighty confined life here always at home, why can't you let one of them go, &amp; take an airing
					now and then with me in my chaise? Ah! Sr (says the Parson) do but look at them, a couple of hale fresh-colour'd hearty Wenches! they
					need no airing, they are well-enough: but there is their Mother, poor Woman, has been in a declining way many years. if your R: H:
					would give her an airing now &amp; then, it would be doing us a great kindness indeed!</p>
         <p>You see, old Wortley-Montagu is dead at last at 83. it was not mere avarice, &amp; its companion,
					abstinence, that kept him alive so long. he every day drank (I think, it was) half a pint of Tokay,
					wch he imported himself from Hungary in greater quantity than he could use, &amp; sold the Overplus for any price he chose to set upon
					it. he has left better than half a million of money: to Lady Mary 1200£ a-year, in case she gives up her pretensions to dowry; &amp; if
					not, it comes to his Son. to the same Son 1000£ per an: for life only, &amp; after him to his Daughter, Lady Bute. (now this Son is about 80,000£ in debt) to all Lady Bute's Children, which are eleven,
					2000£ a-piece. <hi rend="italic">all the remainder</hi> to Lady Bute, &amp; after her to her second Son, who takes the name of Wortley, &amp; (if he fail) to the next in order; &amp; after all these &amp; their Children to Ld
						Sandwich, to whom <hi rend="italic">in present</hi> he leaves some old Manuscripts. now I must tell
					you a story of Lady Mary. as she was on her travels, she had occasion to go somewhere by sea, &amp; (to save charges) got a passage on
					board a Man of War: the ship was (I think) Commodore Barnet's. when he had landed her, she told him,
					she knew she was not to offer to pay for her passage, but in consideration of his many civilities entreated him to wear a ring for her
					sake, &amp; press'd him to accept it, wch he did. it was an emerald of remarkable size &amp; beauty. some time after, as he wore it,
					some Friend was admiring it, &amp; asking how he came by it. when he heard from whom it came, he laugh'd &amp; desired him to shew it
					to a Jeweller, whom he knew. the Man was sent for: he unset it; it was a paste not worth 40 shillings.</p>
         <p>The Ministry are much out of joint. Mr P: much out of humour, his popularity tottering, chiefly
					occasion'd by a Pamphlet against the German War, written by that <hi rend="italic">squeaking</hi> acquaintance of ours, Mr.
						Mauduit: it has had a vast run. the Irish are very intractable, even the Lds J:s themselves; great difficulties about who shall be sent over to tame them: my Ld H:ss
					again named, but (I am told) has refused it. every body waits for a new Parliament to settle their ideas.</p>
         <p>I have had no gout, since you went: I will not brag, lest it return with redoubled violence. I am very foolish, &amp; do nothing to
					mark, that I ever was: I am going to C:ge to take the <hi rend="italic">fresh air</hi> this fine
					winter for a month or so. we have had snow one day this winter, but it did not lie: it was several months ago. the 18th of Jan: I took
					a walk to <hi rend="italic">Kentish-Town,</hi> wind N: W:, bright &amp; frosty. Therm: at Noon was at 42. the grass remarkably green
					&amp; flourishing. I observed, on dry banks facing the South that Chickweed, Dandelion, Groundsel, Red Archangel, &amp; Shepherds-Purse were beginning to flower. this is all I know of the Country.</p>
         <p>My best compliments to Mrs Wharton. I hear her butter is the best in the Bishoprick, &amp; that even Deborah has learn'd to spin. I rejoice you are all in health, but why are you deaf: &amp; blind too, or you could
					not vote for F: V:! I have abundance more to say, but my paper won't hear of it.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu!</salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>1755. </p>
            <table rend="frame">
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>UPSAL IN SWEDEN </cell>
                  <cell>STRATTON IN NORFOLK</cell>
                  <cell>CAMBRIDGE</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Lat: 59, 51 1/2" </cell>
                  <cell>Lat: 52, 45"  </cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Hasel begins to f: </cell>
                  <cell>12 Apr: </cell>
                  <cell>23 Jan:  </cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Snowdrop F: </cell>
                  <cell>13 Apr: </cell>
                  <cell>26 Jan: </cell>
                  <cell>4 Feb:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(White Wagtail) appears </cell>
                  <cell>13 Apr: </cell>
                  <cell>12 Feb: </cell>
                  <cell>3 Feb:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Violets F: </cell>
                  <cell>3 May }</cell>
                  <cell>28 March }</cell>
                  <cell>28 March  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Snowdrop goes off </cell>
                  <cell>}</cell>
                  <cell>}</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Apricot f: </cell>
                  <cell>}</cell>
                  <cell>1 April }</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Elm F: </cell>
                  <cell>8 May </cell>
                  <cell>1 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Swallow returns) </cell>
                  <cell>9 May </cell>
                  <cell>6 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Cuckow heard) </cell>
                  <cell>12 May </cell>
                  <cell>17 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Nightingale sings) </cell>
                  <cell>15 May </cell>
                  <cell>9 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Birch L: </cell>
                  <cell>13 May </cell>
                  <cell>1 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Alder L: </cell>
                  <cell>14 May </cell>
                  <cell>7 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Bramble L: </cell>
                  <cell>7 May </cell>
                  <cell>3 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Elm l: </cell>
                  <cell>15 May </cell>
                  <cell>10 April </cell>
                  <cell>16 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Hawthorn l: </cell>
                  <cell>15 May </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>10 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Acacia l: </cell>
                  <cell>15 May </cell>
                  <cell>12 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lime l: </cell>
                  <cell>21 May </cell>
                  <cell>12 April </cell>
                  <cell>16 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Aspen l: </cell>
                  <cell>20 May </cell>
                  <cell>25 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sycamore l: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>13 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>White Poplar l: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>17 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Beech l: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>21 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Chestnut &amp; Maple l: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>18 April </cell>
                  <cell>18 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Oak l: </cell>
                  <cell>20 May </cell>
                  <cell>18 April </cell>
                  <cell>18 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Ash l: </cell>
                  <cell>21 May </cell>
                  <cell>22 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Fig l: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>21 April </cell>
                  <cell>24 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Horse-Chestnut F: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>12 May </cell>
                  <cell>12 May  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Mulberry L: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>14 May </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Crab &amp; Apple f: </cell>
                  <cell>2 June </cell>
                  <cell>23 April </cell>
                  <cell>22 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Cherry f: </cell>
                  <cell>28 May </cell>
                  <cell>18 April </cell>
                  <cell>17 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lilac f: </cell>
                  <cell>8 June </cell>
                  <cell>27 April </cell>
                  <cell>24 April  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Hawthorn f: </cell>
                  <cell>17 June </cell>
                  <cell>10 May </cell>
                  <cell>12 May  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Plumbtree f: </cell>
                  <cell>28 May </cell>
                  <cell>16 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lilly of yeValley F: </cell>
                  <cell>30 May </cell>
                  <cell>3 May </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Broom F: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>24 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Mulberry L: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>14 May </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Elder f: </cell>
                  <cell>29 June </cell>
                  <cell>25 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lady-Smock f: </cell>
                  <cell>28 May </cell>
                  <cell>18 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Pea &amp; Bean f: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>29 April </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Strawberries ripe </cell>
                  <cell>26 June </cell>
                  <cell>9 July </cell>
                  <cell>16 June  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Cherries </cell>
                  <cell>7 July </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>25 June (on Walls)   </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Currants </cell>
                  <cell>9 July </cell>
                  <cell>30 June </cell>
                  <cell>4 July  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Hay cut </cell>
                  <cell>7 July </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>18 May (near Lond:)  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Rye </cell>
                  <cell>4 Aug: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>19 June at Stoke   </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Wheat </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>21 August </cell>
                  <cell>15 Sept: (latest)  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Barley </cell>
                  <cell>16 Aug: </cell>
                  <cell>3 Aug: </cell>
                  <cell>4 Sept:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Cuckow silent) </cell>
                  <cell>15 July </cell>
                  <cell>end of July </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Swallow gone) </cell>
                  <cell>17 Sept: </cell>
                  <cell>21 Sept: </cell>
                  <cell>28 Sept:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Birch, Elm, Sycomore, Lime, change colour </cell>
                  <cell>22 Sept: </cell>
                  <cell>14 Sept: </cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Ash drops its leaves </cell>
                  <cell>6 Octob: </cell>
                  <cell>9 Octob: </cell>
                  <cell>5 Oct:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Elm strip'd </cell>
                  <cell>7 Octob:  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lime falls </cell>
                  <cell>12 Octob: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Hasel strip'd </cell>
                  <cell>17 Octob: </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <trailer>
                  <hi rend="italic">N:B:</hi> – 1: stands for <hi rend="italic">opening its leaves,</hi> L: for <hi rend="italic">in full
								leaf.</hi> f: for <hi rend="italic">beginning to flower,</hi> F: for <hi rend="italic">full-blown.</hi>
                  <lb/> the Summer-Flowers, especially such as blow about the Solstice, I take no notice of, as they blow at the same time in Sweden,
							&amp; in England, at least the difference is only a day or two. </trailer>
            </table>
            <p>Observe, from this Calendar it appears, that there is a wonderful difference between the earlier Phænomena of the Spring in Sweden
						&amp; in England, no less than 78 days in the flow'ring of the Snow-Drop, 61 days in the appearance of the Wagtail, 62 days in the
						bloom of the Lilac, 43 days in the leafing of the Oak, 40 days in the blooming of the Cherry-tree, 36 days in the singing of the
						Nightingale, 33 in the return of the Swallow, 25 in that of the Cuckow, &amp; so on. yet the Summer-flowers nearly keep time alike in
						both climates, the Harvest differs not a fortnight, some of the Fruits only 9 days; nay, strawberries come earlier there by 13 days,
						than with us. the Swallow stays with us only 4 days longer than with them, &amp; the Ashtree begins to lose its leaves within 3 days
						of the same time. these differences, &amp; these uniformities I know not how to account for. </p>
            <p>Mr Stillingfleet's Kalendar goes no farther than Oct: 26. but I observed, that, on Dec: 2, many of our Rosetrees had put out new
						leaves, and the Laurustine, Polyanthus, single yellow, &amp; bloody Wallflowers, Cytisus, &amp; scarlet Geranium were still in flower. </p>
            <p>Jan: 15. 1756. the Honeysuckles were in leaf, and single Hepatica &amp; Snowdrop in flower. </p>
            <p>As to the noise of Birds, Mr St: marks their times thus in Norfolk. </p>
            <table rend="frame">
               <row>
                  <cell>4 Feb: </cell>
                  <cell>Woodlark singing.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>12 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Rooks pair.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>16 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Thrush sings.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Do </cell>
                  <cell>Chaffinch sings.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>22 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Partridges pair.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>2 March. </cell>
                  <cell>Rooks build.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Do </cell>
                  <cell>Ring-Dove cooes.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>15 April. </cell>
                  <cell>Bittern bumps.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>16 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Redstart returns.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>28 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Black-cap sings.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Do </cell>
                  <cell>White-throat seen.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>5 June. </cell>
                  <cell>Goatsucker (or Fern-Owl), heard in the evening.  <lb/> After the end of June most Birds are silent for a time, probably the
								moulting-season; only the Goldfinch, Yellow-Hamber, &amp; Crested Wren, are heard to chirp.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>7 Aug: </cell>
                  <cell>Nuthatch chatters.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>14 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Stone-Curlew whistles at night.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>15 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Young Owls heard in the evening.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>17 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Goatsucker no longer heard.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>26 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Robins singing.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>16 Sept: </cell>
                  <cell>Chaffinch chirping.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>25 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Woodlark sings, &amp; Feldefares arrive.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>27 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Black-bird sings.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>29 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Thrush sings.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>2 Octob: </cell>
                  <cell>Royston-Crow comes.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>10 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Woodlark in full song.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Do </cell>
                  <cell>Ringdove cooes.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>22 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Woodcock returns.  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>24 Do </cell>
                  <cell>Skylark sings.  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>I add the order of several fruits ripening <lb/> at Stoke, that year. </p>
            <table rend="frame">
               <row>
                  <cell>Hautboy-Strawberry </cell>
                  <cell>25 June  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Wall-Duke Cherry </cell>
                  <cell>Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Early Apricot </cell>
                  <cell>Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Black-heart Cherry </cell>
                  <cell>2 July  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Raspberry </cell>
                  <cell>4 Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Gooseberry </cell>
                  <cell>15 Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Masculine Apricot </cell>
                  <cell>Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Black Fig </cell>
                  <cell>30 Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Muscle } </cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Orleans } Plumb }  </cell>
                  <cell>18 Aug: </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Gr: Gage } </cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Filberd }</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Nectarine }</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Newingt: Peach }  </cell>
                  <cell>4 Sept:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Morella-Cherry }</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Mulberry }</cell>
                  <cell>  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Walnut }  </cell>
                  <cell>18 Sept:  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Melon }</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Bergamot-Pear } </cell>
                  <cell>25 Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Black Muscadine Grape }</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Nectarine over </cell>
                  <cell>Do  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>White Muscad: Grape </cell>
                  <cell>12 Oct:  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
