<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (22 May 1770)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="HSPO">Historical Society of Pennsylvania</institution>
		                <repository>Library</repository>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 525, vol. iii, 1134-1136
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=525</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter CXXXI, 439-442
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:439</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXVII, vol. iii, 284-286
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:284</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0603">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1770-05-22"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0603">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Brown President of Pembroke-Hall Cambridge</addrLine>
			         </address>
			         <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>22 MA</date>
            </stamp>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>22 May. 1770 Jermyn Street </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I have received two letters from you with one enclosed from Paris, &amp; one from Mason. I met poor Baker two or three days after the fire with evident marks of terror in his countenance: he has moved his quarters (I am told) somewhere into
					Gray's-inn Lane near the fields.
				</p>
				     <p>I do not apprehend any thing more than usual from the City-remonstrance, &amp; the Party
					principally concern'd I hear does not in the least regard it. the conversation you mention in the house of Lords is very true: it
					happen'd about a fortnight since, &amp; the A:p
					 replied, it was not any concern of his, as he had received no complaint from the Un: on that head. it begins to be doubted, whether Ld Anglesey will carry his point, his witnesses being so very Irish in their
					understandings &amp; consciences, that they puzzle the cause they came to prove: but this can not be clear'd up till another session.
					Pa: &amp; I have often visited, but never met: I saw my Ld &amp; Tom the other day at breakfast in
					good health, &amp; Lady Maria did not beat me, but giggled a little. Mons:r de Villevielle has found me out, &amp; seems a sensible quiet young Man. he returns soon to France with the
						Embassador, but means to revisit England, &amp; see it better. I dined at Hampton-court on Sunday
					all alone with St:, who enquired after you, &amp; the next day with the same &amp; a good deal of company in Town. I have not seen him
					so well this long time. I am myself indifferent, the head-ach returns now &amp; then, &amp; a little grumbling of the gout, but I mean
					to see you on Monday or Tuesday next.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu! I am ever Yours</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P:S: Pray, is Mrs Olliffe come to Cambridge.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
