<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (15 May 1766)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>Cambridge, MA</settlement>
                  <institution key="HARV">Harvard University</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library</repository>
                  <idno>fMS Eng 945 (18)</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 421, vol. iii, 924-926
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=421</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XCVII, 356-358
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1853/1/356</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXXII, vol. iii, 105-108
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900iii/1/105</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0476">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1766-05-15"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Palgrave, William, 1735-1799</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Robinson, William, Rev., c. 1726-1803</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Macaulay, Mrs. Catherine</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Lyttelton, George Lyttelton, 1st Lord</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Spain</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Naples</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Kent</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Ireland</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Canterbury</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0476">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Jermyn Street, May 15, 1766. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>To-morrow morning I set out for Canterbury. If any letter comes, I believe it will be better to
					direct to me as usual at Mr. Roberts's here, and he will take care to send it. I know not how long my
					stay in Kent may be: it depends on the agreeability of Mr. Robinson and his wife.</p>
         <p>You expect to hear who is Secretary of State. I cannot tell. It is sure this morning it was not
					determined; perhaps Lord Egmont; perhaps Lord Hardwicke (for I do not
					believe he has refused, as is said); perhaps you may hear of three instead of two. Charles Townshend
					affirms he has rejected both that office and a peerage; doubtless from his firm adherence to Mr. Pitt–a name which the court, I
					mean Lord Tt., Lord Nd., and even Lord B. himself, at present affect to celebrate, with what design you are to judge. You have doubtless heard of the honour done to your
					friend Mrs. Macaulay. Mr. Pitt has made a panegyric of her <hi rend="italic">History</hi> in the
						house. It is very true Wilkes has arrived. The tumults in Spain spread wider and wider, while at Naples they are publicly thanking God for their cessation; perhaps you may
					hear. All is not well in Ireland. It is very late at night. Adieu. Pa.
					went home to-day and Mr. Weddell with him. J. Wheeler has returned from
					Lisbon. The great match will not be till after Christmas. Tom is gone
					to Scotland. It is sure the lady did refuse both Lord Mountstuart and
					the Duke of Beaufort.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Good-night.</salute>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I came away in debt to you for two post-chaises. Pray set it down. </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
