<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls (14 September 1770)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Windsor</settlement>
                  <institution key="ETON">Eton College</institution>
                  <repository>College Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
			</supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>bound into a copy of Mathias's <hi rend="it">Works of Thomas Gray</hi> (London, 1814), vol. II, part 2; a photocopy is at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, OSB MSS c 467, box 1, folder 100</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 533, vol. iii, 1146-1147
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=533</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCCLXXII, vol. iii, 293-294
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:293</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, letter XXXI, vol. v, 112-113
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843v:112</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0612">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1770-09-14"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100833902">Nicholls, Norton, c. 1742-1809</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7018903">Richmond, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Linnæus</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Alloa</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0612">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To The Revd Mr Nicholls, at William Turner's Esq at Richmond Surrey</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <date>15 SE</date>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Venga, venga, V: S: si serva! I shall be proud to see you both. the lodgings over the way will be
					empty, but such an entry, such a staircase! how will Mrs N: be able to crowd thro' it? with what grace, when she gets out of her chair,
					can she conduct her hoop-petticoat thro' this augre-hole, and up the dark windings of the <hi rend="italic">grand escalier,</hi> that
					leads to her chamber? it is past my finding out. so I delay, till I hear from you again, before I engage them. I believe, there may be
					a bed for <hi rend="italic">you,</hi> but is there room for Mrs Kipiffe, Mamma's Maid? I am sure, I know not.</p>
         <p>I was very ill, when I received your letter, with a feverish disorder; but have cured it merely by dint of <hi rend="italic">sage-tea,</hi> the beverage of life. it is a polydynamious plant, take my word: tho' your Linnæus would persuade us, it is merely <hi rend="italic">diandrious.</hi>
					 I applaud your industry; it will do you a power of good one way or another, only don't mistake a
						Carabus for an Orchis, nor a Lepisma for an Adenanthera. here is Mr Foljambe has got a <hi rend="italic">Flying</hi> Hobgoblin
					from the E: Indies, &amp; a power of rarities; &amp; then he has given me such a <hi rend="italic">Phalæna</hi>
					 with looking-glasses in its wings; &amp; a Queen of the <hi rend="italic">White Ants,</hi>
					 whose belly alone is as big as many hundred of her subjects, I do not mean their bellies only, but
					their whole persons: and yet her head &amp; her <hi rend="italic">tetons</hi> &amp; her legs are no bigger than other people's. oh, she
					is a jewel of a pismire!</p>
         <p>I hear the triumphs &amp; see the illuminations of Alloa hither, but did Mrs E: lie a night at
					Edinburgh in her way thither? does she meet with no signs of mortality about her castle? are her subjects all civet-cats &amp;
					musk-deer? </p>
         <p>My respects to your Mother. Adieu! I have had an infinite letter from Bonst:n, he goes in October
					to <hi rend="italic">Rocheguion</hi>
					 on the Loire, with the Dutchess d'Enville. the people in several
					provinces are starving to death on the highways. the King (in spite to his parliaments &amp; nation) it is thought, will make the Duke
						d'Aiguillon his chief Minister.</p>
         <closer>
            <dateline>Sept: 14. 1770. </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
