<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (7 September 1757)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Taylor Institution Library</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>St Giles'</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX1 3NA</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>London</settlement>
		                <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
		                <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
		                <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 94-95</idno>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <physDesc>
		                <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
			                  <supportDesc>
				                    <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">200 mm x 160 mm</measure>
				                    </extent>
			                  </supportDesc>
		                </objectDesc>
	              </physDesc>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 249, vol. ii, 525-526
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=249</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXLIX, vol. i, 351-354
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:351</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter LXIV, vol. ii, 289-291
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:289</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter LXXII, vol. iii, 168-170
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:168</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0284">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1757-09-07"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0284">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					       <dateline>Stoke Sept: 7. 1757. </dateline>
					       <salute>Dear Doctr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> I am greatly obliged to your care &amp; kindness for considering with more attention, than it deserves, the article of my
						health. at present I am far better, &amp; take long walks again, have better spirits, &amp; am more
					capable of amusement. the offer you make me of your lodgings for a time I should gladly embrace both for the sake of seeing you, &amp;
					for variety, &amp; because it will answer another end by furnishing me with a reason for not going into the country to <hi rend="italic">a place, where I am invited.</hi>
					 (I think, you understand me) but the truth is, I can not afford to hurry about from place to place;
					so I shall continue, where I am, &amp; trust to <hi rend="italic">illness,</hi> or some other cause for an excuse, since to <hi rend="italic">that place</hi> I am positive, I will not go. it hurts me beyond measure, that I am forced to make these excuses, but go
					I can not, &amp; something must be said. these are cruel things!</p>
				     <p>The family you mention near me are full as civil as ever; Miss Sp: seems to understand; &amp; to all
					such, as do not, she says <hi rend="italic">Φωναντα</hi>
					       <hi rend="italic">συνετοισι</hi>
					 in so many words. and this is both my Motto &amp; Comment. I am afraid, you mistake Mr.
						Roper's complaisance for approbation. Dr. Brown (I hear) says, they
					are the best Odes in our language. Mr. Garrick, the best in ours, <hi rend="italic">or any other.</hi> I should not write this immodest
					panegyrick, did not you guess at the motive of their applause. Ld Lyttelton &amp; Mr Shenstone admire, but wish they were a little clearer. Ld Barrington's explanation, I
					think, I told you before, so will not repeat it. Mr. Fox thinks, if the Bard sung his song but once
					over, King Edward could not possibly understand him. indeed I am of his opinion &amp; am certain, if he had sung it fifty times, it was
					impossible the King should know a jot the more about Edwd the 3d, &amp; Q: Elizabeth, &amp; Spencer, &amp; Milton, &amp;c: Mr Wood (Mr
					Pitt's Wood) is disappointed in his expectations. Dr. Akenside
					criticises opening <hi rend="italic">a source</hi> with <hi rend="italic">a key.</hi>
					 the Critical Review you have seen, or may see. he is in raptures (they say, it is Professor
						Franklin) but mistakes the Æolian lyre for the <hi rend="italic">Harp of Æolus,</hi> &amp; on this
					mistake founds a compliment &amp; a criticism. this is, I think, all I have heard, that signifies.</p>
				     <p>The Encyclopedie, I own, may cloy one, if one sets down to it. but you will own, that out of one
					great good dinner a number of little good dinners may be made, that would not cloy one at all. there is a long article sur <hi rend="italic">le Beau</hi>
					 that for my life I can not understand. several of the geographical articles are carelessly done,
					&amp; some of the antiquities, or ancient history.</p>
				     <p>My best Compliments to Mrs Wharton. I hope the operation going forward on your children will succeed
					to your wishes.</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>Adieu, dear Sr, &amp; believe me ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed>TG:</signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>This letter is <hi rend="italic">to yourself only.</hi> our best Mason I suppose you know is in Town, &amp; <hi rend="italic">in
							waiting.</hi>
						 do you know any thing of St:r? pray desire Mas:n to repeat an epigram to you. </p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
