<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Brown (11 August 1759)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 299*, vol. ii, 634-636
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=299*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter XLVII, 188-192
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1853/1/188</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXCI, vol. ii, 96-99
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/96</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0345">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1759-08-11"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Brown, James, 1709-1784</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0345">
      <body>
         <p>I retract a part of my yesterday's intelligence, having to day had an opportunity of hearing more,
					&amp; from the best hand.</p>
         <p>The merit of Prince Ferdinand's policy &amp; conduct is not a little abated by this account. he had
					made a detachment of 4 or 5000 Men under the Hereditary Prince of Brunswick, wch had got between the
					main French army, &amp; the town of Herwart, where their principal Magazine lay. the fear they were under on that account obliged
					Contades to begin the attack, &amp; he accordingly begun his march at midnight in eight columns. very early in the morning, before the
					Prince had time to make the proper dispositions, they were upon him. he had only his first line formed, when the Battle begun; &amp; of
					that line the English Infantry made a considerable part. Contade's troops (join'd by the Duke of Broglio's Corps) amounted to near four-score thousand: the Prince had only 40 Battalions with him, half of wch only
					engaged (as I said) for want of time. the French Artillery at first did terrible execution, &amp; it was then our four Regiments
					suffer'd so much, 68 of their Officers (all, I think, below a Captain in degree) being kill'd or wounded, 267 private Men kill'd, &amp;
					above 900 wounded. the rest of the line were Hanoverians (who behaved very bravely) &amp; as their number was much greater, it is
					likely they suffer'd still more, but of their loss I have no particular account. in the village of Tonhausen near at hand were all the
					Hessian Artillery, wch, being now turned upon the French, soon silenced their Cannon, &amp; gave an opportunity to come to closer
					engagement. the conflict after this lasted but an hour &amp; quarter; the French made a poor &amp; shameful resistance, &amp; were
					dispersed &amp; routed on all sides. the Marshal himself (having detach'd a body of Men to try, if they could save or burn Herwart)
					retreated along the Weser toward <hi rend="italic">Rintelen &amp; Corvey,</hi> but wrote a letter to the Prince to say, 'that as Minden
					must now soon fall into the hands of his <hi rend="italic">victorious troops</hi> he doubted not, but he would treat the Wounded &amp;
					Sick (who were all lodged there) with his usual humanity.' accordingly he enter'd Minden the next day. 8000 only of ye French were
					slain in the field, 20 pieces of Canon (16 Pounders) taken &amp; 12 Standards. the number of prisoners, &amp; the slaughter in the
					pursuit, not so great as it might have been, for the English Horse (tho' they received orders to move) stir'd not a foot, nor had any
					share in the action. this is unaccountable, but true; &amp; we shall soon hear a greater noise about it. (Ld G: S:)
				</p>
         <p>The Prince of Brunswick fell in with the party sent towards Herwart, entirely routed it, took 5 pieces of Cannon, the Town, &amp; all
					the Magazines. </p>
         <p>The loss of ye Russians is not what has been reported: their march toward Silesia however was
					stop'd, &amp; the King of Prussia is gone in person to attack them.
				</p>
         <p>The story of Durell is all a lye.</p>
         <p>Ld H: is blamed for publishing G:l Yorke's &amp;
						Mitchell's letters so hastily.</p>
         <closer>
            <dateline>Saturday. Aug. 1759.</dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Don't quote me for all this Gazette. the Prussians have had a very considerable advantage over
						Gen: Harsch.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
