<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (22 October 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 150-151</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>3 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">212 mm x 164 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 348, vol. ii, 761-762
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=348</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXXI, vol. ii, 238-240
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900ii/1/238</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CI, vol. ii, 393-395
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/393</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CIX, vol. iii, 289-291
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/289</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0399">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-10-22"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Dugdale, Sir William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Dart, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Ely</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Durham Cathedral</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0399">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Oct: 22. 1761. Southn: Row. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Do not think me very dilatory, for I have been sending away all my things from this house (where nevertheless I shall continue while
					I stay in Town) &amp; have besides been confined with a severe cold to my room. on rummageing Mr Bromwich's &amp; several other shops I am forced to tell you, that there are absolutely no papers at all, that deserve
					the name of Gothick, or that you would bear the sight of. they are all what they call <hi rend="italic">fancy,</hi> &amp; indeed
					resemble nothing that ever was in use in any age or country. I am going to advise, what perhaps you may be deter'd from by the addition
					of expence, but what, in your case I should certainly do. any body that can draw the least in the world is capable of sketching in
					Indian ink a compartment or two of diaper-work, or a nich or tabernacle with its fretwork: take such a Man with you to
					Durham-Cathedral, &amp; let him copy one division of any ornament you think will have any effect, from the high-altar suppose or the
					nine altars, or what you please. if nothing there suits you, chuse in Dart's Canterbury or Dugdale's
						Warwickshire, &amp;c: &amp; send the design hither. they will execute it here, &amp; make a new
					stamp on purpose, provided you will take 20 pieces of it, &amp; it will come to 1/2 or a penny a yard the more (according to the work,
					that is in it). this I really think worth your while. I mention your doing it there, because it will be then under your own eye, &amp;
					at your own choice, &amp; you can proportion the whole better to the dimensions of your room, for if the design be of arcade work, or
					any thing on a pretty large scale, &amp; the arches or niches are to rise one above the other, there must be some contrivance, that
					they may fill the entire space &amp; not be cut in sunder and incompleat .. this indeed, where the work is in small compartments, is
					not to be minded. say therefore, if you come into this; or shall I take a Man here to Westminster, &amp; let him copy some of those
					fretworks? tho' I think, in the books I have named you may find better things. I much doubt of the effect colours (any other than the
					tints of stucco) would have in a gothic design on paper, &amp; here they have  nothing to judge from.
					those I spoke of at Ely were green &amp; pale blue with the raised work white, if you care to hazard it. I saw an all-silver paper
					quite plain, &amp; it look'd like block-tin. in short there is nothing I would venture to send you. One of 3D a yard in small
					compartments thus, might perhaps do for the stairs, but very likely it is common, &amp; besides it is not pure gothick, therefore I
					would not send it alone. Adieu &amp; tell me soon what I shall do.</p>
         <figure>
            <graphic url="/texts/letters/letters.0399.jpg"/>
         </figure>
         <p>I go to Camb: in 3 weeks or less.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
