<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Richard Hurd to Thomas Gray (16 August 1757)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Hartlebury</settlement>
                  <institution key="HARC">Hartlebury Castle</institution>
                  <repository>Hurd Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 245*, vol. ii, 516-518
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=245*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Richard Hurd &amp; William Mason. And letters of Richard Hurd to Thomas Gray.</title> With introduction &amp; notes by the late Ernest Harold Pearce. Ed. with additional notes by Leonard Whibley. Cambridge: University Press, 1932, 36-38
			</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0279">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12417397">Hurd, Richard, 1720-1808</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1757-08-16"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Warburton, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hurd, Dr. Richard</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0279">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute> Dear Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I give you many thanks for the favour of your Odes, which I have received after a tedious expectation. You may be sure the
					title-page amused us a good deal, but M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Brown has explained it. It is not worth
					while to tell you how they are received here. But every body would be thought to admire. 'Tis true, I believe, the greater part don't
					understand them.</p>
         <p> I have been amusing myself in my way, since you left us. The Letter to Mason is printed off, and I
					shall send you a copy very soon to Dodsley's. The dialogues too are all finished after a sort; so that
					I shall have work enough for you against our next meeting in November. I should be better pleased if you would find work for me. And I
					hope you don't forget, among your other amusements this summer, your design for a history of the English poetry. You might be
					regulating your plan, and digesting the materials you have by you. I shall teaze you perpetually, till
					you set about the project in good earnest. It is a wonderful favourite with me, and will, I am certain, in your hands be a work of much
					use as well as elegance.</p>
         <p> Mason has never once writ in all this time, which I take prodigiously ill, and desire you will tell him so. D<hi rend="super">r</hi>
					Warburton sends me word too, he did not keep his appointment with him of going to Durham. So that I can only conclude he is laid up of
					a fit of the Muse, or perhaps is gone to pay a visit to his Druids at Mona.</p>
         <p> If you give me the pleasure of hearing from you, you must write very soon. For I grow sick of this place, and set out on the 29<hi rend="super">th</hi> on my summer rambles. It will be a satisfaction to hear that you are well. I am sollicitous for nothing else. For
					you can never want the best sort of amusements. Once more, let me thank you for the Odes, which I like the better upon every reading.
						M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Nevile too desires me to make his acknowledgments in full form. He is
					mightily flatter'd with the Present you was so kind to make him.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute> I am, Dear Sir<lb/> Your very affectionate humble<lb/> Servant </salute>
            <signed> R. Hurd </signed>
            <dateline>Emman: Coll. 16 Aug. 1757.</dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
