<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Mrs. (Dorothy) Gray (21 June 1739)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 64, vol. i, 112-114
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=64</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter iv, section ii, 50-52
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:50</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XIX, vol. i, 30-32
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:30</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section II, letter IV, vol. ii, 44-46
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:44</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section II, letter IV, vol. ii, 50-53
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843ii:2:50</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter XXII, vol. i, 44-47
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:1:44</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section II, letter IV, vol. i, 177-179
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:177</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0074">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011060">Reims, France</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1739-06-21"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Gray, Mrs. (Dorothy), 1685-1753</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Conway, Henry Seymour, 1721-1795</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Rheims</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">France</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0074">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Rheims, June 21, N.S. 1739.</dateline>
         </opener>
         <p>We have now been settled almost three weeks in this city, which is more considerable upon account of its size and antiquity, than
					from the number of its inhabitants, or any advantages of commerce. There is little in it worth a stranger's curiosity, besides the
					cathedral church, which is a vast Gothic building of a surprising beauty and lightness, all covered over with a profusion of little
					statues, and other ornaments. It is here the Kings of France are crowned by the Archbishop of Rheims, who is the first Peer, and the
					Primate of the kingdom: The holy vessel made use of on that occasion, which contains the oil, is kept in the church of St.
						Nicasius hard by, and is believed to have been brought by an angel from heaven at the coronation of
					Clovis, the first christian king. The streets in general have but a melancholy aspect, the houses all old; the public walks run along
					the side of a great moat under the ramparts, where one hears a continual croaking of frogs; the country round about is one great plain
					covered with vines, which at this time of the year afford no very pleasing prospect, as being not above a foot high. What pleasures the
					place denies to the sight, it makes up to the palate; since you have nothing to drink but the best champaigne in the world, and all
					sort of provisions equally good. As to other pleasures, there is not that freedom of conversation among the people of fashion here,
					that one sees in other parts of France; for though they are not very numerous in this place, and consequently must live a good deal
					together, yet they never come to any great familiarity with one another. As my Lord Conway had spent a good part of his time among
					them, his brother, and we with him, were soon introduced into all their assemblies: As soon as you enter, the lady of the house
					presents each of you a card, and offers you a party at quadrille; you sit down, and play forty deals without intermission, excepting
					one quarter of an hour, when every body rises to eat of what they call the gouter, which supplies the place of our tea, and is a
					service of wine, fruits, cream, sweetmeats, crawfish and cheese. People take what they like, and sit down again to play; after that,
					they make little parties to go to the walks together, and then all the company retire to their separate habitations. Very seldom any
					suppers or dinners are given; and this is the manner they live among one another; not so much out of any aversion they have to
					pleasure, as out of a sort of formality they have contracted by not being much frequented by people who have lived at Paris. It is sure
					they do not hate gaiety any more than the rest of their country-people, and can enter into diversions, that are once proposed, with a
					good grace enough; for instance, the other evening we happened to be got together in a company of eighteen people, men and women of the
					best fashion here, at a garden in the town to walk; when one of the ladies bethought herself of asking, Why should not we sup here?
					Immediately the cloth was laid by the side of a fountain under the trees, and a very elegant supper served up; after which another
					said, Come, let us sing; and directly began herself: From singing we insensibly fell to dancing, and singing in a round; when somebody
					mentioned the violins, and immediately a company of them was ordered: Minuets were begun in the open air, and then came country-dances,
					which held till four o'Clock next morning; at which hour the gayest lady there proposed, that such as were weary should get into their
					coaches, and the rest of them should dance before them with the music in the van; and in this manner we paraded through all the
					principal streets of the city, and waked every body in it. Mr. Walpole had a mind to make a custom of the thing, and would have given a
					ball in the same manner next week, but the women did not come into it; so I believe it will drop, and they will return to their dull
					cards, and usual formalities. We are not to stay above a month longer here, and shall then go to Dijon, the chief city of Burgundy, a
					very splendid and very gay town; at least such is the present design. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
