<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (23 June 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 144-145</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">205 mm x 185 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 336, vol. ii, 740-742
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=336</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXII, vol. ii, 215-218
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:215</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XCVII, vol. ii, 387-388
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:387</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CV, vol. iii, 283-284
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iii:283</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0387">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-06-23"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Ashton, Thomas, 1715-1775</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Brown, James, 1709-1784</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Rousseau, Jean Jacques</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">London</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Eton</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Cambridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0387">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>Dear Doctor </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>When I received your letter I was still detain'd in Town: but am now at last got to Cambridge. I applied immediately to Dr
						Ashton (who was nearest at hand) for information as to the expences of Eton without naming any one's
					name. he returned me the <hi rend="italic">civilest</hi> of answers, &amp; that if the boy was to be on the foundation, I had no more
					to do but send him to him, &amp; the business should be done. as to the charges, he was going to Eton, &amp; would send me an account
					from thence; wch he did accordingly on Sunday last, &amp; here it is inclosed with his second letter.
					you will easily conceive, that there must be additional expences, that can be reduced to no rules, as pocket-money, cloths, books,
					&amp;c: &amp; wch are left to a Father's own discretion.</p>
         <p>My notion is, that your Nephew being an only Son, &amp; rather of a delicate constitution, ought
					not to be exposed to the hardships of the College. I know, that the expence in that way is much lessen'd; but your Brother has but one
					Son, &amp; can afford to breed him an Oppidant. I know, that a Colleger is sooner form'd to scuffle
					in the world, that is, by drubbing &amp; tyranny is made more hardy or more cunning, but these in my eyes are no such desirable
					acquisitions: I know too, that a certain (or very probable) provision for life is a thing to be
					wish'd: but you must remember, what a thing a fellow of King's is. in short you will judge for yourselves. if you accept my <hi rend="italic">good Friend's</hi> offer, I will proceed accordingly: if not, we will thank him, &amp; willingly let him recommend to us
					a cheap boarding-house, not disdaining his protection &amp; encouragement, if it can be of any little use to your Nephew. he has
					married one of Amyand's Sisters with 12,000£: (I suppose, you know her; she is an enchanting
					object!), &amp; he is settled in the Preachership of Lincolns Inn.</p>
         <p>Sure Mr Jon:. or some one has told you, how your <hi rend="italic">good Friend,</hi> Mr. L: has been horsewhip'd, trampled, bruised, &amp; piss'd upon, by a Mrs Mackenzie, a sturdy Scotch Woman. it
					was done in an Inn-yard at Hampstead in the face of day, &amp; he has put her in the Crown-Office. it
					is very true. I will not delay this letter to tell you any more stories.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Adieu! I am ever<lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G: </signed>
            <dateline>Pembroke-Hall. <lb/> June 23. 1761. </dateline>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>Mr. Brown, (the <hi rend="italic">petit bon-homme</hi>) joins his compliments to mine, &amp; presents them to you and Mrs.
						Wharton.</p>
            <p>I have been dreadfully disappointed in Rousseau's Heloïse: but Mason admires it.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
