<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to James Beattie (2 October 1765)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <institution key="UABD">University of Aberdeen Library</institution>
                  <repository>Historic Collections, Special Libraries and Archives, King's College</repository>
                  <collection>AU MS 30, Papers of James Beattie (1735-1803)</collection>
                  <idno>AU MS 30/24/6/2</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                     <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee d.32, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 413, vol. ii, 895-896
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=413</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, letter li, section iv, 318-320
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:1:318</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCLXXVIII, vol. iii, 93-95
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900iii:93</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter CXXII, vol. ii, 458-459
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1816ii:458</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter CXXXIII, vol. iv, 63-65
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1843iv:63</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. in one. London: J. Sharpe, 1819, letter CXXV, vol. ii, 96-98
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1819:2:96</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by Thomas James Mathias. London: William Bulmer, 1814, section IV, letter LI, vol. i, 418-420
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MaW_1814i:418</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0467">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/1100274">Glamis Castle, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1765-10-02"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14766002">Beattie, James, 1735-1803</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7009782">Aberdeen, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Dryden, John</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Scotland</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Glamis</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0467">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To Mr Beattie, Professor in the Marischal-College Aberdeen</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>DUNDEE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Glames-Castle. Oct: 2. 1765.</dateline>
            <salute>Sr </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I must beg you would present my most grateful acknowledgements to your learned Society for the publick mark of their esteem, which
					you say they are disposed to confer on me. I embrace, with so deep &amp; just a sense of their
					goodness the <hi rend="italic">substance</hi> of that honour they do me, that I hope it may plead my pardon with them, if I do not
					accept the <hi rend="italic">form.</hi> I have been, Sr, for several years a Member of the University of Cambridge, &amp; formerly
					(when I had some thoughts of the profession) took a Batchelor of Laws degree there: since that time,
					tho' long qualified by my standing, I have always neglected to finish my course, &amp; claim my Doctor's degree. judge therefore, whether it will not look like a slight &amp; some sort of contempt, if I receive the same
					degree from a Sister-University. I certainly would avoid giving any offence to a set of Men, among whom I have pass'd so many easy,
					&amp; (I may say) happy hours of my life: yet shall ever retain in my memory the obligations You have laid me under, &amp; be proud of
					my connection with the University of Aberdeen.</p>
         <p>It is a pleasure to me to find, that you are not offended with the liberties I took, when you were at Glames. you took me too literally, if you thought I meant in the least to discourage you in your pursuit of Poetry.
					all I intended to say was, that if either Vanity (that is, a general &amp; undistinguishing desire of applause) or Interest, or
					Ambition has any place in the breast of a poet, he stands a great chance in these our days of being severely disappointed: and yet
					after all these passions are suppress'd, there may remain in the mind of one, <hi rend="italic">ingenti perculsus amore</hi>
					 (and such a one I take you to be), incitements of a better sort strong enough to make him write
					verse all his life both for his own pleasure, &amp; that of all posterity.</p>
         <p>I am sorry for the trouble you have had to gratify my curiosity &amp; love of superstition, yet I
					heartily thank you. on Monday, Sr, I set forward on my way to England, where if I can be of any
					little use to you, or should ever have the good fortune to see you it will be a particular satisfaction to me. Ld Strathmore &amp; the
					Family here desire me to make their compliments to You.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am sincerely<lb/> Your Friend &amp; Servant </salute>
            <signed>THO: GRAY. </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>P:S: – Remember Dryden, &amp; be blind to all his faults.
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
