<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (20 July 1761)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 338, vol. ii, 744
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=338</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter LXVIII, 264-265
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:264</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CCXXIV, vol. ii, 219-220
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:219</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0389">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7029839">Aston, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1761-07-20"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="place">Stilton</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Hornby Castle</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Doncaster</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Chatsworth</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Aske Hall</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0389">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Aston July 20th 1761 </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr Gray.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> The Old Man was really dying when I wrote to you from Stilton. But in spite of all his old
					Complaints in spite of an added feaver and fistula, He still holds out, has had strength to undergo two Operations, and is in hopes of
					a perfect recovery. However, if he ever does die I am now secure of succeeding him, &amp; I find the Object of much more importance
					than I at first thought, for one Year with another by fines &amp;c the Preferment is good £230 per Annum:</p>
         <p>The Coronation &amp;c prevents Lady Holdernesse from coming into the North. But I am to meet His Lordship at Doncaster the Day after
					to morrow &amp; proceed with him to Aske &amp; Hornby. He will stay
					in the Country only 8 Weeks, &amp; I shall follow him to Town three Weeks after, as My waiting falls
					in the Coronation month. I wish you would write me an Epithalamic Sermon, It could not fail but get me a Mitre next in goodness to
						Squires.
				</p>
         <p>This letter is merely to tell you My Motions and to beg youll write to me, under His Lordships cover to Aske near Richmond. I was at
					Chatsworth last week, and had the pleasure to find Lord John perfectly recoverd. My Love to Mr
					Brown</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Beleive me Dear Mr Gray <lb/> most cordially yours </salute>
            <signed>W. MASON. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
