<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to Mary Antrobus (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 5 September 1759)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>USA</country>
		                <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
		                <institution key="ROBA">Rosenbach Museum &amp; Library</institution>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
			                  <note>a photostat is in MS. Toynbee c.2, Bodleian Library, Oxford</note>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 301, vol. ii, 638-640
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=301</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0348">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="medium" when="1759-09-05"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29394522">Antrobus, Mary, b. 1732</persName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
			            <p>Gregorian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0348">
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute> Dear Mary </salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p> The Death of the poor Alderman is an event, that you have so long weekly expected, that (tho' it
					may justly afflict his family) yet it could not surprise them.</p>
				     <p> I am sorry to hear of the attempt making to deprive your Mamma of her Office at such a time, &amp; do not understand upon what pretences your enemies should ground such a proceeding,
					when she had so lately too obtain'd a confirmation of it. they charge her to be sure with something; whether justly or unjustly is not
					the Question, but any Friend, who would enter into her cause &amp; justify her effectually, must be acquainted with what is objected,
					&amp; with the reasons she can alledge in her own defence, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> are (I hope) sufficient to set aside the malice of
					these people. M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Shelvocke, if he is continued in his office, seems the first Person to apply to, &amp; (I should
					imagine) you have already done so. tho' I have not seen him for years, I should not scruple speaking to him myself, but that you have
					not furnish'd me with any thing to say; &amp; (if he should not be a friend to our cause, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> is a thing I do not
					know) I might perhaps do more hurt than good by interposing. neither of the Post-Masters are (as you suppose) related to M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Pitt: one is the Earl of Bessborough, &amp;
					the other M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Trevor-Hambden. what I could, I have done: by this night's post I
					have wrote to L<hi rend="super">d</hi> John Cavendish, who is Brother to L<hi rend="super">d</hi> Bessborough, to desire he would write, or speak a word in behalf of your Mamma: but he is as far off as
					Chatsworth in Derbyshire, &amp; besides (tho' I believe inclined enough to oblige me) naturally very shy &amp; backward in asking any
					thing even from his nearest Relations. therefore I can by no means promise myself success, &amp; especially if the case should be (what
					I once told you I was afraid of) that M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> A:<hi rend="super">s</hi> should have
					trusted your Gr: Papa with any money belonging to the Office, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> may be now suddenly demanded of her, w<hi rend="super">ch</hi> I should be extremely sorry for.</p>
				     <p>If there is any thing else I can do, inform me; but my connection with People in power is very small, &amp; that little I have never
					employed in asking favours at their hands, even for myself. I do not recollect any body, that I know, who has any interest in M<hi rend="super">r</hi> Trevor: he is Uncle to the Dutchess of Marlb'rough, if your Mamma knows any
					means of applying to her.</p>
				     <p> My Service to M<hi rend="super">rs</hi> Antrobus. I do not at all expect, she should write herself at such a time, &amp; think you
					may very well be her scribe. </p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute> Adieu, I am<lb/> Yours </salute>
					       <signed> TG. </signed>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p> Love to Dolly . . . pray, may I communicate with Powdish on this subject for any information, or
						is it better not? I am not at all well, &amp; have a sort of fever: they tell me I am going to have a Jaundice.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
