<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to William Mason (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 28 November 1758)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 284*, vol. ii, 597-599
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=284*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, 61-66
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:61</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Essays and Criticisms by Thomas Gray.</title> Ed. with Introduction and Notes by Clark Sutherland Northup. Boston and London: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1911, letter excerpt, 214-215
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=NoC_1911:214</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, fragment, letter no. CLXXX, vol. ii, 65
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900ii:65</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0329">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011896">Stoke Poges, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1758-11-28"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Hurd, Richard, 1720-1808</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="person">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Hurd, Dr. Richard</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="literature">Akenside, Dr. Mark</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0329">
      <body>
         <p>[           ]</p>
         <p>Ode. P: 32<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">Whom</hi> Camber bore. I suppose you say <hi rend="italic">whom,</hi> because the Harp is treated as a Person, but
					there is an ambiguity in it, &amp; I should read <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Camber bore. there's a Specimen of nice Criticism for you!
					I much approve the six last lines of this Stanza. it is a noble Image &amp; well express'd to the fancy &amp; to the ear. </p>
         <p>I. 2.<lb/>
            <lb/>A <hi rend="italic">Rill</hi> has no <hi rend="italic">tide</hi> of waters to <hi rend="italic">tumble</hi> down <hi rend="italic">amain.</hi> I am sorry to observe this just in a place, where I see the difficulty of rhiming. I object nothing to the
					symphony of Ring-doves &amp; Poplars, but that it is an Idea borrow'd from yourself, &amp; I would not have you seem to repeat your own
					inventions.</p>
         <p>I conceive the four last lines to be allegorical, alluding to the brutal ferocity of the Natives, wch by the power of musick was
					soften'd into civility. it should not therefore be the <hi rend="italic">Wolf-Dog,</hi> but the <hi rend="italic">Wolf</hi> itself,
					that <hi rend="italic">bays</hi> the trembling Moon: it is the Wolf, that thins the flocks, &amp; not the Dog, who is their
					Guardian.</p>
         <p>I. 3.<lb/>
            <lb/>I read <hi rend="italic">the Fairy, Fancy.</hi> I like all this extremely, &amp; particularly the ample plumes of Inspiration,
					that</p>
         <p>Beat on the breathless bosom of the air yet, if I were foolish, I could find fault with this verse, as others will do. but what I do
					not conceive is, how such wings as those of Inspiration should be mistaken for the wings of Sleep, who (as you yourself tell me
					presently) <hi rend="italic">sinks softly</hi> down the skies. besides it is not <hi rend="italic">her</hi> is false English: the
					nomin:ve Case is <hi rend="italic">She.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>II. 3.<lb/>
            <lb/>Does the swart-star (that is, Sirius) shine from the North? I believe not, but Dr Long will tell
						you.
				</p>
         <p>II. 1. &amp; 2.<lb/>
            <lb/>These are my favourite Stanzas. I am satisfied both mind &amp; ear, &amp; dare not murmur. if Mador would sing as well in the
					first Chorus, I should cease to plague you. only, <hi rend="italic">Rise at her art's command</hi> is harsh, &amp; says no more
					than</p>
         <q>
            <p>Arise at her command, </p>
         </q>
         <p>or </p>
         <q>
            <p>Are born at her command. II. 3.</p>
         </q>
         <p>I told you of ye <hi rend="italic">swart Star</hi> before. at the end I read <q>
               <p>Till Destiny prepare a shrine of purer clay.</p>
            </q> Afterwards read <hi rend="italic">resume no</hi> more thy strain. You will say I have no notion of Tout-ensembles, if I do not tell you that I like the scheme of this Ode at least as well as the execution.</p>
         <p>And now I rejoice with you in the recovery of your eyes. pray, learn their value, &amp; be sparing
					of them. I shall leave this place in about a fortnight, &amp; within that time hope to dispatch you a
					packet with my <hi rend="italic">criticalities</hi> entire: I send this bit first, because you desire
						it. Dr Wharton is in great hopes, Mr H: will not treat Dr Ak: so hardly as he intended &amp; desires you would tell him so. as his
					request is founded on mere humanity (for he pretends no friendship, &amp; has but a slight acquaintance with the Doctor) I present it
					to you, &amp; wish you would acquaint Mr H: with it, the sooner the better.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am well &amp; stupid, but ever unalterably <lb/> Yours </salute>
            <signed>TG: </signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I don't understand, if Fraser is recover'd. I wish, he was. Do you know any thing of
							Stonhewer?
					</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
