<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>William Mason to Thomas Gray (10 September 1755)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <settlement>New York, NY</settlement>
                  <institution key="NYPL">New York Public Library</institution>
                  <repository>Humanities and Social Sciences Library</repository>
                  <collection>Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</collection>
               </msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 206, vol. i, 438-440
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=206</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Thomas Gray and William Mason, with Letters to the Rev. James Brown, D.D.</title> Ed. by the Rev. John Mitford. London: Richard Bentley, 1853, letter X, 35-37
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=MiJ_1853:35</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CXXIV, vol. i, 276-279
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:276</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0237">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95718679">Mason, William, 1724-1797</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011676">Royal Tunbridge Wells, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1755-09-10"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="literature">Mason, William, 1724-1797</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Tunbridge</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0237">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Tunbridge Sept 10th 55. </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr Gray </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I promisd to write to you from Tunbridge And now I perform it. You can't imagine how much people lye with one another here. I had the
					narrowest escape in the world. The Countess of Schoonfeld lay with evry body and she was but just
					gone when I came hither. However since I came We have sent Miss Ash to Town with Child some people
					say twas Count Bryll that did it But I say nothing, I had been here two days before she went; thats
					all. Lady Caroline who corresponds with her evry post, tells it publickly on the pantiles, then
					Ladies are surprizd. &amp; She crys out "Lord how can ye I wonder she is not with Child evry year." Heres a Mons de St Simon here, much laid with also. but The property of one Lady only who as Sr John Falstaffe says makes him "her
					Philosophers two stones". You cant conceive how she pillages him. Sometimes they take their pastime
					in the midst of a Curricle sometimes in a feild sometimes at his Lodgings &amp; where not? Lady Rotchfort has been here three Days with Lady H A delightful Character! so full of
					the Rheumatics and Achs &amp; Pains all over and then so Genède you know &amp; so detesting of Public places, because People dont dress
					so strangely as they did four year ago, and are not frightful enough to make one Laugh.–I was told yesterday by Lady H that it
					was her Birthday and she wondered I had not writ her some Verses. so I did, &amp; here they are.
				</p>
         <q>
            <p>Had R–d bad my muse essay<lb/> To hail her, on her natal day <lb/> I soon had Ransackd
						Natures bowers <lb/> For Blushing fruit &amp; fragrant flowrs <lb/> And sworn till Fops believd it true <lb/> That all their
						sweetness all their hue <lb/> Were nought to what her cheekes advance <lb/> Adornd tout alamode de France </p>
            <p>Or had gay Lady C***
						<lb/> Been bent on such an odd design, <lb/> And deignd my verses to receive, <lb/> (For Verse is all I have to give) <lb/> It
						soon had been my tuneful prayr <lb/> To beg propitious Fate to spare <lb/> The Bliss she has, &amp; alway lend <lb/> An easy Lord
						and genrous friend. </p>
            <p>But how to suit my song to you <lb/> Is mighty hard, for entre nous <lb/> You're most unfashionably fair, <lb/> Content with your
						own face &amp; air, <lb/> And more unfashionably true, <lb/> A Husband bounds your utmost view. </p>
            <p>This then the Case, my Rhymes I'll close, <lb/> And wish in verse as plain as prose, <lb/> That Tunbridge from her springs may
						grant <lb/> The little added health you want; <lb/> And that for many a happy year <lb/> You need not to her fount repair, <lb/>
						Unless to see as now you see <lb/> Each varied form of vanity, <lb/> And candid laugh, as now you do, <lb/> At all the fools her
						walks can shew. </p>
            <p>Yet one wish more – May Fortune kind <lb/> Soon briskly blow a North-east wind;
						<lb/> And then some few days past &amp; gone <lb/> Youll scarce pull Coifs for St Simon.
					</p>
         </q>
         <p>You must observe this is not the St Simon mentioned in a Book you have formerly read calld the Testament, But another quite of a
					different family and whose name is pronounced Sĕnsĭmmong like a Dactyle. Well, how do you like my
					Verses? Whether shall I call them, To Lady H on her Birthday; or a Lampoon on Lady R &amp; Lady C? one talks of nothing but Lampoons
					here, pray unde derivatur Lampoon? You have a pretty knack at an oldfashioned Welch Ode, but you are nothing like me at an Impromptu. If you write to me Direct to The young Man that my Aunt Dent
					had like to have ravishd. Axton writ to me yesterday about his fellowship. twas rather a
					sesquipedalian Letter; however I answerd it today, &amp; hopd he would behave gratefully to Mr Brown who I sayd was much his friend,
					&amp; would secure him his fellowship.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>and so having concluded my Paper I am yours </salute>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
