<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Gray to Thomas Wharton (28 June 1753)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>UK</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution key="BLUK">British Library</institution>
                  <collection>Manuscripts collection</collection>
                  <idno>Egerton MS 2400, ff. 52-53</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="A.L.S.">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>2 pages
					<measure type="size" unit="mm">201 mm x 161 mm</measure>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>The original letter is extant and usually available for academic research purposes</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 177, vol. i, 376-378
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=177</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. CIV, vol. i, 232-233
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/ToD_1900i/1/232</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 2 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: J. Mawman, 1816, section IV, letter XXXVIII, vol. ii, 236-237
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1816ii/1/236</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>, 5 vols. Ed. by John Mitford. London: W. Pickering, 1835-1843, section IV, letter XLV, vol. iii, 108-110
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/diglib/primary/MiJ_1843iii/1/108</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/texts/letters/tgal0206">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7010874">Cambridge, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="high" when="1753-06-28"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high">Wharton, Thomas, 1717-1794</persName>
               <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7008127">Durham, United Kingdom</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <classCode scheme="TGA">
               <mentioned n="person">Stonhewer, Richard, 1728-1809</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">York</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Burleigh House</mentioned>
               <mentioned n="place">Belvoir Castle</mentioned>
            </classCode>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0206">
      <front>
         <p>
            <address>
               <addrLine>To</addrLine>
               <addrLine>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> Thomas Wharton, MD,</addrLine>
               <addrLine>at</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Durham</addrLine>
               <addrLine>By Caxton</addrLine>
            </address>
            <stamp type="postmark">
               <placeName>CAMBRIDGE</placeName>
            </stamp>
         </p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Camb: June 28 .. 1753.<lb/>Thursday.</dateline>
            <salute>My dear Doctor</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> You may well suppose me no longer here, as I have neglected thus long to answer two very kind letters, &amp; (wch is more) to
					congratulate you on what most of your friends regard as a very happy event: but to me, I own, it has another face, as I have a much
					greater regard for you than for the young Gentleman, whom I never saw; &amp; foresee, that from this time you will never part with your
					bottle, wch is properly the father of this boy. all my rhetorick will be thrown away, the Gout may
					groan at you, &amp; brandish its crutches, the Stone rattle, &amp; the Palsy shake its head unheeded. we shall be no match for Claret,
					if it can get an heir, as well as carry an election. now I talk of elections, we have a report here that your friend Mr V: (I mean Ld
						Barnard) means to bring in his Son-in-law at Durham. is this true?
					H: Vane sets out for the North on Saturday, so I suppose the Bishop's entry will be over next week. and next Monday fortnight I hope to set out myself with Stonhewer, who is going down to his
						fathers, in a Post-chaise. we shall not come very fast, as I propose to see Burleigh, Bevoir-Castle, &amp;c: by the way. but I shall write again before I come,
					to tell you exactly what day we shall be at York. if the time does not suit you, you will inform me as soon as possible. I did not run
					away from his Grace, but follow'd your advice, had a very affectionate squeeze by the hand, &amp; a
					fine Complement in a corner. many people here have been curious to know what it was; but I have kept my own secret, for indeed I do not
					know myself: only I remember it felt warm, &amp; sweated a little. Adieu! you will not fail to
					present my Complements to Mrs Wharton. if she drank as much Claret, as you have done, we shall have the Boy <hi rend="italic">stand</hi> for the County, as soon as he can walk alone. Mr Brown (I believe) will be engaged here with Plummer greatest part of the Summer: [he and Tuthill] desire to be remember'd to
					you both.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am ever<lb/> Truly Yours </salute>
            <signed>T G. </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
