<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>J. Butler to Thomas Gray (<hi rend="it">c.</hi> 2 December 1757)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
	</msIdentifier>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is unlocated, a copy, transcription, or published version survives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 256*, vol. ii, 540-541
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=256*</ref>
                     </bibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray. To which are prefixed Memoirs of his Life and Writings by W[illiam]. Mason.</title> York: printed by A. Ward; and sold by J. Dodsley, London; and J. Todd, York, 1775, imitations, variations, and additional notes, 93-94
				<ref type="url">https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=1775:2:93</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="https://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0292">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName cert="high">Butler, J., Mr</persName>
               <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011400">Andover, United Kingdom</placeName>
               <date cert="medium" when="1757-12-02"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
            <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018834">
               <p>Gregorian</p>
            </calendar>
         </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
            <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0292">
      <body>
         <p>[           ]</p>
         <p>This abrupt execution plunges the reader into that sudden fearful perplexity which is designed to predominate through the whole. the
					irresistible violence of the prophet's passions bears him away, who, as he is unprepared by a formal ushering in of the speaker, is
					unfortified against the impressions of his poetical phrenzy and overpowered by them, as sudden thunders strike the deepest.
				</p>
         <p>[           ]</p>
         <p>Here a vision of triumphant revenge is judiciously made to ensue, after the pathetic lamentation which precedes it. Breaks –
					double rhymes – an appropriated cadence – and an exalted ferocity of language forcibly picture to us the uncontroulable
					tumultuous workings of the prophet's stimulated bosom.
				</p>
         <p>[           ] </p>
         <p>Can there be an image more just, apposite, and nobly imagined than this tremendous tragical winding-sheet? In the rest of this stanza
					the wilderness of thought, expression, and cadence are admirably adapted to the character and situation of the speaker, and of the
					bloody spectres his assistants. It is not indeed peculiar to it alone, but a beauty that runs throughout the whole composition, that
					the historical events are briefly sketched out by a few striking circumstances, in which the Poet's office of rather exciting and
					directing, than satisfying the reader's imagination, is perfectly observed. Such abrupt hints, resembling the several fragments of a
					vast ruin, suffer not the mind to be raised to the utmost pitch, by one image of horror, but that instantaneously a second and a third
					are presented to it, and the affection is still uniformly supported.
				</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
