<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
			   <fileDesc>
				     <titleStmt>
					       <title>Thomas Gray to John Chute (7 September 1741)</title>
				        <respStmt>
	              <name ref="#AH">Alexander Huber</name>
	              <resp>Editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
				     <publicationStmt>
	           <publisher>Thomas Gray Archive</publisher>
	           <address>
		             <addrLine>Bodleian Libraries</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney One Bldg.</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Osney Mead</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>Oxford OX2 0EW</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>UK</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>info@thomasgray.org</addrLine>
		             <addrLine>http://www.thomasgray.org/</addrLine>
	           </address>
	           <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
	           <availability status="restricted">
		             <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.</p>
	           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
				     <sourceDesc>
					       <msDesc>
	              <msIdentifier>
		                <country>UK</country>
		                <settlement>Sherborne St John</settlement>
		                <institution key="VYNE">The Vyne</institution>
		                <collection>Chute of The Vyne, Sherborne St John</collection>
	              </msIdentifier>
	              <additional>
		                <adminInfo>
			                  <availability status="unknown">
                        <p>The original letter is extant, but there is no further information about its availability</p>
                     </availability>
		                </adminInfo>
		                <listBibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Correspondence of Thomas Gray</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by the late Paget Toynbee and Leonard Whibley, with corrections and additions by H. W. Starr. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971 [1st ed. 1935], letter no. 99, vol. i, 184-187
				<ref type="url">http://www.e-enlightenment.com/search/letters/print/?printref_sourceedition=graythOU0084&amp;printref_docnumber=99</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>A History of the Vyne in Hampshire.</title> By Chaloner William Chute. Winchester: Jacob &amp; Johnson, 1888, 86-89
			</bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>The Letters of Thomas Gray, including the correspondence of Gray and Mason</title>, 3 vols. Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. London: George Bell and Sons, 1900-12, letter no. XLIX, vol. i, 90-93
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1900i:90</ref>
			                  </bibl>
			                  <bibl>
                        <title>Gray and his Friends: Letters and Relics, in great part hitherto unpublished.</title> Ed. by Duncan C. Tovey. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1890, section III, letter no. 1, 176-179
				<ref type="url">http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/view.cgi?collection=primary&amp;sequence=ToD_1890:176</ref>
			                  </bibl>
		                </listBibl>
	              </additional>
            </msDesc>
				     </sourceDesc>
			   </fileDesc>
			   <profileDesc> 
         <correspDesc ref="http://www.thomasgray.org/cgi-bin/display.cgi?text=tgal0114">
		          <correspAction type="sent">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9889965">Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771</persName>
			            <placeName cert="high" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7011781">London, United Kingdom</placeName>
			            <date cert="high" when="1741-09-07"/>
		          </correspAction>
		          <correspAction type="received">
			            <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/6079515">Chute, John, 1701-1776</persName>
			            <placeName cert="unknown" ref="http://vocab.getty.edu/tgn/7000457">Florence, Italy</placeName>
		          </correspAction>
	        </correspDesc>
         <calendarDesc>
		          <calendar target="https://lccn.loc.gov/sh85018840">
			            <p>Julian</p>
		          </calendar>
	        </calendarDesc>
         <langUsage>
			         <language ident="eng">English</language>
		       </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
	        <projectDesc>
	           <p>This letter is part of the Primary Texts section of the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
	           <p>XML created for the Thomas Gray Archive.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
	           <p>This letter is part of the correspondence calendar of the complete correspondence of Thomas Gray. The calendar contains detailed bibliographic records for all known original, copied, or published letters written by or to the poet as well as the full-text, where available.  Each record is accompanied by digitised images of the manuscript, where available, or digitised images of the first printed edition.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
	           <taxonomy>
               <bibl>Library of Congress Name Authority File (<abbr>LCNAF</abbr>)</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
		<text type="letter" xml:id="tgal0114">
      <front>
		       <p>
			         <address>
				           <addrLine>A</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Mons:r Monsieur Chute,</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>Gentilhomme Anglois chez Mons:r Ubaldini</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>nel Corso de' Tintori</addrLine>
				           <addrLine>à Florence.</addrLine>
			         </address>
		       </p>
      </front>
			   <body>
				     <opener>
					
					
					       <salute>My Dear Sr</salute>
				     </opener>
				     <p>I complain no more. You have not forgot me. Mrs Dick, to whom I resorted for a Dish of Coffee, instead thereof produced unto me from
					between her fat Breasts your kind Letter, big with another no less kind from our poor mangled Friend
					to whom I now address myself (you don't take it ill) &amp; let him know, that as soon as I got hither, I took wing for the Strand to
					see a certain Acquaintance of his (for I then knew not whether he were dead, or alive) &amp; get some
					News of him. I was so struck with the great resemblance between them, that it made me cry out. he is a
					true Eagle, but a little tamer, &amp; a little fatter than the Eagle Resident: I told him so, but he did not seem to think it so great
					a Compliment, as I did. his Wife had miscarried but was quite well again; his house half pulled down,
					but riseing again more magnificent from its Ruins. he received me, as became a Bird of his Race, &amp; suffer'd himself to be caressed
					without giveing me one Peck, or Scratch. the only bad thing I know of him, is, that he wears a Frock, &amp; a Bob-Wigg. may I charge
					you, my dear Mr Chute (I give you your great Name for want of a little tiny one) with my Compliments to Dr Cocchi, Benevoli (tho' I hate him) &amp; their Patient. particularly to this last
					for recovering so soon, &amp; so much to my Satisfaction. I think one may call him dear Creature, &amp; be fond in Security under the
					Sanction of your Cover. I carried his Mus:m Flor:m to Commissioner Haddock, who is Liddel's Uncle. that Gentleman had left Paris, haveing been elected
					for some place in this Parliament, &amp; (tho' it is like to be controverted) took that opportunity to return to England for a time,
					but is now gone, I think to Spaw. Adieu! Mr M: [...]
				</p>
				     <p>Nunc ad te totum me converto, suavissime Chutî! whom I wrote to from Dover. if this be London, Lord
					send me to Constantinople. either I, or it are extremely odd. the Boys laugh at the depth of my Ruffles, the immensity of my Bagg,
					&amp; the length of my Sword. I am as an Alien in my native land, yea! I am as an Owl among the small birds. it rains, every body is
					discontented, &amp; so am I. you can't imagine how mortifieing it is to fall into the hands of an English Barber. Lord, how You or
					Polleri would storm in such a Case. don't think of comeing hither without Lavaur, or something
					equivalent to him (not an elephant). the Natives are alive, &amp; flourishing. the fashion is a grey
					frock with round Sleeves, Bob-wig, or a Spencer, plain Hat with enormous Brims, &amp; shallow Crown, cock'd as bluff, as possible,
					Muslin-Neckcloth twisted round, rumpled, &amp; tuck'd into the breast; all this with a certain Safaring Air, as if they were just come back from Cartagena. if my pockets had any thing in them, I should
					be afraid of every body I met. look in their face, they knock you down; speak to them, they bite off your Nose. I am no longer ashamed
					in publick, but extremely afraid. if ever they catch me among 'em, I give them leave to eat me. so much for dress, as to Politicks,
					every body is extreme angry with all that has been, or shall be done: even a Victory at this time would be look'd upon as a wicked
					attempt to please the Nation. the Theatres open not till tomorrow, so you will excuse my giveing no account of them tonight. now I have
					been at home, &amp; seen how things go there, would I were with you again, that the Remainder of my Dream might at least be agreeable.
					as it is, my prospect can not well be more unpleasing; but why do I trouble your Goodnature with such considerations? be assured, that
					when I am happy (if that can ever be) your Esteem will greatly add to that happiness, &amp; when most the contrary, will always
					alleviate, what I suffer. many, many thanks for your kindness; for your travels, for your News, for all the trouble I have given, &amp;
					must give you. omit nothing, when you write, for things that were quite indifferent to me at Florence, at this distance become
					interesting. humble Service to Polleri; obliged for his harmonious Salutation, I hope to see some Scratches with his black Claw in your
					next. Adieu!</p>
				     <closer>
					       <salute>I am most sincerely, &amp; ever Your's</salute>
					       <signed>T G: </signed>
					       <dateline>London–Sept: 7: O:S:</dateline>
				     </closer>
				     <postscript>
					       <p>P:S: Nobody is come from Paris yet.</p>
				     </postscript>
			   </body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
